<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Andy McKay</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/blog/andy" rel="alternate"></link>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/blog/rss/latest/andy/" rel="self"></link>
<updated>2025-02-03T00:13:42+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/blog/andy</id>
<author>
<name>Andy McKay</name>
<email>andy@clearwind.ca</email>
</author>

<entry>
<title>A salute for Elon</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2025-02-02-a-salute-for-elon/"/>
<updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/a-salute-for-elon</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;tl:dr; We sold our Tesla because we can no longer be associated in any way with Elon Musk or his companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/tesla-salute.jpg&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got our model 3 in 2018, which meant we were amongst the first in BC. At the time I loved it, the car was absolute night and day from any other car. I said so in an old &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2018-07-25-tesla/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; where I called it “Amazeballs” and also regrettably this about Elon “This is a man on a mission to do good.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have no problem with buying that car - at the time it was the best electric car on the market. It had the best battery and range and great software. It got updated regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanical and design problems abounded in the car that emerged over time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The heating broke and we couldn’t defrost.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Both horns weren’t actually connected in the factory, so the horn was super quiet.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moisture built up in the rear light blocks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The trunk leaked, when it rained we’d have to sponge out inches of water from the trunk.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The car would freeze into a lump and you couldn’t get into the car due to the handle and window design.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software would update &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2022-01-08-how-tesla-is-trying-to-kill-you/&quot;&gt;moving or hiding key functionality&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of 2025 it was clear where Elon was heading and I was starting to look into selling the car. He’d already destroyed Twitter, a place where I had an account for 16 years. He’d repeatedly done so many terrible things in Tesla with the treatment of the workforce, safety rules, and so on. Then the support for Trump came along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The line was crossed with the Nazi salute. Apologists keep arguing it isn’t, but in the context of how he behaves like supporting Tommy Robinson, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2024/dec/28/elon-musk-germany-afd-party&quot;&gt;the AfD editorial&lt;/a&gt;, appearing at an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2025/01/27/nx-s1-5276084/elon-musk-german-far-right-afd-holocaust&quot;&gt;AfD rally and saying that&lt;/a&gt; “frankly too much of a focus on past guilt and we need to move beyond that” it’s clear where his political views lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NjWl_RNDMSA&quot;&gt;Led by Donkeys sum it up well in this video&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/heiltesla-1024x576-1398596338.jpg&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He’s part of an administration that has belittled and attacked Canada. They want to turn Canada into a state through “economic force” and have pushed tariffs onto their biggest ally. He isn’t just donating money and sitting on the sideline, &lt;strong&gt;he’s an active participant&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point my car is over 6.5 years old, the money already went to Tesla. Tesla’s board is trying to pay &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/roberthart/2024/06/13/heres-whats-next-after-musk-claims-tesla-shareholders-approve-massive-pay-package/&quot;&gt;Musk $50 billion dollars&lt;/a&gt;. But every repair, every time I use a super charger, that money goes to Tesla and a bit to Musk. Just driving around in a Tesla associates me with that person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we took a loss, sold the car and bought a Kia EV6. Very happy with it so far. Is Kia perfect? No, no  large car company is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tesla sent a survey after we sold it, when they asked why I bought a Kia I replied simply “The company isn’t run by a Nazi”.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Phone plans in Canada</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2025-01-06-changing-phone-plans/"/>
<updated>2025-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/changing-phone-plans</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you aren’t in a phone contract, you should look at changing phone companies every year or so. Otherwise, you’ll just be getting screwed by Canadian phone companies that are not going to improve your plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s easy to switch phone companies, keep your existing phone number and it’s the only way to get a better deal.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-it-works&quot;&gt;How it works&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the big pre-paid companies are really backed by the major networks. Koodo and Public Mobile uses Telus networks. Fido uses Rogers. These companies are the ones that offer cheaper pre-paid plans and are the way to go if you don’t want to get tied into a contract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember contracts are one-sided and designed to screw you anyway, for example: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/toronto/rogers-bell-telus-contracts-prices-1.7369942&quot;&gt;they can go up in price&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These companies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use the major networks, so you get the same phone, internet coverage as the backing network.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can be serviced by the backing networks. For example: when I had Fido problems, I went to the Rogers store and got it fixed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phone companies are NOT like Netflix who (as of writing) have 3 plans that are clear, stay consistent and are easy to follow &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.netflix.com/en/node/24926&quot;&gt;on one page&lt;/a&gt; and you can change between them as you need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phone companies are NOT like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The create and remove plans continually.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They choose&lt;/strong&gt; who gets what plan when.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is done to make it really hard to compare plans, make it possible to target particular users and to tie people into expensive plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-story&quot;&gt;My Story&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;koodo-telus&quot;&gt;Koodo (Telus)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was on Koodo forever. It worked, it had enough data and I didn’t worry about it worked. In the summer I re-evaluated all my plans and subscriptions and found that I’d been on Koodo so long, I wasn’t even valid in their system anymore, it had been updated multiple times and they hadn’t updated my account (something something software developers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That took a few weeks to resolve and then I was able to see the deal wasn’t that great and that better deals were available elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key point: &lt;strong&gt;In the many years with Koodo, they had never upgraded, updated or improved my account. They just left me on the same plan for all those years.&lt;/strong&gt; That’s not a good way to retain customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Annoyed by their attitude I switched to Fido.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fido-rogers&quot;&gt;Fido (Rogers)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September I switched to Fido. The result was more data and free UK calling for about $15 a month less. When you switch you can keep your phone number and use an eSIM to move over. The eSIM didn’t work first time, but the Rogers store fixed that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a couple of months my family in the UK told me it was easier to call on WhatsApp than a phone. So I didn’t need UK minutes anymore. No problem, I’ll switch to the cheaper plan that was advertised when I joined up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That plan doesn’t exist. I can’t switch to it, even though my wife is on it. Fido won’t let me. I contacted customer support and they said &lt;strong&gt;“We think you are on a good plan and should be happy it.”&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was not happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;public-mobile-telus&quot;&gt;Public Mobile (Telus)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the holidays I switched to Public Mobile. This was done in 20 minutes while watching something on YouTube. The eSIM worked first time and the number transferred. My monthly rate went down another $15 or so a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m now getting more data than with Koodo or Fido, and paying 1/3 of what I was paying with Koodo in the summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the process, I’ve had one problem, resolved by the Rogers store in 5 minutes. I’ve kept my phone number and not had to change it. I will probably review my plan regularly. Apparently the best time to switch is August and September in the “back to school period”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summary: &lt;strong&gt;You should change companies, they are relying on you not switching to make more money.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Cinque Terre</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-12-04-cinque/"/>
<updated>2024-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/cinque</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cinque_Terre&quot;&gt;Cinque Terre&lt;/a&gt; is a series of five villages on the north western Italian coastline. The best way to visit the villages is to take the train that connects La Spezia and Genoa. The best way to get between the villages is to hike them (or take the train).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November, I was able to hike between all five villages. Apparently the trails can often be closed and due to a rainstorm a few days early, the easiest path between the last two villages Manarola and Riomaggiore was closed. This last part “Via dell’Amore” has been closed since 2019 and was re-opened briefly in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To hike the paths in Cinque Terre &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cinqueterre.eu.com/en/cinque-terre-card#cinque-terre-trekking-card&quot;&gt;you will need a trekking card&lt;/a&gt;. When I hiked there was only one checkpoint on the whole trail, I’m sure there are more during the summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;12798154588&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot; data-from-embed=&quot;false&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started off at the North West end in Monterosso, myself hiking and my wife taking the train. We were able to meet up at one village in the middle and at the end. We were both able to move at the pace we wanted to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first I thought I’d try running this route, but this quickly became an idea I abandoned. The first section between Monterosso and Vernazza was the busiest part of the route. It was full of people moving at their pace. The route is very narrow with no passing places in many areas. It’s also lots of elevation change and lots and lots of steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Vernazza there were a lot less people, which was great. At this point the November Italian sun was starting to beat down on me. Pleasant, but still fun. At Corniglia, the trail goes right past a church and a water fountain which was lovely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corniglia to Manarola is the longest part of the trail with a big assent out of Corniglia, a lovely flat part and then a very long descent down into Manarola. All the ascents and descents are stairs, so many stairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Manarola I went over to the Via dell’Amore to find it closed. So backtracked and took the old path over the hill. This is the steepest ascent, a view at the top and then a steep descent. We were rewarded with an amazing sunset in Riomaggiore and then some Italian gelato.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Views all along the trail were absolutely breath taking. Just beautiful views of villages, the sea, hills. You walk along terraces through vineyards, through forests, past houses and then pop out into amazing villages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recommended, but expect it to be busy at the height of the season for a lot of it and expect a lot of sun.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Another Tent</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-09-06-another-tent/"/>
<updated>2024-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/another-tent</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago I &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2022-04-04-a-tent/&quot;&gt;got a tent&lt;/a&gt;. It had its problems and I needed another one. There were some problems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s not as easy to setup as I thought.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s not freestanding.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It doesn’t cope well with wind.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It sometimes doesn’t cope well with humid climates, like this one.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Using hiking poles for the tent poles isn’t as good as an idea as I thought.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wind can be a problem, in wind and rain it could be really bad. In windy places, I found the tent is like a big wind sock especially when it hits the side of the tent. This is due to having a pole at each end and no rigidity in-between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being held up by hiking poles wasn’t the weight or space saving I thought it would be. Long thin poles are easy to put anywhere. They don’t weigh much (200g). Being able to use poles for a day hike and leave your tent up is quite useful. Also, losing or breaking a pole hiking now has bad consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deal breaker is not being freestanding. The tent requires well anchored tent pegs at the front and back to provide tension for the poles to stay up. This makes it hard to put up and won’t stay up well in: sand (beaches on the West Coast Trail), places with wooden pads (Garibaldi, Manning), mountain tops with no soil (Seymour, Golden Ears). Places I wanted to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So time for another tent. Enter the Big Agnes 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bigagnes.com/collections/ultralight-tents/products/fly-creek-hv-ul1-solution-dye&quot;&gt;Fly Creek HV UL1 tent&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tent is great for three seasons, easier to put up, light weight and more rigid and able to cope with the wind and semi freestanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s semi freestanding because the fly requires pegs to hold away from the main, but that’s pretty common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes it is 200g or so heavier than my Tarp Tent, which sucks, but being able to go to toilet without it falling down is a huge win for me. This happened to me on the West Coast Trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/big-agnes.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far I’m extremely happy with this tent, in Garibaldi with some strong gusts of wind, it was nice and solid. In wet weather at Elsay Lake it was fine. It’s well designed and thought out. Really can’t spot any problems with yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s actually smaller than the Tarp Tent and that’s good, it’s easier to pitch. It fits me and my sleeping pad and gear just fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big 👍 from me, so far.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Elsay Lake</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-09-05-elsay-lake/"/>
<updated>2024-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/elsay-lake</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Since my experience on &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2024-07-17-my-limit/&quot;&gt;Howe Sound Crest Trail&lt;/a&gt; I’ve not hiked as much or cared about peaks. So I was glad to be able to do a quick overnight up to Elsay Lake which is nearby and a lake I’ve seen from above - but never visited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also it’s a good overnight trip that I can do straight from my house and end up in the almost back country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;12318210614&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was an overcast day and heading up from Deep Cove I went from patchy sun, into deep cloud, into sun, into deep cloud and ended up at an overcast remote lake. I’ve all but the last 5km or so of this trail before and knew what to expect, until I hit that last 5km.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t hard, but for about 2km its just harder, steeper and less clearly marked than I expected. As you go around Mt Elsay, the trail drops down steeply about 150m of elevation. Overall going from the parking lot down to Elsay Lake means losing about 800m of elevation, the lake it’s self being at 765m elevation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I got to the lake I somehow tripped forward over a log and nailed the landing, no injuries. Or so I thought, I walked forward a few meters and was curious why the back of my leg stung. Somehow I had multiple gashes, 2 inches and 8 inches long on the back of my leg with bloody everywhere. Nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lake itself is lovely, quiet, serene and peaceful. The water was warm after all that hot summer weather. I camped next to the emergency shelter that night so I could use the porch to cook on. It was so quiet, not even sound from the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next day due to a bleeding leg, I decided to get a ride from Mt. Seymour resort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;12318247010&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think most people do the hike to and from Mt. Seymour and I’d definitely recommend that unless you are wanting that extra distance.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Jasper Fire</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-08-12-jasper-fires/"/>
<updated>2024-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/jasper-fires</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On July 22 a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/newsinteractives/features/the-monster-of-jasper&quot;&gt;monstrous fire ripped through Jasper&lt;/a&gt;. This was a terrible tragedy for residents, visitors and the environment in and around Jasper. I’ve got a huge amount of sympathy and empathy for those affected. A firefighter was killed battling the fire and that’s also terrible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hashtag called #JasperStrong went around on social media and I’m more just #JasperSad than anything, because of the damage that has been inflicted on Canadians and Albertans, by those who contribute to climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For context, Alberta has the largest emissions of green house gases in Canada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/ghg-emissions.png&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s oil and gas industry is huge and is exporting oil and gas around the world. The Trans Mountain pipeline that Canadians tax payers paid &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theglobeandmail.com/business/article-canada-trans-mountain-pipeline-expansion/&quot;&gt;$34 billion&lt;/a&gt; for terminates very close to my house and will be pumping out fossil fuels for many decades to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years we have seen climate change affect so many parts of the world. But when it hits farmers in Central America, or causes floods in Asia or whatever a long way away, it can feel like it’s not really a problem. Something I don’t need to worry about. Something I can ignore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then when climate change hits the people close to you, so viscerally and so raw like this, you’d think it would change opinions. You’d think people would wake up and realise that we can’t avoid this, we need to stop it now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’d think so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like after the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2016_Fort_McMurray_wildfire&quot;&gt;Fort McMurray fire&lt;/a&gt; which at an estimated cost of $9.9 billion was the costliest disaster in Canadian history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like after the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lytton_wildfire&quot;&gt;Lytton fire&lt;/a&gt; which completely destroyed the town of Lytton (somewhere I’ve visited, it’s heartbreaking).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like after the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/british-columbia/bc-heat-dome-sudden-deaths-revised-2021-1.6232758&quot;&gt;heat dome&lt;/a&gt; that killed 595 people in British Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These aren’t heat events in far off places in the world, they are extreme events right in our own country and made much, much, worse by climate change. The thing that &lt;a href=&quot;https://albertabeyondfossilfuels.ca/alberta-and-the-carbon-budget/&quot;&gt;Alberta and Canada&lt;/a&gt; is contributing too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alberta’s Danielle Smith, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://duckduckgo.com/?t=ffab&amp;amp;q=danielle+smith+climate+change&amp;amp;ia=web&quot;&gt;elected leader of Jasper won’t talk about it, or diminishes it&lt;/a&gt;. The leader of the federal opposition talks about axing the Carbon tax, but not what they’ll do about actually get Canada to reduce its emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find it incredibly sad, that when we are faced with the evidence of the harm and damage to our own country we still can’t do anything about it. Alberta has continued down this path and elected politicians who continues to ignore it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why the Jasper fire made me #JasperSad.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Russet Lake</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-08-10-russet-lake/"/>
<updated>2024-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/russet-lake</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I haven’t done much back packing in Garibaldi, so extended a trip to Whistler with a chance to hike in the back country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;12081165554&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t leave until around lunch time, so I took the chance to take the gondola up to the Roundhouse at Whistler. Then it’s a good opportunity to get lost in all the trails around the top of the mountain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve got out of that it gradually gets quieter as you do the High Note trail, then quieter on the Musical Bumps trail to Russet Lake. This is a lovely trail that’s accessible to many people, it’s not at all technical and has amazing meadows with views of amazing glaciers and mountains on either side. It’s stunning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Camping at Russet Lake is nice, it was windy in the evening which kept the bugs away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only real problem I’ve got is that you are on a series of mountains that lead you one of two ways, towards Overlord Mountain, or back. There really isn’t anywhere to go with huge glacial valleys on either side. So next day I tried Overlord - an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Overlord_Mountain&quot;&gt;amazing peak with glaciers on either side at 2,625m&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;12081165844&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got up to over 2,115m on the way up Rector Peak and that’s when I found that the trail was getting more exposed than I liked. It probably would have been fine, but based on what &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alltrails.com/ar/trail/canada/british-columbia/overlord-mountain--2&quot;&gt;I read about online&lt;/a&gt; and spoke about with people who did it - I decided to turn around. The views were stunning at this point anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There wasn’t much else to do there, so I headed back down Singing Pass into Whistler. I partly wanted to see what Singing Pass was like and now I know. Consistent gradient, down in the shade of trees, and a pretty boring long hike down into Whistler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would do Russet Lake again, maybe try Overlord Mountain if I’m with someone or feeling in a better head space.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Mt. St. Helens</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-07-31-mt-st-helens/"/>
<updated>2024-07-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/mt-st-helens</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s an active volcano and we thought it would be cool to hike up it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;12006332708&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first hour is in trees and is nice. Then it opens up onto the volcano and you climb up a ridge basically to the top. The defining features of this hike are lava rocks and ash. There are many trails up the ridge, you aim for posts that have been erected, but generally want to avoid being too close to them as that’s the hardest route sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After an hour of that you hit a steep boulder field full of lava rock. It’s a real maze with no clear path so you just have to figure it out up the steep path. After an hour of that you’ve got the final leg which mostly ash and gravel. The last couple of hundred metres is so hard, one step forward, half a step back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone with a fear of vertical drops, there were no problems on this hike - until the view at the end. Get to the top and you are on the crater with a fantastic view and steep vertical drops. A few muinutes there was enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a brief snapshot into life in these areas, everyone we met on the trail was lovely. However we were approached by people wanting us to join (presumably Christian) morning service, many Trump flags and stickers and some guy sitting outside an ice cream shop asking us to vote Trump. Sigh.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Hitting my limit on the Howe Sound Crest Trail</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-07-17-my-limit/"/>
<updated>2024-07-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/my-limit</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ St Marks, ✅ Unneccessary, ✅ North Unneccessary, ✅ Thomas, ✅ James, ✅ David&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I 💚 hiking and the back country, camping and being out in nature. I like mountains and I’ve hiked lots of them. But I don’t like mountaineering in the sense of requiring vertical climbing, vertical drops, rock climbing etc. I’ve tried outdoors climbing and it just scared me, I just have a real fear of vertical drops. For the majority of hikes I’ve done &lt;em&gt;this has never been a problem&lt;/em&gt;. There’s the odd moment on mountains I didn’t like, but that’s rare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then I did the Howe Sound Crest trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11890867390&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This day enabled me to bag 6 peaks but completely destroyed me physically and pretty much wrecked me mentally too, I hit my limit. Between Unnecessary the other side of James Peak there was so much scrambly, vertical stuff that it scared the crap out of me. There’s the traverse around the West Lion, Thomas Peak, ridge walk up James Peak and then the traverse between James peaks. There are parts with vertical cliffs on both sides, sometimes just one side, sometimes inches away. Sometimes you are scrambling down rough rocks, roots and dirts towards instant death on cliffs. There are multiple places where a mis-step won’t just result in scratches, cuts or hurt limb, but just straight death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Many people do these trails and have no problem. This is likely just my problem.&lt;/em&gt; Some even love big drops and you’ll see them grinning on pictures. I don’t. It’s not just the medical problems I’ve had like inner ear vertigo type problems, I just can’t do it. Howe Sound Crest Trail pushed me over my limit and I was just terrified at points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was going to do the whole trail, but in the end found the quickest way off the trail when I realised it was just getting worse and went down into Lions Bay instead of camping. Of course, I’d done all the hard and scary parts and could have just continued, but I understood I was in a bad state and could not face anything else that day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that my problems aren’t shared and went back to read resources to check I wasn’t missing something. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.ca/Glorious-Mountains-Vancouvers-North-Shore/dp/1771602414&quot;&gt;Glorious Mountains of the North Shore&lt;/a&gt; says things like “There is no real exposure, but there exists the possibility for a fall and an injury.” and “Just take it calm and slow” and “Take care when approaching… a fall to the west would be fatal”. I like this book a lot, but for me the danger felt much worse and much more stressful than was presented. The Howe Sound Crest trail is number 2 in trails for search and rescue according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://bc.ctvnews.ca/these-10-b-c-trails-had-the-most-search-and-rescue-calls-last-year-1.6405200&quot;&gt;this list&lt;/a&gt; (actually this was a pretty accurate depiction).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, it’s done I’ll never go back and I can now definitely start crossing off mountains I will never, ever do. I’m no longer sure I’ll do all the peaks on the North Shore or even want to do this anymore, we’ll see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One up side, because I did this with a full backpack on a hot day and took a longer route by exiting… I burnt through what I think is a record 6,309 calories, over 12 hours for one of my biggest single day efforts ever. I was a wreck.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Goat Mountain, Goat Ridge Peak</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-07-13-goat/"/>
<updated>2024-07-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/goat</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ Goat Mountain, ✅ Goat Ridge Peak&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goat Mountain is relatively straightforward, but has very steep paths up it. Some of those steep parts have chains, others do not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there it’s a hike around the ridge to Goat Ridge Peak. This is through heather, blueberry bushes and small trees, with many patches of snow causing streams and waterfalls. This is one of the most beautiful hikes I’ve done this year with absolutely amazing views. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I wasn’t alone. With clear and recent bear footprints in the snow and the mud. Not surprising given the number of blueberry bushes that will be perfect bear food soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11873068247&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What started out as a relatively easy hike, soon turned into something that I struggled with. My heart rate was climbing fast, I was tired and felt more wiped than I have in a long time. The feeling was similar to when I struggled on &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2023-08-18-mt-frosty/&quot;&gt;Mt Frosty&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hike across the peak is very exposed and I was in the mid-day sun at that point for quite a while, working my way across snow. I was tired, dehydrated and had lost a lot of electrolytes which I hadn’t replaced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I pulled a muscle climbing down some quite vertical sections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time I got back to the gondola I was thoroughly drained and tired. Currently I’m doubting if I can actually complete my goal, not only are some peaks really hard (and look very intimidating from up high), but I really questioned by fitness today. At this point I think I’m gonna have to make doing all the peaks a 2024 and 2025 goal.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Pump Peak, Tim Jones Peak, Mt. Seymour</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-07-10-tim-jones-mt-seymour/"/>
<updated>2024-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/tim-jones-mt-seymour</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ 2️⃣ Pump Peak, ✅ Tim Jones Peak, ✅ Mt Seymour&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mountain lakes swum: 1️⃣&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was originally aiming for Runner Peak, but decided that wasn’t happening today. The more I look at Runner Peak, the less I want to do it. Getting up Pump, Second and Third peaks was just fine. It was a hot day around 30c in town, a little cooler on the mountain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are still small patches of snow in parts, but everything is now hikeable and its only parts that get a lot of shade that have snow. No spikes needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11856984669&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really disappointed to be having to pick up garbage on Pump Peak, including plastic water bottles, ziploc baggies and instant noodle packets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stopped at Mystery Lake on the way down. One month ago (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/11606417454&quot;&gt;June 8th&lt;/a&gt;) we went past Mystery Lake and it was partially frozen, surrounded by snow. Today there was no snow. I stopped for a swim and it was glorious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting a new counter of mountain lakes swum in with a counter of 1️⃣ 😎&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Silver Star, Mt. Fromme</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-07-09-silver-star-fromme/"/>
<updated>2024-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/silver-star-fromme</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ Mount Fromme&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the weekend I was in Silver Star resort, so did some hiking on Silver Star Mountain. These aren’t peaks on the North Shore, but it was nice to do something different. We hiked up over Silver Star, down into the provincial park and then back around the hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11824384416&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was hot and the hike up was surrounded with lovely wildflowers. Going into the provincial park side wasn’t much to speak of, long trails with no people, no views, trees on every side, boggy and with bugs. The Black Prince cabin was neat though. Overall it was nice to get a lot of kms on new boots and it was pretty and sunny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that Silver Star hiking trails are very few, since its mostly for mountain bikers, and then they charge you to hike - I wouldn’t recommend it as a hiker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I did Fromme, which is a peak for the peak baggers list. We went down from the Gondola, then up pipeline pass and up to the top of the mountain. Then all the way down to Skyline road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11849326232&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall I really liked Fromme, not too long and steep. A nice flat top to relax on and (mostly) a nice gentle downhill. Would recommend as a nice day hike for most people. It was also really cool to see good views of all the other mountains I’ll be doing as well 😎&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Grouse, Dam and Little Goat</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-06-30-little-goat/"/>
<updated>2024-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/little-goat</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ Grouse ✅ Dam ✅ Little Goat&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are three of the easier peaks on the North Shore, being close to the top of the gondola. Which I took up, making for a relatively easy day. It wasn’t raining and when the skies momentarily cleared was quite warm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The snow hasn’t melted and after Dam it was continuous snow with some parts of the trail hard to make out, due to the lack of tape and flagging in the trees. The clouds cleared momentarily for nice views of Goat and Kennedy Lake, but those views were brief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11778271735&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting back to the gondola I found out it had broken down. Looking at the queue size and number of people, I figured it would be several trips before I could get on the gondola so may as well do the BCMC down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11778576586&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gondola wasn’t fixed until that evening, meaning that apparently many people ill-equipped and not physically able to do the trail were taking it down in the evening. It’s a slippery trail and so there were many first responders out to help. I was on the bus home by that point, but that sounds like a tough day for many.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

</feed>
