<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Andy McKay</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub.ca/blog/andy" rel="alternate"></link>
<link href="https://mckay.pub.ca/blog/rss/latest/andy/" rel="self"></link>
<updated>2020-12-12T23:11:55+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub.ca/blog/andy</id>
<author>
<name>Andy McKay</name>
<email>andy@clearwind.ca</email>
</author>

<entry>
<title>My fifth Gran Fondo</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub.ca/2019-09-20-fifth-fondo/"/>
<updated>2019-09-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub.ca/fifth-fondo</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A bit ago was my fifth Gran Frondo, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2018-09-09-fourth-fondo/&quot;&gt;the last&lt;/a&gt; was in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I dropped 25 minutes off my time and that made me really happy. This year my goal was 4 hours. This was just an aribtrary number, but it was also based on an attempt to qualify for the 2020 version of this race which is a UCI World Cup Event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up to May I was almost continually running with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/2344462557/overview&quot;&gt;BMO Half Marathon&lt;/a&gt; in May which I did in 2h 08m. In March, April and May I was running up to average of 40km a week.  I guess I was kind excited by that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;2:08:42 for my first half marathon - woot! Next year the full deal. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/uwBDROsGSD&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/uwBDROsGSD&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Destroy all cars (@andymckay) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/andymckay/status/1125131691234811904?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 5, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I focused a lot on running this year, my riding patterns changed a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2017 (up to Fondo)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2018 (up to Fondo)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2019 (up to Fondo)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Time&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;243h&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;232h 16m&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;165h 51m&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Distance&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5,050km&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5,279km&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3,889km&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rides&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;198&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;136&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in 2019, I spent less time on the bike. In fact I haven’t spent this little time on a bike since &lt;strong&gt;2015&lt;/strong&gt;, which was my first year. After May I ran less frequently, but carried on running, varying between 0 (on bad weeks) to 30km (on good weeks).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did &lt;a href=&quot;http://mckay.pub/2018-05-27-mt-seymour/&quot;&gt;Mount Seymour&lt;/a&gt; at least 9 times (most yet) and broke my own personal record 4 times. I managed quite a few 100km plus rides: including the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/2532536358&quot;&gt;160km Penticton Gran Fondo&lt;/a&gt; race, the challenge route of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/2648420747&quot;&gt;Ride to Conquer Cancer&lt;/a&gt;, a ride up to Whistler, and a couple of trips to Golden Ears park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also this year I got a little more organised with my training. This is taped to my bedroom wall:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://mckay.pub/files/ED57AcSVUAEa5VC.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I rode with Steed group 2 a few times, that’s the second fastest group and sometimes they go at a hell of a pace. Last year I stepped up from group 4 to group 3. Next year I aim to have group 2 as my default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the race came and as usual I spent a few days before hand excited and not sleeping too well. Yet again I hadn’t lost enough weight and I really doubted if the 4 hour figure was reasonable. Just thinking through what I did last year to get to 4:19 seemed daunting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again I started in the 4 to 4.5 corral which is essential to getting in with a good group. The first 30km was marred by several large and nasty looking crashes. I focused on going fast up to Squamish but needed to save something for later. As I passed my marker in Squamish I thought I was behind but honestly I didn’t feel like I’d pushed myself too hard and felt fresh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unbeknownst to me, I’d set personal records all the way and crushed it. My average was over 32km/h an hour at that point. To get close to 4 hours, my goal was to not let it drop below 30km/h. This year I couldn’t find good draughts in Squamish, the people were going too slow so I kept pulling out… and as a result pulled an awful lot of people through Squamish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I piled up the hills and again failed to find good draughts, despite thinking strategically and doing my best to line them up in the right places. About 25-30km out from Whistler I bonked again and realised I hadn’t been eating right. About 15km I was struggling hard and failing to keep up. My average km kept dropping and dropping. I was just pissed off and couldn’t understand why I couldn’t go faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result? &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/2688389229&quot;&gt;I ended up crossing at 4h 16m&lt;/a&gt;. That’s 3 minutes faster - I was happy and sort of pissed off that I wasn’t faster. It’s my fastest ever time, I’ve been faster every year so I’ll take that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe height=&quot;405&quot; width=&quot;590&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/2688389229/embed/a40d29d1cc807aa0cb7d36fb4cb6830e9eca7f4c&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually I guess I was pretty happy with it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Fuck yeah! Fastest time yet 4:16 &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/DSdOEe33NG&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/DSdOEe33NG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Destroy all cars (@andymckay) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/andymckay/status/1170415223066386432?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;September 7, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not qualify for the World Cup race for next year, but I’ve signed up again to do the normal race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve signed up again and I’m going to crush 4 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>2019 Goals - Five months check in</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub.ca/2019-06-02-five-months-in/"/>
<updated>2019-06-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub.ca/five-months-in</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Checking in with my &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2018-12-28-goals/&quot;&gt;five month goals&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Holy crap it’s been this long.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lost a couple of pounds and finally got back on track with my diet. Not as good as it could be, but getting better.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Still stuggle with eating too much after exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m doing a lot of exercise and I’m back cycling now, yay! Did 127 km bike ride followed by an 80 km bike ride this weekend for example. Yeah I was tired.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Still running a couple of days a week around 5km ish. Need to bring that back up to 8 and 10km and still keep cycling.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I haven’t been to the gym in ages.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’ve got a plan for cycling through to the Fondo. Damn holidays keep getting in the way though.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Create Issue Extension</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub.ca/2019-05-14-create-issue/"/>
<updated>2019-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub.ca/create-issue</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I needed to find a better way to keep track of my to-do lists. I’ve tried a few tools, but after a while always forget about them and don’t keep them up to date. A to-do list is only any good if you add stuff to it and look at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spend 95% my time in about 5 places these days: Google Calendar, Google Docs, Gmail, Slack and Github. I spend a lot of time on the latter, GitHub. So, of course, to super charge my to-do list I went for a quick browser extension - cue colleagues who laugh and say “of course you did” when I mention this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/andymckay/create-issue&quot;&gt;Create issue on GitHub&lt;/a&gt; is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/create-github-issue/&quot;&gt;stupid simple Firefox Extension&lt;/a&gt; that lets you highlight a peice of text on a page, then right click to create an issue. It creates the issue in a repository defined on the config page using a personal access token. That’s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beauty of this is that everything is a web page. Emails. Slack messages. Docs. All you do is highlight some text then right click and it creates an issue with the selected text and a URL to the item. Key to this is that’s it &lt;strong&gt;fast&lt;/strong&gt; to create a simple issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/74699/53767875-fac37300-3e8b-11e9-8401-650d0a317f3a.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this I’ve setup a private repo (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.blog/2019-01-07-new-year-new-github/&quot;&gt;those are free now&lt;/a&gt;). Thanks to all the integrations with GitHub issues, I get a bunch of stuff for free:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;automatic links on other issues and PRs across GitHub back to my to-do item&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;notifications in email and Slack&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/marketplace/stale&quot;&gt;stale&lt;/a&gt; to automatically clean my list&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/probot/reminders&quot;&gt;reminders&lt;/a&gt; to remind me of me of things at set times&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far I’ve used this more than any to-do list system I’ve used in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>2019 Goals - Four months check in</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub.ca/2019-05-13-four-months-in/"/>
<updated>2019-05-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub.ca/four-months-in</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Checking in with my &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2018-12-28-goals/&quot;&gt;four month goals&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lost a couple of pounds but keep going up and down. Still struggling with this. My diet is still not good.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Diet has fallen completely and this is where I need to get back on track.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Running was amazing in April. We continually did longer and longer runs 14km, 16km, 18km, 19km, 21km runs. Only once when I decided to run the last 3km at 5:30 min/km pace did I feel totally exhausted after.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I haven’t been to the gym in ages.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;But most of all…&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/2344462557&quot;&gt;a half marathon&lt;/a&gt;! I didn’t die! I didn’t walk!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seriously most of the half marathon was actually quite fun. It started out in Queen Elizabeth park and headed downtown, around Stanley Park and into downtown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until about 17km I was doing great with a sub 6 min/km pace, but I hit the proverbial wall in the last few km. The run uphill towards the finish (at 5:27 min/km pace I’ll add) was brutal. I ended up starting off with friends, but then running the whole thing by myself, which was probably the best thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty proud of that one and I’ll have to beat my 2 h 8 min time next year.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>2019 Goals - Two months check in</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub.ca/2019-03-02-two-months-in/"/>
<updated>2019-03-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub.ca/two-months-in</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Checking in with my &lt;a href=&quot;httsp://mckay.pub/2018-12-28-goals/&quot;&gt;two month goals&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lost a couple of pounds but keep going up and down.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Diet has fallen completely and this is where I need to get back on track.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Running has improved again. The training runs are getting longer and longer. I did my longest run 11.2km and broke 30km a week twice.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I thought I did the West Van Run in 29 minutes last year. Turns out it was over 30 minutes. This year I came in 27.29, which puts me at a solid 5:30 pace. Faster than last time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gym work has picked up a little, mostly a chance to do long slow bike rides and focus on keeping my heart in zone 1.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Haven’t had alcohol since 2018 even though I’ve been to some pubs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More to do, especially on the weight loss.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>2019 Goals - One month check in</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub.ca/2019-02-01-one-month-in/"/>
<updated>2019-02-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub.ca/one-month-in</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Checking in with my &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2018-12-28-goals/&quot;&gt;one month goals&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Lost 12 pounds. Although I did go as much as 15 pounds down, only to come back up again.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Diet was mostly Keto for a while, but I’ve slipped into some carbs for running and sometimes have too many carbs. That’s probably caused the lack of weight loss.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Running has dramatically improved. At the beginning of the month I was feeling down because I was going slowly. This last week I completed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/2107454561&quot;&gt;7.1k at a sub 6km/minute pace&lt;/a&gt; and my training runs are getting faster.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Signed up for the West Van Run in March, want to beat my time on that from last year - 29 minutes - significantly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Set a goal of doing a 10k in under an hour - that’s 5 minutes to chop off.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Gym work has dropped off significantly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Haven’t had alcohol since 2018 even though I’ve been to some pubs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More to do.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>2019 Goals</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub.ca/2018-12-28-goals/"/>
<updated>2018-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub.ca/goals</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My goal&lt;/strong&gt;: I’m going to beat last years time of 4:19 and do the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rbcgranfondo.com/whistler/&quot;&gt;Whistler Gran Fondo&lt;/a&gt; in September 2019 in 4 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That seems absurdly ridiculous on the face of it, but the fact that I was able to shave off 23 minutes this year was nothing short of miraculous to me. So let’s try shaving off another 19 minutes. How am I going to do this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get serious about losing weight again. I’ve done it in the past and then I revert. This year I’m aiming for a race weight of 160 lbs. In the past I’ve been around 180 lbs by the time I do the Gran Fondo.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Improve my watts per kg. The amount of power you can output is important so I’ve got to lose weight without losing muscle. I did an estimated 236w power last Fondo, if I can do the some power output and weigh less I’ll push up my time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actual things I’m going to do to meet these goals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do a half marathon. I’m in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bmovanmarathon.ca/&quot;&gt;BMO Half&lt;/a&gt; in May. I’ve done 4 10k races so far and I found the last one a bit slow and painful. I need to get comfortable at doing 5k every day and a 10k regularly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cycle regularly in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://steedcycles.com/ride-clubs/&quot;&gt;Steed group 2&lt;/a&gt;. That’s the faster group than I normally ride in.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Complete the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/segments/612178?filter=current_year&quot;&gt;Seymour Hill Climb&lt;/a&gt; in under 1 hour. My top time is 1:15:34 and according to Strava I’m 4924 / 6151. There’s room for improvement there.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do lots of work at the gym to work on my core, leg and back muscles.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can totally do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/strong&gt;: I might just say screw it and not do this. It’s my life.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Car Tracking</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub.ca/2018-12-15-car-tracking/"/>
<updated>2018-12-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub.ca/car-tracking</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This week I recieved and email from the Clean Energy Vehicle program. They’d like us to install a device in our Tesla that tracks us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“By understanding when and where EVs charge to how much energy is consumed, you can help pave the way for future drivers by ensuring that the power system is ready for a plug-in future.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program details &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fleetcarma.com/chargebc/&quot;&gt;are here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“GPS information is collected, but not shared at the individual level. The data is collected and stored but no one outside of FleetCarma will see an individual’s location data.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright so who’s FleetCarma? Let’s look into &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fleetcarma.com/chargebc/terms/&quot;&gt;the terms&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Data Collected by the C2 Device and Privacy…  drive start date and time, duration of trip, trip distance… GPS coordinates of the drive,”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“With the specific exclusion of GPS coordinates when driving, an anonymized subset of the data outlined above may be shared with the Province and BC Hydro and other third party suppliers”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“GPS coordinates during driving will not be shared with any Program partners or third party suppliers except in both anonymous and aggregate form to inhibit extraction of any individual driving behaviour.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not sure who those Program partners or third party suppliers are but GeoTab uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1sVygLN02w2xNovFY4q5vw-oAzfYxCd7WLhyToElgDbs/pub&quot;&gt;some sub-processors&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FletCarma will &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fleetcarma.com/privacy/&quot;&gt;share your information&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“To affiliated entities of CrossChasm Technologies Inc., including wholly owned subsidiaries” (Whomever that is)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When we’re legally required to provide data, such as in response to a subpoena in a civil lawsuit.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s nice to note.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You may also request that your Personal Information be deleted. FleetCarma will promptly respond to your request within 30 days”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I can surmise that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FleetCarma will know all the trips I make in the car.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FleetCarma be subpoenad to give up that information.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;FleetCarma can be hacked to give up all that information.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally this would be a simple, hell no. But I care greatly about electric cars and the infrastructure and this has put me in a bind. The privacy problem here is one that I simply can’t get around.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>BC going electric</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub.ca/2018-11-20-bc-going-electric/"/>
<updated>2018-11-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub.ca/bc-going-electric</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today the BC Government announced that they will be planning to introduce legislation that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;All new cars and trucks sold in B.C. in the year 2040 will have to be zero-emission vehicles&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/british-columbia/every-new-car-sold-in-2040-will-be-zero-emission-b-c-government-says-1.4913679&quot;&gt;CBC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m unreasonably interested and excited by this. There is a simple fact that we need to do this and car companies will not do it, they are too &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thedrive.com/news/24142/bmw-expects-85-percent-of-its-cars-will-keep-traditional-combustion-engines-in-2030&quot;&gt;invested in the existing carbon economy&lt;/a&gt;. My first thought is that 2040 is way too far off, but this really isn’t a simple change and the political and societal desire to change is not strong enough to force a sudden change yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other jurisdictions are making similar noises, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://qz.com/1341155/nine-countries-say-they-will-ban-internal-combustion-engines-none-have-a-law-to-do-so/&quot;&gt;haven’t introduced legislation yet&lt;/a&gt;. Two that talk about it more are the UK and California. There are some interesting questions in BC :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;BC is big. Twice the size of California and over four times the size of the UK. It’s full of a lot of nothing. You can go long ways without encountering anything. This problem is common to most of Canada, but the current range of electric vehicles is more obvious when its 400km to the next charging station.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;BC gets &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_extreme_temperatures_in_Canada&quot;&gt;really cold up north&lt;/a&gt;. Colder than California or the UK. This affects &lt;a href=&quot;https://teslamotorsclub.com/tmc/threads/cold-weather-driving.64591/&quot;&gt;electric batteries and charging&lt;/a&gt;. Again this problem affects all of Canada.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Site_C_dam&quot;&gt;Site C isn’t perfect&lt;/a&gt;, but we’ll need the electricity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remind me why we should have a pipeline to ship oil from Alberta out again?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes I am focusing on electric vehicles here, because that’s the majority of non oil burning cars out there. Notably Vancouver has the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/british-columbia/hydrogen-fuel-pump-opens-in-vancouver-1.4709016&quot;&gt;first hydrogen fuel station&lt;/a&gt; in Canada. We might need hydrogen in other parts of BC, or perhaps there will be another answer by then, but for the moment it looks like we are looking at an electric future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also &lt;a href=&quot;/2018-07-25-tesla/&quot;&gt;Tesla is pretty amazing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, I hope this legislation happens and if so it sets us down an interesting path. A slow one, but there are some real problems to solve on the way.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>So done with the NFL</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub.ca/2018-11-15-done-with-the-nfl/"/>
<updated>2018-11-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub.ca/done-with-the-nfl</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been an NFL for fan for a long time. It started before university when I rebelled against any sport that was vaguely popular at school (and seemed absolutely terrible). For no other reason than they did well at the time, I became a Washington Redskins fan (yes I’m old).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started a football team at university, I was involved in it. I even heard Chuck Noll speak once. If there was a Redskins game on TV, I would go up to the local pub in my jersey and watch the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last few years I’ve become pretty upset with what the NFL has become. Well the NFL has always been this way - but I didn’t care. I enjoyed the game, the drama, the strategy, the rivalies, and I ignored or excused away all the problems for my own enjoyment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally I realised that I couldn’t keep doing this. The problems just kept increasing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Redskins is a terrible name for a team and is pretty much condemned as a racist. They need to change it, but they won’t because the Redskins make lots of money for Daniel Synder (Redskins owner).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The treatment of players and the problems with concussions has been terrible. The NFL has swept it under the rug for so long. Yes they’ve introduced changes, but tried to balance the fundamental problems that constant head contact is part of the game.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Cheerleaders.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Colin Kapernick.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The owners siding with Trump over their players.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The NFL is technically taxed as a charity so it isn’t a good corporate citizen.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The league owners hold regularly hold cities and tax payers to ransom over stadiums.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;So many adverts.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniel Snyder is one such business person and I don’t want to support him. I want to be proud of the thing I spend so much time following and I want to be a good example to my daughters. The only way I know how to do that is stop watching the NFL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s now over half way through the season, I haven’t watched a game, I don’t really know what’s going. I’ve unsubscribed from all the football blogs, podcasts and tweets. They were showing the standings on the TV in a pub and it showed that the Redskins are doing quite well this year after years of being crap. But whatever, I don’t care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps something will change to make me go back, but its not the game being boring, it’s the sides that the NFL takes. Somethings got to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Footnote:&lt;/b&gt; with the exception of the Green Bay Packers who are the only non-profit, community-owned major league professional sports team. Have no cheerleaders, play in all kinds of weather and are just awesome. They haven’t solved the problem about treating their players properly or being in a league with other terrible people though.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>My fourth Gran Fondo</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub.ca/2018-09-09-fourth-fondo/"/>
<updated>2018-09-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub.ca/fourth-fondo</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday was my fourth Gran Frondo, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2017-09-10-third-fondo/&quot;&gt;the last&lt;/a&gt; was in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fondo for me has become the signature event of the year. It’s at the end of the season, as the days get shorter and the evenings draw closer and the rain starts to arrive. The ride provides a nice gauge for how well the training has gone and your level of fitness over the year. Also, since it’s the same ride every year you can compare yourself historically to the ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I dropped 17 minutes off my time and that made me really happy. I finished &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2017-09-10-third-fondo/&quot;&gt;last years post&lt;/a&gt; by saying “I’m going to get below 4hr 30min next year”. So that was my goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equipment wise I got a new bike and upgraded to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cervelo.com/en/road/s-series/s3&quot;&gt;Cervélo S3&lt;/a&gt;. It’s lighter, more aero, bigger gears and faster. I love my S3. I also got a new computer and upgraded to a Wahoo to get a cadence, heart rate and speed monitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My riding patterns changed too, partly due to a change in jobs from &lt;a href=&quot;https://mozilla.org&quot;&gt;Mozilla&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. That meant I had no office to go to and no daily commute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2017 (up to Fondo)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2018 (up to Fondo)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Time&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;243h&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;232h 16m&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Distance&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5,050km&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5,279.3km&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rides&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;198&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;136&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in 2018, I spent less time on the bike, but went father and did longer average rides. There was less time grinding out a commute to and from the office, which whilst good exercise, might not have been good training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did &lt;a href=&quot;http://mckay.pub/2018-05-27-mt-seymour/&quot;&gt;Mount Seymour&lt;/a&gt; 7 times (only made it 3 times last year). I managed quite a few 100km plus rides: including the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/1781360791&quot;&gt;160km Tour De Victoria&lt;/a&gt; race, the challenge route of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://m.strava.com/activities/1797329558&quot;&gt;Ride to Conquer Cancer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/1734448931&quot;&gt;150km up the Sunshine Coast&lt;/a&gt; to Savary Island - and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/1753083769&quot;&gt;173km back&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/1685203057&quot;&gt;132km up to Whistler&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/1694235939&quot;&gt;then back&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theory was that those long rides would help, if I can do a race lasting 160km, perhaps a 122km race won’t seem so bad. Also this year I moved up a group at Steed and rode regularly with the group 3 riders, instead of the group 4. That meant longer rides with less stopping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the winter, I took up running and did my first 10km run and that helped me keep my weight under control and hopefully keep some level of cardio ability over the winter so I didn’t have to start all over again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So yesterday came and I spent a few days before hand excited and not sleeping too well. I realised that I was looking forward to and excited by this ride. Given that my weight loss hadn’t been as much as I wanted and some recent times, I wasn’t expecting to hit my goal of under 4h 30m. I fully expected to be similar to last year, around 4h 45m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I worked my way into the 4.5 hour area instead of starting further back. Turns out this made a difference as I was able to get into a group of people going similar paces and that really helped. It set a good pace and let me do some good drafting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_0576.JPG&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weather was mixed on the first half, some rain - there was a big downpour at Porteau Cove and rain Squamish. But I made good time on the first half. This year instead of focusing on hitting time at check points I focused on two statistics, my heart rate and my average time. Last year 4h 45m meant a speed of 25km/hr. Knowing that the hills are in the second half of the course, I tried to get my average speed high but keep my heart rate low so I had something in the tank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s one of the few long flats around Squamish and I got in behind someone pulling along at 38km/hr. That got my average up to 30km/hr and kept my heart rate under control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/2018-fondo-speed.png&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weather improved after Squamish and was dry from then on. My challenge was to take the hills and keep my average up and it started dropping. But I was determined to keep it up above 25 km/hr. Around Daisy Lake, I got a good draft for a while at 35km/hr pace. But had to keep on racing hard to keep that speed up. You can see the effect this had on my heart rate as it starts to climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/2018-fondo-heart-rate.png&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result? &lt;a href=&quot;https://m.strava.com/activities/1828174637&quot;&gt;I ended up crossing at 4h 19m&lt;/a&gt;. That’s 25 minutes faster than a younger version of me. I was shocked, surprised and so happy and incoherent as I crossed the finish line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can’t believe I did it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve got not idea what goal to set for next year, yes I’ve signed up again.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Tesla Model 3</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub.ca/2018-07-25-tesla/"/>
<updated>2018-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub.ca/tesla</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;About a month ago we got our &lt;a href=&quot;https://ts.la/andrew72696&quot;&gt;Tesla Model 3&lt;/a&gt;. This is a rambling post about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally I don’t mind spending money on some things, but I absolutely hate spending money on depreciating assets. Since I’m lucky enough to have money to save, I feel it should be in boring assets that make a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vanguardcanada.ca/&quot;&gt;solid return every year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve liked looking at fast and expensive cars, but when it comes to actually spending lots of money on them, I’ve always thought its a terrible idea. I’ve wanted a Porsche forever, but I’ve never wanted to spend the money on one. We’ve gone to buy cars and I’ve come away feeling grumpy and miserable that I’ve spent that much money on something that will depreciate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then along came Tesla. Sure Elon Musk and Tesla have a few problems at the moment, but here is a person who is actually trying to do something about the fact that our planet is burning up. This is a man on a mission to do good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a company that released the Model S, a car so revolutionary that it broke &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcrunch.com/2015/08/27/teslas-model-s-p85d-just-broke-consumer-reports-ratings-system-scoring-103-out-of-100/&quot;&gt;Consumer Reports scoring&lt;/a&gt;. A car that has taken over the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cleantechnica.com/2018/04/22/tesla-model-s-crushes-luxury-car-competition-in-usa/&quot;&gt;luxury model class&lt;/a&gt;. We test drove a Model S and it was amazing. Everything we drove after that felt like it was ancient technology. But there’s no way in hell I’d spend that kind of money on a Model S.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then along came the Model 3 and we put our refundable deposit down predicting we’d need a new car eventually. And waited and waited. Finally our spot came up and we had to buy the premium version which sucked. It meant more money and that made me grumpy. We thought about it, I got more grumpy but eventually we went for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a few reasons why. The time is right for electric cars. The infrastructure is in place. Most car manufacturers, spurred by Tesla, are producing electric cars. There’s a tipping point and its happening over the next few years. In BC over 90% of electricity comes from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bchydro.com/energy-in-bc/operations/generation.html&quot;&gt;hydro electricity&lt;/a&gt;. A car is rarely a green choice in terms of the plastic, metal and other materials used, the manufacturing process, the amount of road infrastructure dedicated to it and so on. But this is about as good as a car gets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how is it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/model-3-top.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width: 400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazeballs. I irrationally love this thing. I’m still making excuses to go places so I can drive the car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The car is minimalist on the the inside and I like it. So many cars have a billion buttons and knobs for every function. Everything apart from lights, indicators and wipers are controlled through the tablet mounted in the middle. But most of those are automatic anyway, so hey why bother. Sitting in my Toyota now feels fussy and complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/model-3-dash.jpg&quot; style=&quot;width: 400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It goes fast. Really fast. You put your foot down and it just goes and keep going. Silently and with power. It accelerates faster than that Porsche Boxster I wanted. And thats more than fast enough for me thank you. It’s got a 500km range and we barely do that in a few weeks around town. Because of the huge battery in the bottom it goes round corners amazingly well. Everytime we get in it, its like driving a sports car. A quiet and amazing sports car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a car this price, I wanted a few more things like an automatically closing and opening trunk and front trunk. But then you’ve got other things like a great tablet as a dashboard that’s fast and responsive and helpful. When you are on the phone its loud and clear. It’s got full time LTE for traffic routing. I could go on and on. And no we didn’t get autopilot, that is scary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This feels like a car from the future that doesn’t destroy the environment. Driving it is amazing and I still love it. Way more than I should.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh and my other favourite toy, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cervelo.com/en/road/s-series/s3&quot;&gt;my Cervélo S3&lt;/a&gt;, fits perfectly in the boot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you plan on buying one, here’s my &lt;a href=&quot;https://ts.la/andrew72696&quot;&gt;affiliate code&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Pedestrians vs Drivers</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub.ca/2018-06-29-pedestrians/"/>
<updated>2018-06-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub.ca/pedestrians</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So often these days the debate is framed as “drivers vs cyclists” or “drivers vs pedestrians”. Basically drivers vs everyone. Because if there’s one thing we’ve learnt is that drivers think all the roads, parking spaces and infrastructure is all for them and absolutely no-one else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you need to walk to get into a car. You need to get out of a car to walk when you get to your destination. Everyone becomes a pedestrian at some point. In fact everyone in a car gets out of a car, eventually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you can have a world where people go into their garages at their houses, drive to work and go into their garages there … and no-one ever interacts with anything other than cars in the real world. Or perhaps you can treat pedestrians with respect. And people on bicycles. And just about everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

</feed>
