<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Andy McKay</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/blog/andy" rel="alternate"></link>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/blog/rss/latest/andy/" rel="self"></link>
<updated>2025-08-25T00:58:35+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/blog/andy</id>
<author>
<name>Andy McKay</name>
<email>andy@clearwind.ca</email>
</author>

<entry>
<title>West Coast Trail - Third Time</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2025-08-24-west-coast-trail/"/>
<updated>2025-08-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/west-coast-trail</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So there I am in Europe feeling left out at seeing the beautiful hikes my friends are doing. June to September are the best months for hiking in BC when the snow has mostly gone, the weather is sunny and the mountains and coast are just beckoning. I noticed that there’s a spot on the West Coast Trail, so I snap it up and off I go. I first did the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2022-06-25-west-coast-trail/&quot;&gt;trail solo in 2022&lt;/a&gt; then &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2023-07-31-west-coast-trail/&quot;&gt;with a friend in 2023&lt;/a&gt;. This would be a solo trip and I booked it for 4 nights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again getting there was by public transport to Victoria then hop on the trail bus up to the start at Gordon River. Except this time, there were very few places to stay overnight in Victoria and it was &lt;em&gt;expensive&lt;/em&gt;. I would also be using my &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2024-06-17-a-backpack/&quot;&gt;30L backpack&lt;/a&gt;, 15L smaller than last time. The food filled out the side pockets and I strapped a dry bag or tent on the bottom. So it didn’t quite all fit in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-one-gordon-river-to-camper-bay&quot;&gt;Day One: Gordon River to Camper Bay&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;15495517227&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot; data-from-embed=&quot;false&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every time I’ve done the West Coast Trail I’ve gone this route. Every time I’ve gotten to the junction and Thrashers and found that the tides won’t work for going around Owen Point and every time continued onto Camper Bay. So same old, same old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weather forecast was rain and lots of it, so I was glad to get here while it was dry and thought I’d relax. I could have possibly gone one campsite more, but the Park staff were not recommending to stay at the next campsite because it requires a creek crossing. They were predicting that the creeks would get very high with the incoming rain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spent some time chatting to and helping a couple who were on their &lt;em&gt;first backpacking trip&lt;/em&gt; and rather than a nice simple overnight one somewhere to test out their gear chose this trail. I didn’t see them again, I hope they did ok.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-two-camper-bay-to-cribbs-south-side&quot;&gt;Day Two: Camper Bay to Cribbs south side&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;15495517267&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot; data-from-embed=&quot;false&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the hardest day I’ve done on the West Coast Trail. I started raining the evening before and did not stop. Over 75mm of rain was coming down over 24 hours. So my options were sit in a tent and wait it out (something a lot of people did) or just go for it. I just went for it and kept going. Once you are wet, may as well stay wet right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the hardest and most technical part of the trail and I just kept going. The forest was bad, with wet slippy muddy everything. I slipped down multiple times, sometimes in deep puddles of muddy water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I got to the beach and the creeks which were raging, to say the least. Creeks and waterfalls were appearing where they aren’t normally. It was all muddy and brown and the rain and wind was relentless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cable car at Carmanah Creek was broken but hikers coming the other way told me it was very tough, but doable. I made a bad choice and forded in the wrong spot at Carmanah Creek and in a few steps the water went over my knees and then suddenly it was over my waist. My backpack became slightly bouyant and lifted me up a bit, I almost lost footing. Fortunately my next steps got footing and I came out the other side, really shaken. I’d almost been swept away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept going to Cribbs campsite, because what else is there to do. Cribbs was the point were everyone north and south bound stopped, at this point in the afternoon it was so flooded that traversing was impossible. Multiple groups at Camper Bay said they’d go to Cribbs the next day - only seven people made it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got my tent up in the wind in rain and took a nap. Apart from my sleeping gear, everything was wet. Later on it stopped raining and the sun came out for a little but before sunset. I was mentally and physically wiped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-three-cribbs-south-side-to-tsocowis-creek&quot;&gt;Day Three: Cribbs south side to Tsocowis Creek&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;15495517241&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot; data-from-embed=&quot;false&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;15495433867&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot; data-from-embed=&quot;false&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sun never really came out and everything was wet and damp, what is there to do but walk. So walk I did. Cribbs creek had gone down so that crossing twice here just meant water splashing up to the knees. On the beaches there were regularly creeks to cross so my boots never dried out until I got home. Everyone camps at Tsusiat, so I went further and decided to stop somewhere different at Tsocowis. It was raining a little bit for 10 minutes here and there throughout the day, nothing too bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This part has some of the most beautiful parts of the trail on it as you alternate between headlands, the forest and cliffs. Was just an absolute joy to do again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sun came out again when I camped and for a couple of hours I tried to dry things out, but it was late in the day and the sun was to feeble to make much difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-four-tsocowis-creek-to-pachena-bay&quot;&gt;Day Four: Tsocowis Creek to Pachena Bay&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;15495517156&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot; data-from-embed=&quot;false&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was a day ahead of schedule and didn’t have a problem with that. The walk from here to Pachena is very nice and straightforward - apart from a recent mudslide near Michigan which has made it a muddy mess to access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sun came out in Pachena Bay as I encountered bears on the trail. I had a few hours to lie in the sun and dry my gear out (well almost) while I waited for the trail bus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did the trail in 4 days, just 3 nights, and that felt good for my pace. I hike faster and pack lighter than many and it worked for me. This experience in the rain did validate a few things for me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you can’t see the bottom of a creek, think twice&lt;/strong&gt;. I should have slowed down and not just followed footsteps.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always ensure your sleeping gear stays dry&lt;/strong&gt;. A backpack cover is &lt;em&gt;not enough&lt;/em&gt;. My sleeping gear is always in a dry bag inside my backpack. If you are getting rain like I had, up to your waist in puddles or almost being washed away in a river, everything will be wet. When I camped at Cribbs, I was the &lt;em&gt;only one who&lt;/em&gt; had a dry sleeping bag and clothes. Everyone else was sleeping in wet gear and that’s a common cause of hypothermia.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If it’s on the outside of your backpack, clip it on&lt;/strong&gt;. Just assume it will wiggle free of a strap, so attach it to your backpack by a strap and a clip.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dry bags seperate the wet from the dry&lt;/strong&gt;. Stopping dry stuff in your backback getting wet is important. Want to keep something dry? Stick it in the bag. Got something wet and you want to keep everything else dry? Stick it in a dry bag. This was very, very useful on subsequent days.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Camino Francés</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2025-08-10-camino/"/>
<updated>2025-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/camino</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In June my wife and I decided to do 126km+ on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://caminoways.com/camino-frances&quot;&gt;Camino Francés&lt;/a&gt; as part of our trip to Europe. As someone who backpacks a lot in Canada, the Camino could not be more different. I’ll hike up mountains with my backpack and see no-one for a day, my only company being mosquitoes and bears. The Camino is almost the exact opposite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that was exactly why we decided to go for it, if you are unsure if a long multi day hike is for you - the Camino provides plenty of support systems. You can just hop in a taxi or bus between towns. You can send your baggage along to each hostel so you don’t have to carry it. There’s tons of places to stop and eat. Those things don’t happen in the backcountry of Canada when you are 50km away from a cell phone signal or a road 😀&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this trip we didn’t book accomodation ahead, other than the first night because we were unsure how far we’d get each day. We were in Europe for a longer trip, so we divided our luggage into a 40L and 60L backpack. We then shipped the 60L onto &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.elcaminoconcorreos.com/en/transfer-luggage&quot;&gt;Santiago de Compostela&lt;/a&gt; for pickup whenever we got there using the Spanish post office. That meant we just had a 40L backpack for our 6 day trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-1-sarria--portomarin&quot;&gt;Day 1: Sarria 👉 Portomarin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;14745907509&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot; data-from-embed=&quot;false&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started out a little late and got a little lost in Sarria trying to find the &lt;a href=&quot;https://caminoways.com/camino-pilgrim-passport-certificates&quot;&gt;Pilgrim Passport&lt;/a&gt;, but got this figured out and stamped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This turned out to be the quietest section of the Camino for us, &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;/strong&gt; of people start in Portomarin, since 100km is now the shortest distance to obtain a certificate and Portomarin is 100km away from Santiago de Compostela.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Camino is a combination of roads and tracks. Whenever you meet someone on the trail you call out “Buen Camino” and it took a while on the first day to get the hang of that. This was a hot day and the last few km were a real drag heading down into Portomarin. Unfortunately in the last 8km we didn’t really spot much accomodation choices so continuing onto Portomarin became our goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Portomarin was crowded and almost everywhere was full. While my wife had a rest, I went around to so many places looking for a spare bed. One of the first hotels had one room left, but was super expensive. After going to at least more than a dozen places that were full, we gave up and got the expensive room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dinner was a bit of a miss that night, but we were both tired after the heat so we didn’t care too much. By this point I’d learnt:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;as someone who doesn’t drink alcohol Spain does excellent non-alcholoic beers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;as someone who doesn’t eat meat, your eating out options are very limited in Spain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some blisters were starting to form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-2-portomarin--palas-de-rei&quot;&gt;Day 2: Portomarin 👉 Palas de Rei&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;14755405237&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot; data-from-embed=&quot;false&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This day had a bit more of an elevation change and was also hot. There were a lot of people leaving Portomarin in the morning. Something of a theme, people stay in the same place and all leave around the same time as they work their way along the trail. That means cafes and rest spots along the trail tend to get busy in waves as people arrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although we weren’t the fastest, we weren’t the slowest and the crowds would usually thin throughout the day somewhat. Sometimes we were on quiet stretches, sometimes it got quite busy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the struggles finding a spot to sleep yesterday, we booked a spot ahead of time. Silly me booked for a place that’s not in the middle of town though and is roughly a 15 EUR taxi ride out of town. Oops. Silly mistake, but it was quiet and had good food. But another nice feature of the trail, there’s lots of accomodations somewhere nearby and for this stretch there are so many people on it that there is a huge support system there for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spoke to lots of people on this hike, which is nice and part of it’s charm. This night we chatted to a person from Montreal who was doing the same distance as us. A couple from Australia who’d come from the French border and had been going for a couple of weeks. And a lady who’d come from &lt;b&gt;La Frézelle, France and had been on the go for over two months to complete the roughly 1,500km+ trip&lt;/b&gt; 😱&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My wife was getting a bad blister. Two long days in hot sun had left us drained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-3-palas-de-rei--melide&quot;&gt;Day 3: Palas de Rei 👉 Melide&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;14764333070&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot; data-from-embed=&quot;false&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weather wasn’t as hot today and my shoulders were sore from a backpack I’m not used to. We’d decided to set our sets on a shorter day and booked a spot in Melide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again there were swarms of people leaving Palas de Rei and the beginning was very busy, but as usual thinned out. Parts of the Spanish countryside were lovely and we were really enjoying the tracks, trees and trails. It’s well sign posted all the way and you’ll have to work hard to get lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Melide was a good distance for us, but turned out to not have great restaurant or hotel choices compared to other places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blisters were still there, although mine were starting to toughen up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-4-melide--arúza&quot;&gt;Day 4: Melide 👉 Arúza&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;14774800650&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot; data-from-embed=&quot;false&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was another shorter day of about 15km to help us recover from the first couple of days. Interestingly staying at Melide had meant that we’d not stayed in accomodation where most people stop. That meant that it was quieter for much of our walk as we were out of sync with others. Until we hit a group of school children who got off a bus and are rather chatty and loud 😢&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arúza is a nice town with some a nice church and some good cafes, we had a great pizza in an Italian restaurant. Our hotel also had a great view across the fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got some stuff to help the blister in a pharmacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-5-arúza--o-pedrouzo&quot;&gt;Day 5: Arúza 👉 O Pedrouzo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;14786304413&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot; data-from-embed=&quot;false&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O Pedrouzo was actually going to be our first and only stop in a hostel, staying in bunk beds. As opposed to hotels which we’d been in since then. This is a popular place to stop as it’s about 20km walk from here to the destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although people of ages were staying at the hostel in the bunk beds - people in the hotels had bags (often suitcases) shipped on by a service and were older. The hostel had more young people with backpacks. The Camino is for pilgrims of all ages and gets lots of tourists who want support. It has religious people for whom the pilgrimage is important and people who don’t care for religion but like a good hike (that’s me).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of this 19km segment, I felt like I had quite a bit of pent up energy and was feeling better after 2 long days in the sun at the beginning of the week. So I got a nice &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/14786716859&quot;&gt;4.20km run with a fast pace after the hike which was good&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally had a vegetarian paella for dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-6-o-pedrouzo--santiago-de-compostela&quot;&gt;Day 6: O Pedrouzo 👉 Santiago de Compostela&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;14797920459&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot; data-from-embed=&quot;false&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lovely day that started out cloudy, keeping us nice and cool. I thought it would be a bit wierd walking around the airport, but apart from one bit close to the runway it was a lovely walk through fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’d gotten a hotel right on the trail in town about 800m away from the destination. But the walk in through Santiago is long and at one point my wife was limping really badly from blisters and really just done with it. An old lady said “You’ve been walking too much” at my wife and that’s pretty much how she felt at that point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We dropped our bag at the hotel and carried on into Santiago to go see the cathedral and the end point for the pilgrammage. It’s an impressive cathedral that’s for sure. It’s probably got more power for religious people, for me it was just endpoint, an impressive one admittedly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blister on my wifes foot was horrid by this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day we got our certificates of the pilgramage and was able to spend a bit more time exploring the cathedral, it’s grounds and the old city in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was by far the longest multi-day hike my wife has done. It’s also the longest I’ve done (previous record the West Coast trail at 75km or so) but I’m more used to walking long distances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m super proud of her having the courage to give it a go and sticking with it, even when she was in clear pain at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s so very different from hiking in Canada. Walking between small town, after small town with little churches and cafes dotted around is just not an experience I get much. It’s not wilderness backpacking, that’s for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would do it again, but I would be hesitant about the last few days of the Camino Francés because it’s so busy. About 70% of pilgrims do that section and in the busy months, it’s very busy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the good news is there are &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camino_de_Santiago#/media/File:Camino_de_Santiago_%E2%80%93_Map_of_main_routes_WP.svg&quot;&gt;many routes&lt;/a&gt;. How about the route from Lisbon through Portugal, or from Seville north through Spain, or from Biarritz along the coast, or from the Pyrennes…. these all sound fantastic and I could happily do those if I have the chance.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Elections Canada</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2025-04-28-elections-canada/"/>
<updated>2025-04-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/elections-canada</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today is voting day for the Federal Election in Canada. For this election I worked as a Deputy Returning Officer for &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elections_Canada&quot;&gt;Elections Canada&lt;/a&gt;, the non-partisan body government body that runs federal elections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to get involved because elections are important and maintaining a good electoral system is something that is easy to take for granted. The repeated lies and destruction of democracy that we are seeing in the US is something that I don’t want to see here. I’m hoping that when this election is completed, transfer of power is quick, with grace, and no sowing of lies or disinformation from either party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elections Canada is interesting, it’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.elections.ca/content.aspx?section=res&amp;amp;dir=rep/off/cou&amp;amp;document=index44&amp;amp;lang=e&quot;&gt;budget for an election is around $492 million&lt;/a&gt; so it’s costing roughly $20 per voter to maintain our federal democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The advance voting happened over Easter weekend and there were long queues at our polling station. Of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burnaby_North%E2%80%94Seymour&quot;&gt;77k voters&lt;/a&gt;, over &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.elections.ca/content.aspx?section=med&amp;amp;document=ge45_advpol&amp;amp;lang=e&quot;&gt;30k voted&lt;/a&gt;, so that’s about 38% of voters in our riding. On election day the number of polling stations and staff dramatically increases, with 10-20x (my estimate) or more the amount of staff helping out. The result during advance voting was long lineups, frustrated voters and frazzled staff. Which of course led to questions like: why isn’t this electronic?, why isn’t this more efficient? and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that gets to the interesting question of how voting works in a democracy. Be it one as geographically vast as Canada, or as huge a population as India. It’s not easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elections Canada has &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elections_Canada#Appointments_and_staff&quot;&gt;permanent staff of 500&lt;/a&gt; which rises to 235,000 during an election. Once the writ is dropped (the election announced) there is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elections_in_Canada&quot;&gt;minimum of 36 days&lt;/a&gt; to election day. There is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.elections.ca/content.aspx?section=abo&amp;amp;dir=oec&amp;amp;document=p2&amp;amp;lang=e&quot;&gt;planning and readiness phase that Elections Canada&lt;/a&gt; gets into, so that when the writ drops, it’s ready to go. But that’s a &lt;strong&gt;huge and rapid&lt;/strong&gt; scaling of people and staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that got me thinking about the system. How do you build a system that can scale from 500 people to 235,000 people? How do you ensure over 27 million people are able to vote across this vast country? How do you ensure its transparent, yet private and secure? How do you ensure it’s free from corruption and interference?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elections aren’t like everything else and efficiency isn’t necessarily a key goal. Let me give you one example, in the current election process casting a ballot goes like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Deputy Returning Officer hands you a ballot with their initials and poll number written in pen on the back.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You go behind a screen and mark the candidate of your choice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You fold the ballot up so no-one can see the ballot and then hand it back to the Deputy Returning Officer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Deputy Returning Officer tears off the counterfoil and checks the number on the counterfoil, then hands the ballot back to you.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You place it in the ballot box.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not the most efficient system, but then ask yourself some questions like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do you ensure that only one ballot goes in the box?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do you ensure that the ballot that goes in the box is the one you gave to the voter?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do you ensure that Deputy Returning Officer isn’t corrupt and manipulating your ballot?
…and so on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And all of a sudden the ideas you’ve got in your head about how to speed it up, start to get a bit more complicated. I’m sure there are ways to make it faster, but you’ve just got a bunch more scenarios to think through first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve gotten past things like security, privacy and interference, then remember scale. You’ve got to scale this rapidly and for a large number of people across multiple languages and situation. Any system has to be easy to understand and be trained on in a couple of hours for so many people. It’s got to be flexible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ve got to have thousands and thousands of polling stations across Canada. But what about long term care homes, people sick in hospital, prisoners, work camps out in the bush and so on. People stuck in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/north/poll-workers-fly-helicopter-west-dawson-voters-1.7516049&quot;&gt;remote areas in the Yukon&lt;/a&gt; needed helicopters to fly in election officials. Any system has to be simple, robust and flexible as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s pretty impressive system, even if it can be frustratingly people intensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned India, because it has 969 million eligible votes and is the worlds largest democracy. By law each voter can be no more that 2km away from a polling both. That meant one team had to do a two day trip into the forest so &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aljazeera.com/gallery/2024/5/8/an-election-booth-inside-a-forest-in-india-for-just-one-voter&quot;&gt;that they could get the vote of one monk&lt;/a&gt;. Voting in India &lt;a href=&quot;https://apnews.com/article/india-election-2024-explainer-41d7aa3131dc0c7e0df1ea4be6b6a4c7&quot;&gt;takes months&lt;/a&gt; and is a whole other scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall I’m glad to have helped take part in making democracy work, tonight I head off to help in the counting process. I’ll probably get involved again.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Mueller Hut</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2025-03-27-mueller-hut/"/>
<updated>2025-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/mueller-hut</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.doc.govt.nz/parks-and-recreation/places-to-go/canterbury/places/aoraki-mount-cook-national-park/things-to-do/tracks/mueller-hut-route/&quot;&gt;Mueller Hut Route&lt;/a&gt; is a hike near Aoraki (Mount Cook) that was recommended by a friend. It’s again a straight up then straight down hike, but this time the hike is interesting (compared to &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2025-03-25-roys-peak/&quot;&gt;Roys Peak&lt;/a&gt;)and has a hut at top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started this hike by camping overnight near Aoraki Village. The trail goes straight up the side of a mountain and will have the sun beating down on it - so I decided to head out at 6:30am and get as much of the steep part of the hike before the sun comes up. My plantar fasciitis was playing up and hurting quite a lot, so it took me longer to get out of bed and get moving than I thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trail is straight up. The first 500m is stairs snaking up the mountain. The next 500m is working up the slope over rocks and grass, followed by boulders and scree. Fortunately the sun takes a bit longer to hit the trail because it’s behind another mountain. This meant I got to about 650m in elevation before the sun hit. I also got to see an amazing sunrise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;13753905724&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot; data-from-embed=&quot;false&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the top you hit the ridge which goes around the “back” and up towards the hut. This is all big rocks and amazing views. It also was, very, very windy and the temperature dropped dramatically. Once you’ve gotten up to that its a view of mountains, glaciers and just amazing scenery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were bunches of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kea&quot;&gt;Kea&lt;/a&gt; flying around and they were very cool to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hut looks like a great place to stay, however it seems to get booked quite far in advance and I didn’t have chance to book that, so made it into a day trip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going up there were only a few other people on the hike, which was lovely. On the way down it got more and more crowded the further down I went with more and more people coming up. Recommend doing it early to avoid the crowds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the Department of Conservation guidance is 10-12 hours return. I got to the top, looked around and got back to the campsite in under 5 hours. Perhaps a lot of people do this trail unprepared physically and lacking the right gear so they use guidance to give people more realistic ideas of the trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would recommend and do again.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Alpine crossing</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2025-03-27-alpine-crossing/"/>
<updated>2025-03-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/alpine-crossing</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.doc.govt.nz/tongariroalpinecrossing&quot;&gt;Tongariro Alpine crossing&lt;/a&gt; is apparently one of the most popular and well known hikes in New Zealand. My last two hikes (&lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2025-03-25-roys-peak/&quot;&gt;Roys&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2025-03-27-mueller-hut/&quot;&gt;Mueller&lt;/a&gt;) were on the South island, this one is on the North island. Because I had a day spare, I also got in a bit of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.doc.govt.nz/tongarironortherncircuit&quot;&gt;Tongariro North Circuit&lt;/a&gt; as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both of these are trails in the Tongariro National Park under the towering volcanoes of Mt Ngauruhoe, Mt Tongariro and Mt Ruapheu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was able to book a night in the campsite at the Mangatepopo Hut. So I started from Whakapapa Village, headed up to Taranki Falls and then over to the Mangatepopo Hut where I set up camp and spent the night. The hike to the falls was lovely, lots of beautiful forest and streams with a good waterfall. The rest of the Northern Circuit I found quite boring - Mt Ngauruhoe just got slowly closer as the rest of the scenery barely changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;13839389346&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot; data-from-embed=&quot;false&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time the website said “The section of track between Whakapapa Village and Mangatepopo Hut is not up to our usual Great Walk standards”. The standard was much higher than any hike I’ve been on, except maybe Stanley Park. Certainly higher than the conditions of say, the West Coast Trail. My plantar fasciitis was the worse its been at the end of this day, I hobbled around the campsite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day I headed up to the Alpine Crossing and the hike went from nice to epic. I loaded up with some drugs and topical muscle relaxant and went for it. Unfortunately there is a road near the Mangatepopo Hut and at first light hordes of hikes were disgorged from buses and my quite hike turned into a bit of conga line for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;13847643978&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot; data-from-embed=&quot;false&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hike goes up a ridge of volcanic rock up to a crater and just starts to become amazing. The crater with volcanoes on either side is something to behold, then you climb up another ridge next to the red crater. And that’s where the temperature started to drop rapidly and the wind picked up. Seriously windy. It was at the point where a slight change in direction and I’d feel the wind hit me and my backpack and almost knock me off me feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one side is the red crater, with plumes of steam coming off it. At the top you greeted with multiple emerald colour lakes, more steam plumes an epic views of volcanoes in front of you. For someone who isn’t good with vertical drops, I wasn’t worried 👍&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming down was a long hike and not too exciting, but there were amazing views of Lake Taupo and it ended with lush forests. By the end my foot was very sore and I was really glad to see my wife (who also was nice enough to do the shuttle).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would recommend and do again with a few of caveats:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When the rangers talk about bad weather at the top believe them. It turned very fast for me. I can imagine a lot of people get into trouble on this one. It starts nice and sunny at the bottom, but changes very rapidly up there.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Because of the aforementioned changes in weather, please bring appropriate gear. Many day hikers were not well equipped.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It will be crowded, live with it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spent the evening in geo-thermal hot springs and my foot couldn’t have been happier.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Roys Peak</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2025-03-25-roys-peak/"/>
<updated>2025-03-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/roys-peak</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Roys Peak was my first big hike on a trip to New Zealand. It came about in an interesting way, we were looking for a campground near &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/place/W%C4%81naka,+New+Zealand/@-44.7234134,168.9779258,11z/&quot;&gt;Wanaka&lt;/a&gt; and read that “we kept being woken up by people waking up at 4am to go hiking”. That had me intrigued and I had to find out what hike it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turn’s out a few years ago some Instagrammer took a picture of themselves at a view point at sunrise. As a result, many people are hiking this peak to get the shot. &lt;em&gt;Shudder&lt;/em&gt;. You will, as a result, also find a billion articles on line about it. In the end to avoid all those people I decided to hike up before sunset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heading up at sunset was a great idea because this trail is completely open, with no trees or cover. At this time of year, about 5:30pm the sun starts to set behind the ridge, meaning that the hike up was in the shade and that was wonderful. The hike is really boring, it’s a wide 4x4 trail all the way. It’s continuous grade with little variation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;13734523496&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot; data-from-embed=&quot;false&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stopped at the viewpoint to watch the sunset. On the website it’s unclear if you can camp at the peak, but I spoke to someone who was told by locals that you could, so I camped there overnight. The hike was boring, but the views and sunset was absolutely bloody fantastic. Seriously one of the best sunsets I’ve seen, ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But of course the Instagrammers couldn’t be avoided. I’d expected people to arrive early and at 5 o’clock a group of people hiked up and said “Oh look a tent”. Then stood by my tent and chatted, loudly. Then the blue tooth speaker person joined. Then more. &lt;em&gt;Aaargh&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I took my tent down, looked in horror at the many headlamps I could see coming up the trail and headed on up to the peak to watch the sunrise. The peak was full of people and blue tooth speaker person, so I headed to another bump a little away, put in my noise cancelling headphones and enjoyed the sunrise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;13735883572&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot; data-from-embed=&quot;false&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a spectacular sunrise, but not as good as the sunset. The walk down was long, boring, crowded, and monotonous. You aren’t doing this hike for the trail, you are doing it for the view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wouldn’t do it again, unless a friend wanted to see the view. Which was stunning. I think this hike also gave me plantar fasciitis from the just continuous down grade. Not sure, but it started not long after this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.doc.govt.nz/parks-and-recreation/places-to-go/otago/places/wanaka-area/things-to-do/isthmus-peak-and-glen-dene-ridge-tracks/&quot;&gt;Isthmus Peak for an alternative&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>A salute for Elon</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2025-02-02-a-salute-for-elon/"/>
<updated>2025-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/a-salute-for-elon</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;tl:dr; We sold our Tesla because we can no longer be associated in any way with Elon Musk or his companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/tesla-salute.jpg&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got our model 3 in 2018, which meant we were amongst the first in BC. At the time I loved it, the car was absolute night and day from any other car. I said so in an old &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2018-07-25-tesla/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; where I called it “Amazeballs” and also regrettably this about Elon “This is a man on a mission to do good.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have no problem with buying that car - at the time it was the best electric car on the market. It had the best battery and range and great software. It got updated regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mechanical and design problems abounded in the car that emerged over time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The heating broke and we couldn’t defrost.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Both horns weren’t actually connected in the factory, so the horn was super quiet.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moisture built up in the rear light blocks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The trunk leaked, when it rained we’d have to sponge out inches of water from the trunk.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The car would freeze into a lump and you couldn’t get into the car due to the handle and window design.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software would update &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2022-01-08-how-tesla-is-trying-to-kill-you/&quot;&gt;moving or hiding key functionality&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of 2025 it was clear where Elon was heading and I was starting to look into selling the car. He’d already destroyed Twitter, a place where I had an account for 16 years. He’d repeatedly done so many terrible things in Tesla with the treatment of the workforce, safety rules, and so on. Then the support for Trump came along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The line was crossed with the Nazi salute. Apologists keep arguing it isn’t, but in the context of how he behaves like supporting Tommy Robinson, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2024/dec/28/elon-musk-germany-afd-party&quot;&gt;the AfD editorial&lt;/a&gt;, appearing at an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2025/01/27/nx-s1-5276084/elon-musk-german-far-right-afd-holocaust&quot;&gt;AfD rally and saying that&lt;/a&gt; “frankly too much of a focus on past guilt and we need to move beyond that” it’s clear where his political views lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NjWl_RNDMSA&quot;&gt;Led by Donkeys sum it up well in this video&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/heiltesla-1024x576-1398596338.jpg&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He’s part of an administration that has belittled and attacked Canada. They want to turn Canada into a state through “economic force” and have pushed tariffs onto their biggest ally. He isn’t just donating money and sitting on the sideline, &lt;strong&gt;he’s an active participant&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point my car is over 6.5 years old, the money already went to Tesla. Tesla’s board is trying to pay &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/roberthart/2024/06/13/heres-whats-next-after-musk-claims-tesla-shareholders-approve-massive-pay-package/&quot;&gt;Musk $50 billion dollars&lt;/a&gt;. But every repair, every time I use a super charger, that money goes to Tesla and a bit to Musk. Just driving around in a Tesla associates me with that person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we took a loss, sold the car and bought a Kia EV6. Very happy with it so far. Is Kia perfect? No, no  large car company is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tesla sent a survey after we sold it, when they asked why I bought a Kia I replied simply “The company isn’t run by a Nazi”.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Phone plans in Canada</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2025-01-06-changing-phone-plans/"/>
<updated>2025-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/changing-phone-plans</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you aren’t in a phone contract, you should look at changing phone companies every year or so. Otherwise, you’ll just be getting screwed by Canadian phone companies that are not going to improve your plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s easy to switch phone companies, keep your existing phone number and it’s the only way to get a better deal.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-it-works&quot;&gt;How it works&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the big pre-paid companies are really backed by the major networks. Koodo and Public Mobile uses Telus networks. Fido uses Rogers. These companies are the ones that offer cheaper pre-paid plans and are the way to go if you don’t want to get tied into a contract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember contracts are one-sided and designed to screw you anyway, for example: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/toronto/rogers-bell-telus-contracts-prices-1.7369942&quot;&gt;they can go up in price&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These companies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use the major networks, so you get the same phone, internet coverage as the backing network.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can be serviced by the backing networks. For example: when I had Fido problems, I went to the Rogers store and got it fixed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phone companies are NOT like Netflix who (as of writing) have 3 plans that are clear, stay consistent and are easy to follow &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.netflix.com/en/node/24926&quot;&gt;on one page&lt;/a&gt; and you can change between them as you need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phone companies are NOT like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The create and remove plans continually.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;They choose&lt;/strong&gt; who gets what plan when.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is done to make it really hard to compare plans, make it possible to target particular users and to tie people into expensive plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;my-story&quot;&gt;My Story&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;koodo-telus&quot;&gt;Koodo (Telus)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was on Koodo forever. It worked, it had enough data and I didn’t worry about it worked. In the summer I re-evaluated all my plans and subscriptions and found that I’d been on Koodo so long, I wasn’t even valid in their system anymore, it had been updated multiple times and they hadn’t updated my account (something something software developers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That took a few weeks to resolve and then I was able to see the deal wasn’t that great and that better deals were available elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key point: &lt;strong&gt;In the many years with Koodo, they had never upgraded, updated or improved my account. They just left me on the same plan for all those years.&lt;/strong&gt; That’s not a good way to retain customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Annoyed by their attitude I switched to Fido.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fido-rogers&quot;&gt;Fido (Rogers)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September I switched to Fido. The result was more data and free UK calling for about $15 a month less. When you switch you can keep your phone number and use an eSIM to move over. The eSIM didn’t work first time, but the Rogers store fixed that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a couple of months my family in the UK told me it was easier to call on WhatsApp than a phone. So I didn’t need UK minutes anymore. No problem, I’ll switch to the cheaper plan that was advertised when I joined up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That plan doesn’t exist. I can’t switch to it, even though my wife is on it. Fido won’t let me. I contacted customer support and they said &lt;strong&gt;“We think you are on a good plan and should be happy it.”&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was not happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;public-mobile-telus&quot;&gt;Public Mobile (Telus)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the holidays I switched to Public Mobile. This was done in 20 minutes while watching something on YouTube. The eSIM worked first time and the number transferred. My monthly rate went down another $15 or so a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m now getting more data than with Koodo or Fido, and paying 1/3 of what I was paying with Koodo in the summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the process, I’ve had one problem, resolved by the Rogers store in 5 minutes. I’ve kept my phone number and not had to change it. I will probably review my plan regularly. Apparently the best time to switch is August and September in the “back to school period”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summary: &lt;strong&gt;You should change companies, they are relying on you not switching to make more money.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Cinque Terre</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-12-04-cinque/"/>
<updated>2024-12-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/cinque</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cinque_Terre&quot;&gt;Cinque Terre&lt;/a&gt; is a series of five villages on the north western Italian coastline. The best way to visit the villages is to take the train that connects La Spezia and Genoa. The best way to get between the villages is to hike them (or take the train).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November, I was able to hike between all five villages. Apparently the trails can often be closed and due to a rainstorm a few days early, the easiest path between the last two villages Manarola and Riomaggiore was closed. This last part “Via dell’Amore” has been closed since 2019 and was re-opened briefly in 2024.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To hike the paths in Cinque Terre &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cinqueterre.eu.com/en/cinque-terre-card#cinque-terre-trekking-card&quot;&gt;you will need a trekking card&lt;/a&gt;. When I hiked there was only one checkpoint on the whole trail, I’m sure there are more during the summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;12798154588&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot; data-from-embed=&quot;false&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started off at the North West end in Monterosso, myself hiking and my wife taking the train. We were able to meet up at one village in the middle and at the end. We were both able to move at the pace we wanted to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first I thought I’d try running this route, but this quickly became an idea I abandoned. The first section between Monterosso and Vernazza was the busiest part of the route. It was full of people moving at their pace. The route is very narrow with no passing places in many areas. It’s also lots of elevation change and lots and lots of steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Vernazza there were a lot less people, which was great. At this point the November Italian sun was starting to beat down on me. Pleasant, but still fun. At Corniglia, the trail goes right past a church and a water fountain which was lovely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corniglia to Manarola is the longest part of the trail with a big assent out of Corniglia, a lovely flat part and then a very long descent down into Manarola. All the ascents and descents are stairs, so many stairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Manarola I went over to the Via dell’Amore to find it closed. So backtracked and took the old path over the hill. This is the steepest ascent, a view at the top and then a steep descent. We were rewarded with an amazing sunset in Riomaggiore and then some Italian gelato.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Views all along the trail were absolutely breath taking. Just beautiful views of villages, the sea, hills. You walk along terraces through vineyards, through forests, past houses and then pop out into amazing villages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recommended, but expect it to be busy at the height of the season for a lot of it and expect a lot of sun.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Another Tent</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-09-06-another-tent/"/>
<updated>2024-09-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/another-tent</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago I &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2022-04-04-a-tent/&quot;&gt;got a tent&lt;/a&gt;. It had its problems and I needed another one. There were some problems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s not as easy to setup as I thought.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s not freestanding.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It doesn’t cope well with wind.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It sometimes doesn’t cope well with humid climates, like this one.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Using hiking poles for the tent poles isn’t as good as an idea as I thought.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wind can be a problem, in wind and rain it could be really bad. In windy places, I found the tent is like a big wind sock especially when it hits the side of the tent. This is due to having a pole at each end and no rigidity in-between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being held up by hiking poles wasn’t the weight or space saving I thought it would be. Long thin poles are easy to put anywhere. They don’t weigh much (200g). Being able to use poles for a day hike and leave your tent up is quite useful. Also, losing or breaking a pole hiking now has bad consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The deal breaker is not being freestanding. The tent requires well anchored tent pegs at the front and back to provide tension for the poles to stay up. This makes it hard to put up and won’t stay up well in: sand (beaches on the West Coast Trail), places with wooden pads (Garibaldi, Manning), mountain tops with no soil (Seymour, Golden Ears). Places I wanted to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So time for another tent. Enter the Big Agnes 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bigagnes.com/collections/ultralight-tents/products/fly-creek-hv-ul1-solution-dye&quot;&gt;Fly Creek HV UL1 tent&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This tent is great for three seasons, easier to put up, light weight and more rigid and able to cope with the wind and semi freestanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s semi freestanding because the fly requires pegs to hold away from the main, but that’s pretty common.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes it is 200g or so heavier than my Tarp Tent, which sucks, but being able to go to toilet without it falling down is a huge win for me. This happened to me on the West Coast Trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/big-agnes.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far I’m extremely happy with this tent, in Garibaldi with some strong gusts of wind, it was nice and solid. In wet weather at Elsay Lake it was fine. It’s well designed and thought out. Really can’t spot any problems with yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s actually smaller than the Tarp Tent and that’s good, it’s easier to pitch. It fits me and my sleeping pad and gear just fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big 👍 from me, so far.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Elsay Lake</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-09-05-elsay-lake/"/>
<updated>2024-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/elsay-lake</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Since my experience on &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2024-07-17-my-limit/&quot;&gt;Howe Sound Crest Trail&lt;/a&gt; I’ve not hiked as much or cared about peaks. So I was glad to be able to do a quick overnight up to Elsay Lake which is nearby and a lake I’ve seen from above - but never visited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also it’s a good overnight trip that I can do straight from my house and end up in the almost back country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;12318210614&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was an overcast day and heading up from Deep Cove I went from patchy sun, into deep cloud, into sun, into deep cloud and ended up at an overcast remote lake. I’ve all but the last 5km or so of this trail before and knew what to expect, until I hit that last 5km.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t hard, but for about 2km its just harder, steeper and less clearly marked than I expected. As you go around Mt Elsay, the trail drops down steeply about 150m of elevation. Overall going from the parking lot down to Elsay Lake means losing about 800m of elevation, the lake it’s self being at 765m elevation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I got to the lake I somehow tripped forward over a log and nailed the landing, no injuries. Or so I thought, I walked forward a few meters and was curious why the back of my leg stung. Somehow I had multiple gashes, 2 inches and 8 inches long on the back of my leg with bloody everywhere. Nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lake itself is lovely, quiet, serene and peaceful. The water was warm after all that hot summer weather. I camped next to the emergency shelter that night so I could use the porch to cook on. It was so quiet, not even sound from the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next day due to a bleeding leg, I decided to get a ride from Mt. Seymour resort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;12318247010&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think most people do the hike to and from Mt. Seymour and I’d definitely recommend that unless you are wanting that extra distance.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Jasper Fire</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-08-12-jasper-fires/"/>
<updated>2024-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/jasper-fires</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On July 22 a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/newsinteractives/features/the-monster-of-jasper&quot;&gt;monstrous fire ripped through Jasper&lt;/a&gt;. This was a terrible tragedy for residents, visitors and the environment in and around Jasper. I’ve got a huge amount of sympathy and empathy for those affected. A firefighter was killed battling the fire and that’s also terrible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hashtag called #JasperStrong went around on social media and I’m more just #JasperSad than anything, because of the damage that has been inflicted on Canadians and Albertans, by those who contribute to climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For context, Alberta has the largest emissions of green house gases in Canada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/ghg-emissions.png&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s oil and gas industry is huge and is exporting oil and gas around the world. The Trans Mountain pipeline that Canadians tax payers paid &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theglobeandmail.com/business/article-canada-trans-mountain-pipeline-expansion/&quot;&gt;$34 billion&lt;/a&gt; for terminates very close to my house and will be pumping out fossil fuels for many decades to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years we have seen climate change affect so many parts of the world. But when it hits farmers in Central America, or causes floods in Asia or whatever a long way away, it can feel like it’s not really a problem. Something I don’t need to worry about. Something I can ignore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then when climate change hits the people close to you, so viscerally and so raw like this, you’d think it would change opinions. You’d think people would wake up and realise that we can’t avoid this, we need to stop it now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’d think so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like after the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2016_Fort_McMurray_wildfire&quot;&gt;Fort McMurray fire&lt;/a&gt; which at an estimated cost of $9.9 billion was the costliest disaster in Canadian history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like after the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lytton_wildfire&quot;&gt;Lytton fire&lt;/a&gt; which completely destroyed the town of Lytton (somewhere I’ve visited, it’s heartbreaking).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like after the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/british-columbia/bc-heat-dome-sudden-deaths-revised-2021-1.6232758&quot;&gt;heat dome&lt;/a&gt; that killed 595 people in British Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These aren’t heat events in far off places in the world, they are extreme events right in our own country and made much, much, worse by climate change. The thing that &lt;a href=&quot;https://albertabeyondfossilfuels.ca/alberta-and-the-carbon-budget/&quot;&gt;Alberta and Canada&lt;/a&gt; is contributing too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alberta’s Danielle Smith, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://duckduckgo.com/?t=ffab&amp;amp;q=danielle+smith+climate+change&amp;amp;ia=web&quot;&gt;elected leader of Jasper won’t talk about it, or diminishes it&lt;/a&gt;. The leader of the federal opposition talks about axing the Carbon tax, but not what they’ll do about actually get Canada to reduce its emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find it incredibly sad, that when we are faced with the evidence of the harm and damage to our own country we still can’t do anything about it. Alberta has continued down this path and elected politicians who continues to ignore it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why the Jasper fire made me #JasperSad.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Russet Lake</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-08-10-russet-lake/"/>
<updated>2024-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/russet-lake</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I haven’t done much back packing in Garibaldi, so extended a trip to Whistler with a chance to hike in the back country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;12081165554&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t leave until around lunch time, so I took the chance to take the gondola up to the Roundhouse at Whistler. Then it’s a good opportunity to get lost in all the trails around the top of the mountain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve got out of that it gradually gets quieter as you do the High Note trail, then quieter on the Musical Bumps trail to Russet Lake. This is a lovely trail that’s accessible to many people, it’s not at all technical and has amazing meadows with views of amazing glaciers and mountains on either side. It’s stunning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Camping at Russet Lake is nice, it was windy in the evening which kept the bugs away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only real problem I’ve got is that you are on a series of mountains that lead you one of two ways, towards Overlord Mountain, or back. There really isn’t anywhere to go with huge glacial valleys on either side. So next day I tried Overlord - an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Overlord_Mountain&quot;&gt;amazing peak with glaciers on either side at 2,625m&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;12081165844&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got up to over 2,115m on the way up Rector Peak and that’s when I found that the trail was getting more exposed than I liked. It probably would have been fine, but based on what &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alltrails.com/ar/trail/canada/british-columbia/overlord-mountain--2&quot;&gt;I read about online&lt;/a&gt; and spoke about with people who did it - I decided to turn around. The views were stunning at this point anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There wasn’t much else to do there, so I headed back down Singing Pass into Whistler. I partly wanted to see what Singing Pass was like and now I know. Consistent gradient, down in the shade of trees, and a pretty boring long hike down into Whistler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would do Russet Lake again, maybe try Overlord Mountain if I’m with someone or feeling in a better head space.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

</feed>
