<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Andy McKay</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/blog/andy" rel="alternate"></link>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/blog/rss/latest/andy/" rel="self"></link>
<updated>2023-01-31T15:48:41+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/blog/andy</id>
<author>
<name>Andy McKay</name>
<email>andy@clearwind.ca</email>
</author>

<entry>
<title>No we don't need a third bridge</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2023-01-30-third-bridge/"/>
<updated>2023-01-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/third-bridge</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It seems odd that we’d have to say this, but we don’t need a third bridge to Vancouver in North Vancouver. Yet apparently &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nsnews.com/opinion/almost-two-thirds-of-north-shore-readers-say-a-new-bridge-is-needed-6423723&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; suggests that two thirds of readers say they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;its-the-easy-choice&quot;&gt;It’s the easy choice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s people in cars everywhere, we build roads, bridges and car parks and so on. When you see traffic congestion it’s simple to just want to build more infrastructure. Build more roads and bridges and the traffic will get better right? Nope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember this is the community that has seen $250 million invested in the interchange at Mountain Highway and traffic has just gotten worse and worse since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The easy choice is the wrong one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-would-it-actually-go&quot;&gt;Where would it actually go?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/options.png&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vancouversun.com/news/local-news/a-look-at-six-possible-routes-for-rapid-transit-across-burrard-inlet&quot;&gt;This article discusses some routes&lt;/a&gt; and breaks them down into bridges and tunnels. The tunnels are all around Stanley Park, because no-one wants to knock the tress down in the park. Well some people do, but let’s assumes that’s politically unpalatble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bridges are all around Second Narrows, because it’s a shorter and easier bridge to build with some houses and industrial land on either side. Industrial land is much easier to rezone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s have a tunnel! There have been so many tunnels proposed, but it’s really expensive and hard. Burrard Inlet gets to 66m deep. If you build a tunnel, you have to build the infrastructure to get to it, which brings to my next point…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-would-it-need-on-either-side&quot;&gt;What would it need on either side?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expand around the Second Narrows? On the north side you hit the highway going north and the “cut” which is constrained to a couple of lanes each way. There isn’t really room to grow there. Highway 1 is 2 to 3 lanes across the North Shore, so widening that would require a vast re-allocation of land. On the south side you hit Cassiar tunnel which is going to be really hard and expensive to expand and then it goes on through the rest of Vancouver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expand around Lions Gate? And expand a highway through one of the most amazing parks in the world? What happens when it hits the north end. It currently goes left, towards Park Royal or right towards Marine Drive. Neither of which can take more load.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhere in the middle, near the Seabus? So how would the traffic get there? Would we have to turn Lonsdale into a highway to connect up Highway 1? Where on earth would a highway landing in East Vancouver go?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you increase the bridge capacity, you have to increase the capacity around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;its-cheaper-than-transit&quot;&gt;It’s cheaper than transit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost of the Skytrain is roughly $500 million per km for the Broadway Skytrain construction. [1] I’m no expert but that seems really expensive, but I’m not an expert on why it costs that much.  A suggested line across the North Shore and then to downtown at 20km could be roughly in the $10 billion price range. But it’s probably more expensive due to the bridge. [2]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost of the Massey Tunnel replacement is $4.15 billion, the suggested bridge replacement was $2.7 billion. [3]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not really worth trying to compare a 20km rapid transit line to a bridge that is 629m long, but let’s be clear: road infrastructure is expensive to build, expensive to maintain [4] and involves zero user fees. Don’t be fooled that it’s cheap to build or maintain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-next&quot;&gt;What next&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way out of this problem, for many reasons I haven’t covered, including climate change, accessibility, climate change, health, increasing density and so on is to increase our investments in alternative forms of transport. From active transport like cycling to public transit like buses and trains. No city has solved this by building more bridges. And it will look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/portland.png&quot; width=&quot;300px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you really want to live in a place like that (sorry Portland)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The saddest part of the article “less than 18 per cent – indicated they’d need more information to have an informed opinion on the topic.”. It’s not just that people have this opinion, it’s that they don’t want to learn more about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] https://www.theglobeandmail.com/canada/article-why-canada-gets-less-for-more-when-it-comes-to-building-transit-2/
[2] https://dailyhive.com/vancouver/north-shore-city-councils-rapid-transit-translink-approval-plan
[3] https://vancouversun.com/news/local-news/b-c-to-make-announcement-on-george-massey-tunnel-replacement
[4] https://www.lakecountry.bc.ca/en/news/you-asked-why-does-road-maintenance-cost-so-much.aspx (I can’t find a number yet for how much BC spends on this.)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>North Vancouver District - 2022 Elections</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2022-10-13-nvandistrict/"/>
<updated>2022-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/nvandistrict</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here’s how I will be voting on the weekend: &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mrmathewbond/&quot;&gt;Matthew Bond&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jordanback&quot;&gt;Jordan Back&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jimhanson_nv&quot;&gt;Jim Hanson&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/globalpope&quot;&gt;Catherine Pope&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ellisonmallin&quot;&gt;Ellison Mallin&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://mobile.twitter.com/harrison4nv&quot;&gt;Harrison Johnston&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because we need change in North Vancouver District and the existing council have repeatedly failed to produce this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In North Vancouver, there are two big intertwined issues, transportation and housing. The majority of residents living in North Vancouver work somewhere else, the majority of people working in the North Vancouver live somewhere else. That’s because house prices here are so high and everyone has to come into the district.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These candidates seem to understand the problems that exist in the district and want to bring change and improvements. We can’t keep having single family homes across the district that no-one can afford to buy. We can’t keep increasing investment in cars and car infrastructure because it doesn’t solve anything, induced demand just keeps bringing more cars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best time to invest in active forms of transport was years. The second best time to do it is now. Specifically candidates who said things like “I cycled to this meeting along the Seymour Parkway, and let me tell you its not pleasant” will get my vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Who I listened to and won’t vote for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mike Little, Lisa Muri and Betty Forbes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Betty Forbes is the person who got on council to ban pigeons, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/british-columbia/north-van-pigeons-betty-forbes-1.5964869&quot;&gt;because her neighbour has one&lt;/a&gt;. She thinks that cycling &lt;a href=&quot;https://bikehub.ca/municipal-elections/northvandistrict&quot;&gt;is well funded&lt;/a&gt; and suggested that building more parking lots and having bus shuttles will reduce traffic. Yep, more parking to have less cars. So pretty clueless on that one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s Mike Little’s opinion on cyclists:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/NVanDistrict?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@NVanDistrict&lt;/a&gt; incumbent Mayor Mike Little: if cyclists really cared about safety, they’d look like motorcyclists, with their protective clothing. But our cyclists won’t even go one block out of their way! They want to be on the main drag. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Just doesn’t get it. Vote accordingly. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/B3zUZREgR5&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/B3zUZREgR5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Martyn Schmoll (@martynschmoll) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/martynschmoll/status/1580589310973480960?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;October 13, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His opinion on traffic is that he’s working on a business plan for skytrain (sometime in the next ten years) and a replacement for the Ironworkers Memorial Bridge. So in twenty years Mike might bring some change to the District. Maybe, but in the meantime it’s all cyclists fault. I’ll go tell my daughter to go buy motorcycle gear and stay out of the way of cars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lisa Muri is confusing, because she’s extremely good at talking and confusing the issue. But when I’ve listened to her I found undertones of being obstructionist, unhelpful and blaming others. Lisa has been a councillor for 25+ years and plays politics well - if you don’t want anything to change in North Vancouver she’s your candidate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter Teevan? Well a life long worker in finance at automative dealerships wants to build a 6 lane each way multi level replacement to the Ironworkers Memorial bridge. One more lane will fix it, bro.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Valley Fondo, Cowichan Crusher and Penticton Fondo</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2022-07-14-some-bike-races/"/>
<updated>2022-07-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/some-bike-races</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some of the bike races I did this year, so far&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;valley-fondo&quot;&gt;Valley Fondo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I registered for the this Fondo in 2020 so my registration was a roll-over from that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normally this starts in the middle of Fort Langley, but this time it started in a muddy field nearby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;7255284868&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this race tough for a few reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I forgot to take pills that control my heart rate and so had to stop a couple of times&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My back started to hurt really early in the race and didn’t get better&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I got some good drafts, but struggled on hills and lost groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I find the race goes around nice parts of the valley. But I struggled to get a real sense of where I was, where I was going and so on. It just felt like I was cycling around in circles (I was). I was extremely glad that this race finished quite short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d probably not do this race again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cowichan-crusher&quot;&gt;Cowichan Crusher&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I registered for this at the last minute and made it into a camping trip and did 120km the day before to get there. Most of the information is over in &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2022-06-07-south-vancouver-island/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;. It’s nice to do a gravel race for a change and I wasn’t aiming for anything good here, just to have fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;okanagan-fondo&quot;&gt;Okanagan Fondo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another hold over from 2020, this is my second time doing this Fondo. It happens to fall the day after my birthday and I really enjoy the Okanagan. After my experience in the Valley Fondo and my complete lack of cycling with Steed this year, I expected to go into this one and struggle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;7448317184&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out I didn’t struggle this time. My back didn’t hurt until about 140km or so, usual for a long bike ride. My heart stayed under control and the weather was good. All the way south I was able to get into good groups and share pulling with some good drafts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was saving some energy for the hill at 110km, because that totally destroyed me last time and after that I was spent. Not so this time, it was tough, but nowhere as near as bad as I remembered. It did cause my average speed to drop below 32km/h, but as I approached and passed the observatory, I was able to start increasing my average speed above 30km a bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I started realising I could land this in under 5 hours, at an average pace over 30km/h… and I did hitting PRs on most of the route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one felt good and I’d love to come back and do it again.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Sixth Trip - Mt. Frosty</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2022-07-14-mt-frosty/"/>
<updated>2022-07-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/mt-frosty</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On Sunday I competed in my second Okanagan Gran Fondo. It was really good and I improved greatly on my time from last year, chopping off almost 30 minutes and completing my first Fondo at over 30km an hour. On Sunday my wife dropped me off in Manning Park on the way home so I could climb Mt. Frosty, the tallest peak in Manning Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-1-windy-joe&quot;&gt;Day 1: Windy Joe&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;11.92km, 685m elevation, 5hr 19min&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hiked up to Windy Joe and then out to the Pacific Crest Trail campsite:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;7463885716&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Windy Joe is a cool old fire lookout station on top of a hill. It was a nice hike, but there are many, many logs across the paths and navigating them with a backpack is a challenge. It was also hot hitting 35c around midday according to our thermometer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So normally it wouldn’t be challenging but with the heat and logs, we were happy to camp in what turned out to be a beautiful spot with a fabulous view up the valley towards Mt Frosty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_3585.JPG&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;The hut on top of Windy Joe&lt;cite&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_3591.JPG&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;We are heading up that mountain tomorrow&lt;cite&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-2-mt-frosty&quot;&gt;Day 2: Mt Frosty&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;11.88km, 1,011m elevation, 8hr 7min&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the big one, up and over &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frosty_Mountain&quot;&gt;Mt Frosty&lt;/a&gt;, at 2,426m the tallest mountain in &lt;a href=&quot;https://bcparks.ca/explore/parkpgs/ecmanning/&quot;&gt;Manning Park&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;7463886069&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trail just goes up continually without almost any breaks, up into the alpine and snow. We had stunning hot weather and amazing views every single way as plants bloomed in the alpine. Parts of the trail were obscured by snow, so we put spikes on, got the poles out and hiked up the side of the mountain as it got windier and windier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The view from the top is just amazing and every time I hike mountains like this, I find no matter what pictures I take, they are completely inadequate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the top there’s a path across the ridge to the top, or down to the campsite. So we dropped bags and headed up to the top for the view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_3639.JPG&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;Top is up there&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_3649.png&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;Top of Mt. Frosty&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming down was a lot of snow on the other side as we made our way down the to the campsite for the night. We all got sunburnt and wowed at the views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-3-frosty-creek-camp&quot;&gt;Day 3: Frosty Creek Camp&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;9.69km, 2hr 33min&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The camp at Frosty Creek is ok, but you can tell this side of the mountain is more popular and gets more visitors as it wasn’t in as good shape. Anyway this is a short and lovely hike down into the valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;7463885584&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always ❤️ coming down into the valley after a hike up a mountain, the thick air with lush vegetation full of animals. It’s just such a contrast to being on the top of a windswept mountain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_3664.JPG&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;Lightening Lakes&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fantastic hike that just caused me a bit of anxiety because I’m not great with heights and being on top of windblown ridge with deadly drops on either side isn’t my happy place. Some people do this in one day, in fact one of our party did when she ran the &lt;a href=&quot;https://raceroster.com/events/2022/57012/frosty-mountain-50k-27k-and-13k&quot;&gt;Frosty Mountain race&lt;/a&gt;. I think anyone who does that is bad ass. I was happy to do it at a leisurely pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve found that now I’ve got a clearly defined set of gear it was super easy to pack, go through my checklist and get going on a hike, so that’s great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fantastic way to end my sabbatical.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Fifth trip - West Coast Trail</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2022-06-25-west-coast-trail/"/>
<updated>2022-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/west-coast-trail</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pc.gc.ca/en/pn-np/bc/pacificrim/activ/SCO-WCT&quot;&gt;West Coast Trail&lt;/a&gt; is one of the most popular hiking trips in the world and has for many years been a rite of passage for many people in BC. In June I noticed that a spot was available - they normally all get booked for the year as soon as the reservations open in January - and took it. Heading from the south to the north on June 20th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of spending the weeks cycling or running I focused on hiking with a back pack, doing my usual local trails with varying weights of backpacks and also doing the &lt;a href=&quot;/2022-06-25-stein-valley/&quot;&gt;Stein Valley&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d read lots of posts about the trail and the toll the 75km takes on people. Over 100 people are year are evacuated usually due to hypothermia or injuries from slipping. The weeks leading up to the trip were mostly full of anxiety… would I be fit enough, would I have the right gear and so on. I went full on as &lt;a href=&quot;/2022-06-25-packing-light/&quot;&gt;light as possible&lt;/a&gt;, was this a bad move? We’d find out. Oh and I was doing it solo, the most dangerous way to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;👉 &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcweb.azureedge.net/-/media/pn-np/bc/pacificrim/WET4/visit/PDF/2019-WCT-Map_EN.pdf&quot;&gt;Map of the trail as a PDF&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sorry, this is a long one.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-there&quot;&gt;Getting there&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me leaving a car at Port Renfrew or Bamfield wasn’t option. Port Renfrew has paved access, Bamfield is accessible only by logging road. The two main options are the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ladyrosemarine.com/schedule-rates&quot;&gt;Bamfield ferry to Port Alberni&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&quot;https://trailbus.com/&quot;&gt;Trail Bus&lt;/a&gt;. I took the bus from Victoria to the start and they picked me up at Bamfield and took me back to Nanaimo. The bus was cool, but its a bus on logging roads, you’ll get a comfier ride on the ferry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;direction&quot;&gt;Direction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a note that I had no choice in direction. The two main ways are north to south or south to north. Options from Nitinaht are available, which is basically in the middle. The hardest parts of the trail are by far the sections from Walbran Creek south. Specifically the section to the west of Camper Bay and east of Camper Bay to Gordon River.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are doing south 👉 north, you do the hardest parts first. If you are doing north 👉 south, you will do the hardest parts last. Some say, its better to save the hardest part to last since you will have eaten food and have a lighter pack. I was happy I did south to north and got the tough stuff done while fresh, it just got easier every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-one-gordon-river-to-camper-bay&quot;&gt;Day one: Gordon River to Camper Bay&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;13.35km in 5h 33min&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bus deposited us at the entrance to the park. A bunch of nervous hikers all checking out each others backpacks and asking how long they’ll take and so on. A really nice person gave us an orientation and talked us through the video. For the route you’ll need to keep a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcweb.azureedge.net/-/media/pn-np/bc/pacificrim/WET4/visit/PDF/2019-WCT-Map_EN.pdf&quot;&gt;map on hand&lt;/a&gt; and have a list of the tide times. A lot of trail is on the beach and you’ll need to know what the tide is (they give you this, don’t lose it). This means you will also need a device that tells you the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the chatter was about how small my backpack and was how light it was. At this point I wasn’t quite sure if I was just completely stupid for going so small and light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The park ranger told us that the first campsite Thrasher takes most people 4 hours to get to - it’s only 5km away. The next campsite Camper Bay takes another 4 hours to get to. They then got into details about going from Thrasher to Camper Bay by see - it involves a boulder field that takes about 3 hours and then dangerous cliffs and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of this seemed to be an exercise in caution, understanding the map and tides. I imagine that the rangers have to deal with people of all abilities on this trail and they have to deal with pulling people out when it goes wrong, a tough job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get to the start you have to take a ferry and at about 10:30am I was off, on the West Coast Trail, solo  - the most dangerous way to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other side of the river you are faced with a vertical ladder to scale. The first of many and telling of what is to come:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/P1020717.JPG&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;This is the start. Get used to it.&lt;cite&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took me 2 and a bit hours to get to the junction to Thrashers. I was hiking at my usual comfortable speed I was doing in North Vancouver and overtaking people who started on the 8am ferry. It felt comfortable for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;7362981527&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I would end up at Thrashers at 1pm ish and have an entire day to wait for tides to go around the coast. And I’d have to wait in the morning for the tides again. That would get me to Campers on day 2. I’m not good at waiting around and the boulder field and only part of the map marked “Very dangerous” didn’t appeal. Plus, I really wanted to ensure I finished on schedule… the day after the West Coast Trail is my daughters graduation, I promised not to miss it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pushed on to Camper Bay and got there in two and a bit hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/P1020722.JPG&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;So many broken bridges and boardwalks. This coast is tough on infrastructure.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trail Gordon River to Thrashers felt like a hike on the more remote North Vancouver trails (eg: Three chop, upper lynn loop etc). Just throw in a bunch of ladders. Thrashers to Camper Bay was a muddy hell hole of broken boardwalks, mud, deep mud, slippy everything and mud. Parts of this were not that much fun. People I chatted to later said the boulder field on the coast wasn’t fun either so 🤷‍♂.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway I took the cable car across and camped at Camper Bay for the night. Met a nice group from Alberta who let me share their camp fire. Mostly we spoke about how I managed to do it so fast, when some of their group took over 6 hours to get to Thrashers 🤷‍♂. The advantage of doing this kind of trail regularly and having a super light backpack I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-two-camper-bay-to-bonilla-point&quot;&gt;Day two: Camper Bay to Bonilla Point&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;16.8km in 7h 24min&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the sun rose, I staggered out of bed, made my tea and oats and packed up. First one out on the trail up north. For this day there were multiple places I could camp, it was more about where I wanted to finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;7362981573&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The section out of Camper Bay continued the trend of being broken boardwalks, mud, bog, ladders, rivers, bridges, ladders, more ladders, mud and so on. Did I mention mud? There’s a lot of that. When you get to Walbran Creek, it mud comes to and end you was able to exit from the forest onto the beach for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/P1020736.JPG&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;So many ladders and its hard to get a feel of how steep they are from these pictures.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still felt good at this point, strong and powering through things. I will admit, I did find some of the ladders a bit scary at times. Heights aren’t my thing and having a backpack and poles etc makes it harder. Doing some of those in pouring rain, with heavy backpacks must be hard. Camper Bay to Walbran is rough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/P1020754.JPG&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;Coming out of the forest onto the beach felt pretty good.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had lunch at Walbran Creek and tried to cross - silly idea. I got my feet and gaiters totally drenched and was only half way across when it got really deep. So I back tracked and went across the creek using the cable car higher up. But that gave me the excuse to have a cup of tea, change socks and dry things out a little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that it was gorgeous beach walking for a while. I stopped at Bonilla Point to camp because its cute, has a waterfall and was deserted. And it stayed that way, being the only person there all night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bear in mind, not all beach walking is easy. The sand is at an angle and often very soft so you slip a lot. You’ll also be climbing over rocks, seaweed, rock shelves and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That night the weather closed it and we got wet west coast mist for many hours, so I hid in the tent most of the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-three-bonilla-point-to-tsusiat-falls&quot;&gt;Day three: Bonilla Point to Tsusiat Falls&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;25.24km in 9h 52min&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tsusiat Falls is one of the most popular camping sites on the West Coast Trail. It marks a destination for hikers from the north. For them its the last site before a long trek to Cribbs through an area that’s low in water and has no formal campsites. Similarly from the south, once you go past Cribbs there isn’t anything much till Tsusiat. You can camp &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; anywhere, but there is a 5km or so stretch between the two with no camping due to animal activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I headed out with some damp gear, but nothing too bad from last night heading. Cribbs was really close to Bonilla and I went through there at 9:30am, so I wasn’t going to stop there. This was pretty much all on the beach and easy hiking as the sun started to work it’s way through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;7362981605&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trail alternated with little bits inland and the beach before inland towards Nitinaht. I was feeling pretty good here still and powering along quite happily. Views were getting better and the trails were improving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/P1020782.JPG&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;I wish every hike was this beautiful.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the Nitinaht ferry there’s the Crabshack which serves crabs and other delicacies like bags of chips and pop. I went for a grill cheese which took 40 minutes, but was worth it. A quick ferry ride across the river led me on to the trail so I could keep powering towards Tsusiat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point the trail is high up on a cliff, close to the edge with fantastic views. And here I met my first bear. It saw me first and darted at 90% to me across the trail. I quickly saw 2 cubs shoot up a tree. I backed of and fumbled for my bear spray shouting “Bear” at the top of my voice to warn others and something to make noise to keep the bear aware of where I was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 4 minutes of not seeing any bear and shouting until I felt like an idiot, I inched forward, bear spray at the ready. It was long gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/P1020816.JPG&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;One of the many random beaches without people on that you see from the trail. Just amazing.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of hike to Tsusiat was uneventful, but getting even more pretty including a cool sea arch that I only just made the tides for. That night I was surrounded by tons of people but the waterfall and sea meant I didn’t hear much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/P1020837.JPG&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;Tents and waterfall at Tsusiat.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-four-tsusiat-falls-to-michigan-creek&quot;&gt;Day four: Tsusiat Falls to Michigan Creek&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;12.64km in 5h 14min&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, the number of campsites is limited, Michigan Creek is the last formal campsite. Darling River campsite is closed due to bear activity, so Michigan seemed like the best bet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;7362981453&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a combination of beach and trail up on the cliffs. Probably one of the most scenic sections with views down to the rocks and bluffs and beaches. Some serious ladders and a bit of mud, but overall the trail is really good at this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tsocowis Creek is a lovely spot with a nice campsite that had no one there. I stopped, put up the hammock and had a good nap. The hike to Michigan Creek is along the beach with a couple of streams to ford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hiking was pretty easy and I still felt good, able to power along and got to Michigan Creek in the early afternoon. I spent a while failing to set up my hammock, none of the trees were quite right. Finally settled on a spot in the trees with my tent and chilled… only to find I’d lost my camera &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Aargh. I knew the last time I used it was Tsocowis Creek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/P1020869.JPG&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;Bridge over waterfall at Tsocowis Creek.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After ages searching the campground, asking people and retracing my steps I was at a loss. So I grabbed my Spot, my bear spray and hiked the 9km return to Tsocowis Creek to see if it was there. It wasn’t. So really I did 21km+ this day, but 9km of it was in the sun without a backpack - nice and easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later that night someone found the camera next to their tent. Yay 😃&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_3472.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;Evening at Michigan Creek&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-five-michigan-creek-to-pachena-access&quot;&gt;Day five: Michigan Creek to Pachena Access&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;12.62km in 3h 24min&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can probably tell the times are getting shorter and shorter for similar distances. The differences in the trail, the quality of the infrastructure and the quality of the trail is like night and day. If the first day is a hike on the hardest North shore trail, this is a walk on Stanley Park. It’s mostly in great condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;7362971051&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was another bear sighting, which ran off quickly once it spotted me. Sea lion rock is awesome and is a few rocks full of sea lions. Was as advertised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/P1020881.JPG&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;Sea lion rock is loud and fun to watch.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a few hours I turned up at the beautiful beach at Pachena and I was done at 12:30pm, one day early.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/P1020891.JPG&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;The end at Pachena beach.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trail bus crew were able to move my reservation up a day and by 5:30pm I was in Nanaimo waiting for a ferry home and kinda wishing I was able to turn back and do the whole trail once again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The trail is beautiful&lt;/strong&gt; in that special west coast way, similar to Haida Gwaii and so on. Long empty beaches, bears, eagles, ravens, sea otters and just continuous beauty. I hope I never get tired this amazing coast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The trail is muddy&lt;/strong&gt; beyond anyway I thought possible. It’s really bad and that makes it really slippy. It’s what makes the trail harder and I can’t imagine how bad it is in the rain. You need gaiters and poles for the mud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Difficulty is subjective&lt;/strong&gt;. I didn’t find it that hard, because I’ve spent years hiking on the North Shore and it is similar to the harder trails. If you don’t do this kind of hiking regularly, if you’ve got a big backpack you will find it &lt;strong&gt;very tough&lt;/strong&gt;. I think back to the experience some people had said they had hiking (almost none) and their backpack weight (very heavy) on the bus to the trail and cringe, I hope they made it in the time they had allotted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Light is better&lt;/strong&gt; when it comes to backpacking. The majority of accidents are people slipping and if you are fatigued from carrying a 60lb backpack and trying to negotiate this trail, you are more likely to have a serious slip. I didn’t feel I missed anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s more sanitised than I expected&lt;/strong&gt;. I did go 4 hours at a time without seeing people and I did camp by myself. But those were the exceptions, it’s become quite popular and all the rivers have bridges or cable cars. There is support and exit points if you have an accident and that’s all good. But I’m craving something more remote, maybe the North Coast trail, Haida Gwaii etc. The possibilities are endless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved this hike and my time on the trail so much and I missed it as soon as I was done. I would do it again. Those last three days in the sun were amazing and I ❤️ this part of the world, so very much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_3486.jpeg&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;Felt good to be done and now I can get to a hot shower and my daughters graduation. And maybe a beer.&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;👋 I’ll be back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I used an old camera for pictures. This meant I could leave my phone off and only use it for emergencies and not have to carry a battery pack. This was much lighter and worked well. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Fourth Trip - Stein Valley</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2022-06-25-stein-valley/"/>
<updated>2022-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/stein-valley</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of my favourite places in BC is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bcparks.ca/explore/parkpgs/stein_val/&quot;&gt;Stein Valley Nlaka’pamux Heritage Park&lt;/a&gt;, located by Lytton, BC. It’s special for a couple of reasons. It’s one of the only large unlogged watersheds &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stein_River&quot;&gt;left in BC&lt;/a&gt;. It’s much warmer than everywhere else, making it ideal for trips when you want to avoid rain, or weather elsewhere is crappy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The park is big, with one main trail that comes in from the west side of the Fraser River and goes up to the Stein Lake, 50km+ away. This means there is really only one main trail and route in the park with not many options until you get up to the lake. Once you get up the lake passes and trails exist through over to the west to Blowdown Creek etc. This is serious alpine wilderness hiking, which unfortunately I haven’t been able to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our plan was to head up for three days and enjoy the weather. It was also a trial for the West Coast Trail trip as I haven’t back packed in a while… instead using a bike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-one-heading-up-the-stein&quot;&gt;Day one: heading up the Stein&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entry to the Stein means going through Lytton and seeing first hand the devastation of the heat dome last year. The scarred and twisted remains of the centre of the town are just heartbreaking. It’s no exaggeration to say that the town is just gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get to the Stein you can take the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.gov.bc.ca/gov/content/transportation/passenger-travel/water-travel/inland-ferries/lytton-reaction-ferry&quot;&gt;reaction ferry&lt;/a&gt; across the river. Except because of flooding and high snow melt, the ferry was closed. The ramp to get onto the ferry was flooded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;7293015309&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two choices left; the rail bridge to the south of Lytton and then an 8km hike up to the park trailhead or the suspension bridge and a ~2km hike. We went for the latter. It looks like this and with a 30km+ wind howling up the Fraser it made an interesting crossing while carrying a large backpack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_3377.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the hike was pretty straightforward, beautiful forests by a raging river. Pictographs carved on rock and lots of camping sites in 28c sunny weather, sounds pretty good to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We camped at Devils Staircase campground, which isn’t a staircase and isn’t really hard or devilish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-two-leaving-the-stein&quot;&gt;Day two: leaving the Stein&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan for day two was to head further into the Stein, without our backpacks. We set off heading north and hit a snag. About 1km north of the campground the trail is badly washed out with a gully of death leading right down to the river.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was seriously steep, seriously sketchy and with a very large penalty if you slipped. I just wasn’t comfortable crossing, I tried and nearly lost it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So at that point, we headed back, packed up and reluctantly headed out of the Stein Valley and found a gin and tonic instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;7293015342&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns out in almost 30c heat, hiking up hills with 40lb+ backpacks and crossing the suspension bridge of doom was enough to wipe us out. Getting back to the car, we definitely felt like we’d done a good hike and we enjoyed our gin and tonic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have the ambition to get to the Stein Lake and do the Stein Valley traverse, ideally by crossing over from Blowdown Creek or Lizzie Pass. But not this weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Packing Light</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2022-06-25-packing-light/"/>
<updated>2022-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/packing-light</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For my upcoming West Coast trail I was determined to pack light. The difference between a 11.3kg (25lb) and 22.6kg (50lb) backpack on your ability to hike is huge. I really felt that difference on the Stein Valley where I had a 19.9kg backpack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The West Coast trail is 75km, takes the average person 6-8 days and involves lots of rough terrain. The main causes of emergency evacuation from the West Coast Trail or evacuation and injuries due to slips and falls. The majority of the latter come from people with overloaded packs and tired people. A lighter pack reduces fatigue and reduces the chance of injury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Stein Valley my 65L pack weighed 19.9kg (44lbs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the West Coast Trail my 40L pack weighed 11.8kg (26lbs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what was in it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_3459.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what it looked like packed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_3460.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;That’s food and gear for 6 nights&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note:&lt;/em&gt; as I hiked I moved more stuff inside and moved the tent onto the bottom of the pack to reduce snags and catching things on the side. It also made my backpack cover fit better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;big-wins&quot;&gt;Big Wins&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/tags/gear/&quot;&gt;gear page for details&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 40L backpack&lt;/strong&gt; is lighter than my 65L one. That’s partly because its smaller, but also because its a lot newer. The 65L one is over 20 years old still good but things have advanced a long way since then. The 40L backpack is 2.1kg lighter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My tent&lt;/strong&gt; is a bit of a pain to put up and sleep in, suffering from wind, condensation and camping on sand (all of which happen on the West Coast Trail). However &lt;a href=&quot;/2022-04-04-a-tent/&quot;&gt;it weighs 517g&lt;/a&gt;, including pegs. You don’t need to carry poles because you just hiking poles. Win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My sleeping bag&lt;/strong&gt; is 530g and &lt;a href=&quot;/2022-04-05-sleeping-bag/&quot;&gt;packs down super small&lt;/a&gt;. Add in a base layer or thermal set for sleeping which weighed 315g.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clothes&lt;/strong&gt; I ended up with the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;shorts and t-shirt for hot weather&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pants and top for the normal west coast weather&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pants and top for cold or very wet weather&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gloves and toque&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 pairs of socks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a thin but warm top (329g)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a waterproof jacket (410g)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means I was re-wearing clothes, but able to layer together up to 4 or 5 layers together if I really needed it. No need to carry a puffy down jacket, just use smart layers to build for the weather.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Food&lt;/strong&gt; is all dehydrated:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;oats for breakfast&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cliff bars and dried mango for snacks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dehydrated food for dinner in bags&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;herbal tea bags&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cooking&lt;/strong&gt; is done using a &lt;a href=&quot;/2022-06-25-a-stove/&quot;&gt;Jetboil Flash&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My one luxury was a hammock (at 200g) for when I just wanted to relax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a bunch of other miscellaneous bits of pieces, dry bags, satellite tracker, toilet roll and so on. But those things above are the biggest sources of space and weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key here for me was to be ruthless, I know all the weights of these because I measured everything and put it on a spreadsheet. The difference between the yellow gore-tex Sugoi jacket and a blue MEC gore-tex jacket was 200g, something I hadn’t really thought about until I weighed them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep weighing things and be ruthless about what you do and don’t need. You have to be ready for any weather and any situation, you have to ensure you don’t get cold and face hypothermia - but you don’t have to take everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hiked the West Coast Trail with people carrying 65lb backpacks and goggled at the stuff they brought. I think they probably felt the same too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some examples that made me wonder:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A tent that required 18 pegs to be set up. 18!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A person carrying cucumber as food. Cucumber is 96% water.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A person carrying cans of tuna. Those cans contain water or oil and then you have to pack out the cans.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A person who brought in 3 saws to the West Coast Trail so they could cut up firewood.
…and so on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But respect to the people who don’t bother with tents at all, they are hardcore.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>A stove</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2022-06-25-a-stove/"/>
<updated>2022-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/a-stove</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the past for camping I’ve used a primus stove like this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.primusequipment.com/4a5848/globalassets/catalogs/primus/p3/p351/p35111/p351110/nocolor/351110_essential_trail_stove.jpg?width=680&amp;amp;height=680&amp;amp;mode=BoxPad&amp;amp;bgcolor=fff&amp;amp;quality=80&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It need a pot, a pot handle and a fuel canister. It was better for cooking than some of the other stoves we had, but it has some problems. The flames aren’t very focused, tending to go up the side and it needs a lot of fuel. Fuel is heavy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For my West Coast Trail trip I was determined to be lightweight, that means the only food I took was dehydrated. Fresh water is in abundance on the West Coast Trail and I realised all I was ever doing was boiling water, I don’t need pots or pans. I won’t be cooking for frying anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jetboil.com/&quot;&gt;Jetboil&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://johnsonoutdoors.widen.net/content/ejkh4iomht/png/1114606_primary.png?w=1040&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If all you do is boil water, this is what you want.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used the Jetboil on the West Coast Trail and loved it for the following reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It boils really fast.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The colour coding on the side tells you when its boiled.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When its boiled, you don’t need to fiddle with pans or pan handles, the cover allows you to pick it up and pour. It’s just really easy to use.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s really light.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s efficient which means you can carry less fuel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just for the fuel alone, using the Jetboil meant I could carry one 200g tank of fuel for 5 days of hiking. I would normally carry one &lt;strong&gt;large&lt;/strong&gt; fuel tank, at least 500g+ (haven’t got a full one to weigh). Because the old stove is that inefficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was able to carry less and lighter, saving myself carrying multiple items and at least 500g. Over half the people on the trail, if not more, had a Jetboil or similar system.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>A Watch</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2022-06-08-a-watch/"/>
<updated>2022-06-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/a-watch</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On my racing bike I have a Wahoo Element Bolt and sensors for speed, cadence and power. On my gravel bike I have none of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I started doing longer bike trips I realised I didn’t really want all that information. I don’t care about speed, just the time and how long it is to my destination. I want to enjoy the ride. I don’t want to maintain an average speed, or care about my power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These trips are for enjoying the ride. So I started using my watch that I use for running and hiking instead to record the trips. The advantages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The battery lasts for ever&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I have to manually look at my wrist to see information&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I have only the information I care about and nothing else&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A few less gadgets to worry about&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://coros.com/pace2&quot;&gt;Coros Pace 2&lt;/a&gt; for a while now and love it. It offers “20 Days For Regular Use/30 Hours In Full GPS Mode”. I’m not sure about that, but I haven’t had to charge it on any trip so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Controls are two buttons which are easy to operate in the cold, rain or when you are tired. It does what I want, records activity and tells me the information I need. Would highly recommend if you want something simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In comparison my Apple Watch died before I completed a marathon (admittedly a long one up a mountain). The Apple Watch was so complicated it did random stuff and was hard to read and operate. In the cold, rain or when sweaty it would be so hard to use.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>From the Troller to the Raven</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2022-06-07-the-raven/"/>
<updated>2022-06-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/the-raven</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In 1986 Spirit of the West released the album &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tripping_Up_the_Stairs&quot;&gt;Tripping up the Stairs&lt;/a&gt;. On that album was a song “The Crawl” on &lt;a href=&quot;https://music.apple.com/ca/album/the-crawl/1273513877?i=1273513884&quot;&gt;Apple Music&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Kc4eYv2Oyq8&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The album details a pub crawl along the North Shore “From the Troller to the Raven with all stops inbetween”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spirit of the West are no more and at the end of the June the Raven won’t be&lt;/strong&gt;. Multiple people have told me and confirmed by staff that the end of June 2022, the Raven, established 1979 will be closing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://scontent.fcxh3-1.fna.fbcdn.net/v/t39.30808-6/281104355_5315095888535669_5475206090518731323_n.jpg?stp=c0.9.526.274a_dst-jpg_p526x296&amp;amp;_nc_cat=109&amp;amp;ccb=1-7&amp;amp;_nc_sid=340051&amp;amp;_nc_ohc=o03CX2dRhMoAX9VDBF0&amp;amp;_nc_ht=scontent.fcxh3-1.fna&amp;amp;oh=00_AT9pm3MQekHwUyYidJ2WPwRYq3w-vccG1lLGpcxpKn12wA&amp;amp;oe=62A458F6&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The song &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?client=firefox-b-d&amp;amp;q=spirit+of+the+west+the+crawl&quot;&gt;tells the story&lt;/a&gt; of doing a pub crawl from the Troller in Horseshoe Bay all the over to Deep Cove. It mentions a few pubs on the way Park Royal Hotel (closed), The Rusty Gull (open), Square Rigger (open), Queen’s Cross (open). Unfortunately when they get to the Raven, they get the last beer to find they’d lost half their friends and had no money to get a taxi and were walking home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to the Raven for the first time with my then to be wife on my first visit to Canada - over 29 years ago. Since we now live two blocks away, we tend to go there a lot more than we used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of the demise of the Raven is simple greed. The story (as I know it) is that the buildings were taken over by a developer who wanted to turn into condos. The district denied their rezoning plans. The developer has since tripled rents and made the businesses their untenable and one-by-one they’ve all been leaving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, I’m surprised it’s hung on as long as it has. Over the last many years it’s been on its last legs. The beer has gone downhill with less craft beer and become very expensive. The mens toilets have been in various states of disrepair. The food has varied greatly, depending on the chefs - ‘ve gone through plenty. We’ve had food with no cutlery, pizza with metal bits in it, orders messed up. Sometimes poutine that was cold, had plastic in it, was more gravy than anything and so on. With COVID-19 they got a patio to supplement the tiny sunless one by the road - it’s in the parking lot with a fantastic view of cars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet I still like going to the Raven. It was for me and many an extension of our living rooms. A few weeks ago I was there and saw 5 different groups of friends as people came and went over the evening. No need to get tables or order food - people would just pop in and out. We’d turn up after skiing on Mt Seymour, or biking on the mountain, or kayaking on the ocean in whatever we were wearing and have a drink with friends and no-one would care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though it did end up being pretty crap, I will miss the Raven and I think Deep Cove will be worse because of it’s loss.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Third Trip - South Vancouver Island</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2022-06-07-south-vancouver-island/"/>
<updated>2022-06-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/south-vancouver-island</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks after my &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2022-05-17-second-trip/&quot;&gt;second trip&lt;/a&gt;, it was time to head out on my second trip. I’ve been finding long trips to other countries expensive and hard to organize and I absolutely love British Columbia, so I decided just to spend more time here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friend mentioned the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cowichancrusher.com/&quot;&gt;Cowichan Crusher&lt;/a&gt; fondo and my course was set. I had a few days spare before the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.valleygranfondo.com/&quot;&gt;Valley Fondo&lt;/a&gt;, so didn’t want to go too crazy so instead went to southern Vancouver Island.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this trip I planned on camping, so went with full gear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-1-deep-cover-to-lake-cowichan&quot;&gt;Day 1: Deep Cover to Lake Cowichan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s warm up for the Fondo by doing a 120km ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;7218875101&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out this route is pretty straightforward, avoiding the highway is still a struggle and there’s still choke points where you have to go on the highway north of Cedar, around Ladysmith and near the turn off to Lake Cowichan. At this point I did not know about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cvrd.ca/121/Cowichan-Valley-Trail&quot;&gt;Cowichan Valley Trail&lt;/a&gt; which goes from Duncan to Lake Cowichan (and more), if you go this way look it up to avoid roads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-2-cowichan-crusher&quot;&gt;Day 2: Cowichan Crusher&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out it’s not 100+km, but actually 91km. The route was published on the Friday night and listed over 1760m of elevation, but it was only 1084m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;7224179380&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was an out and back along the south side of Lake Cowichan. Started off with a bit of road, then wide logging roads and undulating hills. At 40km there was a loop and an insane hill that was really steep. I now have 38-42 gearing and was struggling up it. When I saw people walking at the same speed I was grinding, I eventually swallowed my pride and walked up the last bit. The slope down was even steeper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a small event that was fun. I didn’t focus on trying to do amazing, just have some fun and get some gravel in. Of course, it was a race and there were other people so soon my racing instinct took over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was able to ditch all my gear at the start so didn’t have to lug it around. After a pub lunch with a friend, I went to my campsite and promptly got lost on the way there. So ended up over 118km.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;7229659808&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I got to the campsite, it was lovely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_3243.JPG&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I had a bit of a problem. My original plan was to head to Port Renfrew, then Sooke, then back to Lake Cowichan and home by Wednesday with two rest days before the Valley Fondo. There were two problems: the forecast was a lot of rain and I had many sores from two long days (not going to go into details there, suffice to say I was in pain).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-3-lets-try-going-to-nanaimo&quot;&gt;Day 3: Let’s try going to Nanaimo&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on how I felt I reluctantly decided to head home. I felt this was the second time I’d failed at a full Vancouver Island trip, but I wanted my body to recover before the Fondo. But I thought I’d add a twist. Instead of repeating day 1 and doing the highway, I’d try a new route - this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/lake-cowichan-to-nanaimo.png&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This route was spectacular. Soaring mountains, rivers, a road that turned into a logging road and got narrowers. Waterfalls, bear poop, deer and no people. And it went up and up and got smaller and narrower. And steeper. Then it became unrideable. For a long time. Then I was fording streams, then trees were across the road. Then snow, deep snow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was before it went really wrong:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_3270.JPG&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn’t ridden my bike for about an hour when I had to make a decision. I was aiming for Nanaimo but had 62km to go and was in snow and getting pretty lost. I had all the gear to camp out, but realised I was unprepared and lacking information on where I was going. It’s well and good camping, but if you are going the wrong way, it could go very wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to turn back to Lake Cowichan. Oh but on the way, my tubeless tyre sprung a leak. It was right on the rim, so I think the rim seal (if that’s a thing failed). My repair kit didn’t work so I pulled the tyre off and stuffed in a tube. I only had one spare tube, so was in for a long walk if anything else failed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After and 7 hours and 102km 1,259m elevation I got back to a cheap hotel - I needed a hot shower and couldn’t face another 20km+ to the campsite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;7229660119&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sitting in the warm pub, absolutely wiped and very, very sore I realised I’d missed a turning. That turning would have lead me along a contour line, to the top of a valley and down most of the rest of the way. If I’d carried on going I would have just ended up at top of a mountain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lesson learned, research and get good maps for when you go off on logging roads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-4-lake-cowichan-to-deep-cove-the-boring-way&quot;&gt;Day 4: Lake Cowichan to Deep Cove, the boring way&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y’know, following roads and trails that are well established. I did give up at Park Royal and my wife met me, I was wiped. It was still a 115km day so I averaged 100km+ each day and some decent elevation. This is a higher average distance each day than my previous 2 trips and I felt it in many ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;7235049728&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Highlight was that I found the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cvrd.ca/121/Cowichan-Valley-Trail&quot;&gt;Cowichan Valley Trail&lt;/a&gt; which goes from Lake Cowichan straight into Duncan on a old train line. It’s fast easy and delightful 25km+ of trail that I’d recommend to anyone going that way. I was able to stop in Duncan and pick up some tubes from a local bike shop and then work my way up the coast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I should carry more than one spare tube.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Definitely research logging roads more and have a better map than just Google maps.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I enjoyed camping so much the second night, I wish I’d camped the third night too. I’m bored of hotels and the camping was delightful - at the time my brain was just focused on the first place to crash.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My five day trip got shortened by a single day by adding an absolutely epic exploration day by accident, so the trip was pretty good. I don’t feel bad I didn’t get to Nanaimo that way, it was a super exciting and interesting ride. I probably wouldnt do it again that way though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to note that after day 2 I did adjust my seat slightly and that seemed to help, but it did take a couple of days of not riding for things to heal.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Second Trip - Maui</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2022-05-17-second-trip/"/>
<updated>2022-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/second-trip</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks after my &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2022-04-24-first-trip/&quot;&gt;first trip&lt;/a&gt; it was time to head out on my second trip. The weather in Vancouver and British Columbia has been unseasonably cold and very frustrating. I wanted to go somewhere warm. There are lots of choices, but all of sudden they all got really expensive. On a whim I found a cheap flight to Maui and off I went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;changes-from-my-first-trip&quot;&gt;Changes from my first trip&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This trip had a few differences: I was flying, Maui is really warm, I was never staying anywhere too remote. For this reason I decided not to pack stove, cooking gear, or food. I could live without a good cup of tea for a week. This meant I could remove my frame bag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My wife also pointed out that we had an air mattress that compacted smaller and it fit nicely into my &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2022-05-17-panniers/&quot;&gt;new panniers&lt;/a&gt;, meaning I could take one dry bag less as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out camping is really hard to find in Maui. Covid has meant that availability is limited and some have just closed. Here’s the “official” campsites that are left (excluding walk in ones at the top of Haleakala):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/camping-maui.png&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/@20.6704429,-156.5285182,10.41z/data=!4m2!10m1!1e1&quot;&gt;Google map&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you search for campsites on Maui you might find more including state parks that are “good for camping”. You’ll probably also find lots of websites saying you can camp on any beach as long as you have a fishing rod.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these places are better than other. The road either side of Lahaina certainly had lots of cars and tents parked up camping on beaches and space for others. So you probably could camp there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I’m worried enough generally about safety in the US from private property to people with guns that I didn’t feel comfortable doing that based on what some random websites say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end I could only get a total of 3 nights camping out of my 7 there. I would have liked more, but it resulted in me getting in the rides I wanted so it’s not so bad. If like me, you want to camp in campsites with facilities and less worries - book early. The resulting trip and locations I stayed in is a result of booking late and trying to avoid the expensive areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-1-jet-lag-and-assemble-bike&quot;&gt;Day 1: Jet lag and assemble bike&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stayed in Kahului, assembled my bike after a 10:30pm arrival the night before. Most hotels will not store bike boxes or anything overnight, but I did persuade one nice person at the hotel to do it for me (cost a bit in tips).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe height=&quot;405&quot; width=&quot;590&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/7110978753/embed/5cd626998d8e95ebbfab65f71002802ad2c22b23&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was just a quick shake out ride and then a visit to Walmart to stock up on groceries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-2-kahului-to-olowalu&quot;&gt;Day 2: Kahului to Olowalu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first long ride, ending up with campsite and a beach in Olowalu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe height=&quot;405&quot; width=&quot;590&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/7121391240/embed/73b811f333e399e90f3795b6eccd0260a273df53&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_2052.JPG&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I absolutely loved this ride. It was gorgeous, very sunny and unbelieveably windy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a big hill coming out of Kahului - its always good to start with the hill and get it out of the way. The village of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Kahakuloa,+HI+96793,+USA/@21.0009245,-156.5628451,15z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m8!1m2!10m1!1e1!3m4!1s0x7eab2bdab3f68513:0x65c8e7836e04e78!8m2!3d21.0009085!4d-156.55406&quot;&gt;Kahakuloa&lt;/a&gt; marks the transition from the hill - it’s a good place for drinks and banana bread and has spectacular scenery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next section is all cliff side roads, with fantastic views. At the beginning the road gets very, very narrow but does soon even out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last big transition is around &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/place/D.T.+Fleming+Park/@21.0058175,-156.6468452,14.43z/data=!4m8!1m2!10m1!1e1!3m4!1s0x7eaad5c776457c77:0x9160a3ac662334d7!8m2!3d21.0048584!4d-156.6513703&quot;&gt;DT Fleming Park&lt;/a&gt; where it turns into a highway with a wide shoulder. This is a good place to stop for toilet and water top up before cruising down the highway for the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-3-olowalu-to-kihei&quot;&gt;Day 3: Olowalu to Kihei&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the morning I had to make a decision, to try &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/dir/Olowalu+Beach,+Hawaii+96761,+United+States/Haleakala+Crater,+Hawaii,+USA/@20.7946001,-156.5663247,11z/data=!4m14!4m13!1m5!1m1!1s0x7954d620a4d0104d:0x6a34602b0ffa082e!2m2!1d-156.6156274!2d20.8090713!1m5!1m1!1s0x7954c811eeb96541:0x864843523f88c0bc!2m2!1d-156.2535131!2d20.7096826!3e1&quot;&gt;Haleakala Crater&lt;/a&gt; or not. I felt that if I did that, I would absolutely wipe myself out for a couple of days. I was also feeling tired from my previous days ride. Jet lag, or first big exercise since my marathon? Not sure, but I decided to pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end I took a leisurely ride from Olowalu over to Kihei and had a nice lunch and layabout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe height=&quot;405&quot; width=&quot;590&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/7122582736/embed/a5602855ad48294a11ca7d3487719d7ac0222f26&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a flat ride, a good chunk on a busy highway. It also had brutal headwinds that seemed to change and hit me each way. At one point I just gave up riding and walked my bike along the sandy beach instead, tough life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_2081.JPG&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-4-olowalu-to-kahului&quot;&gt;Day 4: Olowalu to Kahului&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big ride was coming up, around Hana and I’d got a hotel back in Kahului to act as the launch point. So I wanted this day to be relatively quiet as well, but I did some of the simple short 20km route yesterday and it wasn’t that fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So instead I went the long way back to Kahului and reversed my route from the day before. Why the heck not, it was gorgeous. This time I got to stop at some different places on the way and it was just as amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe height=&quot;405&quot; width=&quot;590&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/7127821053/embed/4ed5c263f566ddae06399b7d295827833db5688f&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one hill that almost defeated me, called “The Wall” which &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/7127821053/segments/2959625694434573968&quot;&gt;Strava shows as 15.8%&lt;/a&gt; but feels more like 18%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_2120.JPG&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-5-kahului-to-kipahulu&quot;&gt;Day 5: Kahului to Kipahulu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the big one that I’d been looking forward to. I’d been lucky enough to get a campsite a Kipahulu, which is down in Haleakala National Park and half way around east Maui.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ❤️ the east side of Maui and was looking forward to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; A lot of people recommend doing this counter clockwise to avoid tourist traffic heading out to Hana. I did this clockwise because the week before the road near &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Kaupo,+HI+96790,+USA/@20.6364922,-156.1309922,15z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m8!1m2!10m1!1e1!3m4!1s0x7954ba30cdccfdb5:0xcfee263a13947dc3!8m2!3d20.6364792!4d-156.1222243&quot;&gt;Kaupo&lt;/a&gt; has been washed out and it was impassable. I wanted to ensure that I didn’t cycle counter clockwise, get to Kaupo and then be stuck and have to do a 170km diversion to get to my campsite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe height=&quot;405&quot; width=&quot;590&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/7138008219/embed/5df4b9d3bbf2ef1ee38149d9ec0d8159eb4b726d&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first part of the road until it gets into the “road to Hana” is mostly forgettable and a bit hilly. But then it turns into the most magnificient road ever. It generally flows really nicely and provides comfortable riding with amazing views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tourists are annoying as air conditioned tourists fight to pass each other in their rented SUVs that are far too big for the road and then park at each stop. But they didn’t really get in the way of riding and because they weren’t going fast generally were safe to be around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a wonderful drink and snack stop at Halfway to Hana that kindly filled up all my water bottles. After that you’ve got a long climb, so its good to fill up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most tourists run around at Hana, but that’s such a shame. The road down to Kipahulu just gets better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The campsite is spectacular and it was basically empty. I had a nice chat with the camp manager and in the past the camp was repeatedly overrun with people that were abusing the site. So they’ve introduced reservations and limited the number of visitors. If you can get a spot it’s worth it, amazing campsite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_2177.JPG&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wouldn’t be a visit to the national park without a hike up to the waterfalls that evening would it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe height=&quot;405&quot; width=&quot;590&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/7138007945/embed/8aba46fa2f77129d77cae7ca9f1aad5323ea7d90&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a tiring day, on top of a good ride yesterday and I slept well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-6-kipahulu-to-kahului&quot;&gt;Day 6: Kipahulu to Kahului&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The road was open. Funnily enough there were a few rental cars that really shouldn’t have been there either, but that’s always the way. This was another amazing ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The road is advertised as four wheel drive only. It’s just fine for a bike. A road bike would probably be ok, just take it easy on the gravelly bits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It starts with being close to the sea and beaches. Then it starts to open out and you get to climb. And climb. And climb. Many short steep sections. There is no water for 45km and 1,000 meters and it was getting up to 28c.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe height=&quot;405&quot; width=&quot;590&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowtransparency=&quot;true&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/7138008275/embed/f53b039a252167d21f91c1166f0f405e3de2d203&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This where I started to struggle. But I just rested a few times and enjoyed the remoteness. On one side you had the sea, the other the volcano stretching up with the observatory on top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_2238.JPG&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At about 45km you get to the Maui Winery and general store that sold water and food. It was a most welcome sight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately the climbing doesn’t stop until you reach the road that branches off to Haleakala. I didn’t take that and instead cruised dow the hill into Kahului - a nice chance to get my average speed up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-7-recovery-and-fly-home&quot;&gt;Day 7: Recovery and fly home&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I needed a break, my legs hurt, I was a bit sunburnt (no rain at all) and tired. So I packed my bike and lay on the beach drinking a beer and reading a book for a few hours before heading home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maui isn’t a big island and accomodation is a problem. If I did it again, I’d probably aim for a week in an apartment somewhere like Kihei and just use that as a base. Do west Maui in one day, then spend a day on the beach. Then do the volcano, then a day on the beach. That sort of thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winds are really, really strong. I’m glad I left my frame bag at home, it would have provided more surface area for the wind to catch. It was hard enough as it was. Minimize your surface area for the wind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally the Kihei and Lahaina areas are for tourists. Sandy beaches, no rain, no wind. That’s not the part of Maui that I love. The north shore of west Maui and the east side of Maui are beautiful, wild, remote and just perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Panniers</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2022-05-17-panniers/"/>
<updated>2022-05-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/panniers</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For my &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2022-04-24-first-trip/&quot;&gt;first trip&lt;/a&gt; I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mec.ca/en/product/5047-621/Division-Double-Pannier&quot;&gt;these panniers&lt;/a&gt; from MEC that were on my wife’s bike already. There was a few downsides I discovered with these panniers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They aren’t that big.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They aren’t waterproof.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The velcro to hold it down doesn’t always stick.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are fine for the trips my wife does, to and from school which takes 10 minutes. They hold up to the worst Vancouver rain for 10 minutes. However 8 hours of rain is another story, they got wet inside. Plus the velcro didn’t stay shut and then I worried about things falling out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I ended up with &lt;a href=&quot;https://waterflyshop.com/products/waterfly-bike-pannier-bag&quot;&gt;these panniers&lt;/a&gt;. They are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bigger, holding 25L according to the spec.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Waterproof, although I haven’t had them in 8 hours of rain yet.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Will stay closed thanks to lots of clips.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The downside is that they are not light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my first trip I was able to get all my usual gear in and have space for more. The sidepockets were really helpful for storing phones and tools in. So far, quite happy.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

</feed>
