<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Andy McKay</title>
    <updated>2025-09-26T01:17:34.127183+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://mckay.pub/</id>
    <author>
        <name>Andy McKay</name>
        <email>andy@mckay.pub</email>
    </author>
    
    <entry>
        <title>Big Agnes Tiger Wall UL2 Tent</title>
        <link href="https://mckay.pub/2025-09-25-a-two-person-tent.html"/>
        <published>2025-09-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <id>https://mckay.pub/2025-09-25-a-two-person-tent.html</id>
        <content type="html">
            &lt;p&gt;Last year I bought the &lt;a href=&#34;/2024-09-06-another-tent.html&#34;&gt;Big Agnes UL1 Tent&lt;/a&gt; which was a replacement for my &lt;a href=&#34;/2022-04-04-a-tent.html&#34;&gt;Tarptent ProTrail&lt;/a&gt;. I liked the Big Agnes tent so much, I sold my Tarptent and then bought another one. This time a 2 person tent to replace our aging 23+ year old MEC tent, which is heavy and in bad shape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;🚨 Big Agnes is a US company 🤦‍♂, so Canadian 🇨🇦 buyers beware. I bought this in 2024, before the current administration.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Tiger Wall UL2 Tent, like the UL1 Tent is a white &#34;solution dyed&#34; tent, which is meant to consume much less water during the production process. Like the UL1, it&#39;s light coming in at 776g when I weighed it on my scales at home, compared to 556g for the one man. That&#39;s light enough that I can use it for backpacking comfortably and took it to New Zealand and multiple trips within British Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the UL2 tent, it has doors and vestibule on either side of the tent, allowing occupants to get in and out easily, without disturbing others. The tent is a squish, you have to like the person you are in the tent with, there&#39;s enough room for my and the wife to lie flat on our backs, but not alot more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It comes with pockets on the sides, the top above heads and above the feet. This is enough space to put all your light stuff, leaving the rest to the vestibule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the UL1, it&#39;s semi-free standing, the frame stands on it&#39;s own at the front and sides, but the back requires at least two pegs. So far I&#39;ve put up the tent on wooden pads and it&#39;s been just fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s listed as three season tent and since I don&#39;t really camp in the winter, this is just fine for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got this on sale and it&#39;s not listed on Big Agnes site anymore, but so far I&#39;m very happy with all the Big Agnes tents I&#39;ve bought. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Total weight as carried - fly and inner sheet, poles, pegs with bag for each: &lt;code&gt;1126g&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are looking for a Canadian tent supplier, check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://durstongear.com/&#34;&gt;Durston&lt;/a&gt;, I haven&#39;t used their tents yet, but starting to see them more on hikes.&lt;/p&gt;
        </content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>