<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Andy McKay</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/blog/andy" rel="alternate"></link>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/blog/rss/latest/andy/" rel="self"></link>
<updated>2024-09-05T20:40:54+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/blog/andy</id>
<author>
<name>Andy McKay</name>
<email>andy@clearwind.ca</email>
</author>

<entry>
<title>Elsay Lake</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-09-05-elsay-lake/"/>
<updated>2024-09-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/elsay-lake</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Since my experience on &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2024-07-17-my-limit/&quot;&gt;Howe Sound Crest Trail&lt;/a&gt; I’ve not hiked as much or cared about peaks. So I was glad to be able to do a quick overnight up to Elsay Lake which is nearby and a lake I’ve seen from above - but never visited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also it’s a good overnight trip that I can do straight from my house and end up in the almost back country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;12318210614&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was an overcast day and heading up from Deep Cove I went from patchy sun, into deep cloud, into sun, into deep cloud and ended up at an overcast remote lake. I’ve all but the last 5km or so of this trail before and knew what to expect, until I hit that last 5km.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t hard, but for about 2km its just harder, steeper and less clearly marked than I expected. As you go around Mt Elsay, the trail drops down steeply about 150m of elevation. Overall going from the parking lot down to Elsay Lake means losing about 800m of elevation, the lake it’s self being at 765m elevation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I got to the lake I somehow tripped forward over a log and nailed the landing, no injuries. Or so I thought, I walked forward a few meters and was curious why the back of my leg stung. Somehow I had multiple gashes, 2 inches and 8 inches long on the back of my leg with bloody everywhere. Nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lake itself is lovely, quiet, serene and peaceful. The water was warm after all that hot summer weather. I camped next to the emergency shelter that night so I could use the porch to cook on. It was so quiet, not even sound from the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next day due to a bleeding leg, I decided to get a ride from Mt. Seymour resort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;12318247010&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think most people do the hike to and from Mt. Seymour and I’d definitely recommend that unless you are wanting that extra distance.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Jasper Fire</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-08-12-jasper-fires/"/>
<updated>2024-08-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/jasper-fires</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On July 22 a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/newsinteractives/features/the-monster-of-jasper&quot;&gt;monstrous fire ripped through Jasper&lt;/a&gt;. This was a terrible tragedy for residents, visitors and the environment in and around Jasper. I’ve got a huge amount of sympathy and empathy for those affected. A firefighter was killed battling the fire and that’s also terrible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A hashtag called #JasperStrong went around on social media and I’m more just #JasperSad than anything, because of the damage that has been inflicted on Canadians and Albertans, by those who contribute to climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For context, Alberta has the largest emissions of green house gases in Canada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/ghg-emissions.png&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s oil and gas industry is huge and is exporting oil and gas around the world. The Trans Mountain pipeline that Canadians tax payers paid &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theglobeandmail.com/business/article-canada-trans-mountain-pipeline-expansion/&quot;&gt;$34 billion&lt;/a&gt; for terminates very close to my house and will be pumping out fossil fuels for many decades to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years we have seen climate change affect so many parts of the world. But when it hits farmers in Central America, or causes floods in Asia or whatever a long way away, it can feel like it’s not really a problem. Something I don’t need to worry about. Something I can ignore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then when climate change hits the people close to you, so viscerally and so raw like this, you’d think it would change opinions. You’d think people would wake up and realise that we can’t avoid this, we need to stop it now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’d think so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like after the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2016_Fort_McMurray_wildfire&quot;&gt;Fort McMurray fire&lt;/a&gt; which at an estimated cost of $9.9 billion was the costliest disaster in Canadian history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like after the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lytton_wildfire&quot;&gt;Lytton fire&lt;/a&gt; which completely destroyed the town of Lytton (somewhere I’ve visited, it’s heartbreaking).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like after the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/british-columbia/bc-heat-dome-sudden-deaths-revised-2021-1.6232758&quot;&gt;heat dome&lt;/a&gt; that killed 595 people in British Columbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These aren’t heat events in far off places in the world, they are extreme events right in our own country and made much, much, worse by climate change. The thing that &lt;a href=&quot;https://albertabeyondfossilfuels.ca/alberta-and-the-carbon-budget/&quot;&gt;Alberta and Canada&lt;/a&gt; is contributing too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alberta’s Danielle Smith, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://duckduckgo.com/?t=ffab&amp;amp;q=danielle+smith+climate+change&amp;amp;ia=web&quot;&gt;elected leader of Jasper won’t talk about it, or diminishes it&lt;/a&gt;. The leader of the federal opposition talks about axing the Carbon tax, but not what they’ll do about actually get Canada to reduce its emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find it incredibly sad, that when we are faced with the evidence of the harm and damage to our own country we still can’t do anything about it. Alberta has continued down this path and elected politicians who continues to ignore it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why the Jasper fire made me #JasperSad.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Russet Lake</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-08-10-russet-lake/"/>
<updated>2024-08-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/russet-lake</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I haven’t done much back packing in Garibaldi, so extended a trip to Whistler with a chance to hike in the back country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;12081165554&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t leave until around lunch time, so I took the chance to take the gondola up to the Roundhouse at Whistler. Then it’s a good opportunity to get lost in all the trails around the top of the mountain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve got out of that it gradually gets quieter as you do the High Note trail, then quieter on the Musical Bumps trail to Russet Lake. This is a lovely trail that’s accessible to many people, it’s not at all technical and has amazing meadows with views of amazing glaciers and mountains on either side. It’s stunning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Camping at Russet Lake is nice, it was windy in the evening which kept the bugs away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only real problem I’ve got is that you are on a series of mountains that lead you one of two ways, towards Overlord Mountain, or back. There really isn’t anywhere to go with huge glacial valleys on either side. So next day I tried Overlord - an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Overlord_Mountain&quot;&gt;amazing peak with glaciers on either side at 2,625m&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;12081165844&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got up to over 2,115m on the way up Rector Peak and that’s when I found that the trail was getting more exposed than I liked. It probably would have been fine, but based on what &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alltrails.com/ar/trail/canada/british-columbia/overlord-mountain--2&quot;&gt;I read about online&lt;/a&gt; and spoke about with people who did it - I decided to turn around. The views were stunning at this point anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There wasn’t much else to do there, so I headed back down Singing Pass into Whistler. I partly wanted to see what Singing Pass was like and now I know. Consistent gradient, down in the shade of trees, and a pretty boring long hike down into Whistler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would do Russet Lake again, maybe try Overlord Mountain if I’m with someone or feeling in a better head space.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Mt. St. Helens</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-07-31-mt-st-helens/"/>
<updated>2024-07-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/mt-st-helens</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s an active volcano and we thought it would be cool to hike up it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;12006332708&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first hour is in trees and is nice. Then it opens up onto the volcano and you climb up a ridge basically to the top. The defining features of this hike are lava rocks and ash. There are many trails up the ridge, you aim for posts that have been erected, but generally want to avoid being too close to them as that’s the hardest route sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After an hour of that you hit a steep boulder field full of lava rock. It’s a real maze with no clear path so you just have to figure it out up the steep path. After an hour of that you’ve got the final leg which mostly ash and gravel. The last couple of hundred metres is so hard, one step forward, half a step back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone with a fear of vertical drops, there were no problems on this hike - until the view at the end. Get to the top and you are on the crater with a fantastic view and steep vertical drops. A few muinutes there was enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a brief snapshot into life in these areas, everyone we met on the trail was lovely. However we were approached by people wanting us to join (presumably Christian) morning service, many Trump flags and stickers and some guy sitting outside an ice cream shop asking us to vote Trump. Sigh.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Hitting my limit on the Howe Sound Crest Trail</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-07-17-my-limit/"/>
<updated>2024-07-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/my-limit</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ St Marks, ✅ Unneccessary, ✅ North Unneccessary, ✅ Thomas, ✅ James, ✅ David&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I 💚 hiking and the back country, camping and being out in nature. I like mountains and I’ve hiked lots of them. But I don’t like mountaineering in the sense of requiring vertical climbing, vertical drops, rock climbing etc. I’ve tried outdoors climbing and it just scared me, I just have a real fear of vertical drops. For the majority of hikes I’ve done &lt;em&gt;this has never been a problem&lt;/em&gt;. There’s the odd moment on mountains I didn’t like, but that’s rare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then I did the Howe Sound Crest trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11890867390&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This day enabled me to bag 6 peaks but completely destroyed me physically and pretty much wrecked me mentally too, I hit my limit. Between Unnecessary the other side of James Peak there was so much scrambly, vertical stuff that it scared the crap out of me. There’s the traverse around the West Lion, Thomas Peak, ridge walk up James Peak and then the traverse between James peaks. There are parts with vertical cliffs on both sides, sometimes just one side, sometimes inches away. Sometimes you are scrambling down rough rocks, roots and dirts towards instant death on cliffs. There are multiple places where a mis-step won’t just result in scratches, cuts or hurt limb, but just straight death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Many people do these trails and have no problem. This is likely just my problem.&lt;/em&gt; Some even love big drops and you’ll see them grinning on pictures. I don’t. It’s not just the medical problems I’ve had like inner ear vertigo type problems, I just can’t do it. Howe Sound Crest Trail pushed me over my limit and I was just terrified at points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was going to do the whole trail, but in the end found the quickest way off the trail when I realised it was just getting worse and went down into Lions Bay instead of camping. Of course, I’d done all the hard and scary parts and could have just continued, but I understood I was in a bad state and could not face anything else that day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that my problems aren’t shared and went back to read resources to check I wasn’t missing something. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.ca/Glorious-Mountains-Vancouvers-North-Shore/dp/1771602414&quot;&gt;Glorious Mountains of the North Shore&lt;/a&gt; says things like “There is no real exposure, but there exists the possibility for a fall and an injury.” and “Just take it calm and slow” and “Take care when approaching… a fall to the west would be fatal”. I like this book a lot, but for me the danger felt much worse and much more stressful than was presented. The Howe Sound Crest trail is number 2 in trails for search and rescue according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://bc.ctvnews.ca/these-10-b-c-trails-had-the-most-search-and-rescue-calls-last-year-1.6405200&quot;&gt;this list&lt;/a&gt; (actually this was a pretty accurate depiction).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, it’s done I’ll never go back and I can now definitely start crossing off mountains I will never, ever do. I’m no longer sure I’ll do all the peaks on the North Shore or even want to do this anymore, we’ll see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One up side, because I did this with a full backpack on a hot day and took a longer route by exiting… I burnt through what I think is a record 6,309 calories, over 12 hours for one of my biggest single day efforts ever. I was a wreck.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Goat Mountain, Goat Ridge Peak</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-07-13-goat/"/>
<updated>2024-07-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/goat</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ Goat Mountain, ✅ Goat Ridge Peak&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goat Mountain is relatively straightforward, but has very steep paths up it. Some of those steep parts have chains, others do not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there it’s a hike around the ridge to Goat Ridge Peak. This is through heather, blueberry bushes and small trees, with many patches of snow causing streams and waterfalls. This is one of the most beautiful hikes I’ve done this year with absolutely amazing views. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I wasn’t alone. With clear and recent bear footprints in the snow and the mud. Not surprising given the number of blueberry bushes that will be perfect bear food soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11873068247&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What started out as a relatively easy hike, soon turned into something that I struggled with. My heart rate was climbing fast, I was tired and felt more wiped than I have in a long time. The feeling was similar to when I struggled on &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2023-08-18-mt-frosty/&quot;&gt;Mt Frosty&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hike across the peak is very exposed and I was in the mid-day sun at that point for quite a while, working my way across snow. I was tired, dehydrated and had lost a lot of electrolytes which I hadn’t replaced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I pulled a muscle climbing down some quite vertical sections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time I got back to the gondola I was thoroughly drained and tired. Currently I’m doubting if I can actually complete my goal, not only are some peaks really hard (and look very intimidating from up high), but I really questioned by fitness today. At this point I think I’m gonna have to make doing all the peaks a 2024 and 2025 goal.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Pump Peak, Tim Jones Peak, Mt. Seymour</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-07-10-tim-jones-mt-seymour/"/>
<updated>2024-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/tim-jones-mt-seymour</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ 2️⃣ Pump Peak, ✅ Tim Jones Peak, ✅ Mt Seymour&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mountain lakes swum: 1️⃣&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was originally aiming for Runner Peak, but decided that wasn’t happening today. The more I look at Runner Peak, the less I want to do it. Getting up Pump, Second and Third peaks was just fine. It was a hot day around 30c in town, a little cooler on the mountain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are still small patches of snow in parts, but everything is now hikeable and its only parts that get a lot of shade that have snow. No spikes needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11856984669&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really disappointed to be having to pick up garbage on Pump Peak, including plastic water bottles, ziploc baggies and instant noodle packets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stopped at Mystery Lake on the way down. One month ago (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/11606417454&quot;&gt;June 8th&lt;/a&gt;) we went past Mystery Lake and it was partially frozen, surrounded by snow. Today there was no snow. I stopped for a swim and it was glorious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting a new counter of mountain lakes swum in with a counter of 1️⃣ 😎&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Silver Star, Mt. Fromme</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-07-09-silver-star-fromme/"/>
<updated>2024-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/silver-star-fromme</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ Mount Fromme&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the weekend I was in Silver Star resort, so did some hiking on Silver Star Mountain. These aren’t peaks on the North Shore, but it was nice to do something different. We hiked up over Silver Star, down into the provincial park and then back around the hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11824384416&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was hot and the hike up was surrounded with lovely wildflowers. Going into the provincial park side wasn’t much to speak of, long trails with no people, no views, trees on every side, boggy and with bugs. The Black Prince cabin was neat though. Overall it was nice to get a lot of kms on new boots and it was pretty and sunny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that Silver Star hiking trails are very few, since its mostly for mountain bikers, and then they charge you to hike - I wouldn’t recommend it as a hiker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I did Fromme, which is a peak for the peak baggers list. We went down from the Gondola, then up pipeline pass and up to the top of the mountain. Then all the way down to Skyline road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11849326232&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall I really liked Fromme, not too long and steep. A nice flat top to relax on and (mostly) a nice gentle downhill. Would recommend as a nice day hike for most people. It was also really cool to see good views of all the other mountains I’ll be doing as well 😎&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Grouse, Dam and Little Goat</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-06-30-little-goat/"/>
<updated>2024-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/little-goat</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ Grouse ✅ Dam ✅ Little Goat&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are three of the easier peaks on the North Shore, being close to the top of the gondola. Which I took up, making for a relatively easy day. It wasn’t raining and when the skies momentarily cleared was quite warm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The snow hasn’t melted and after Dam it was continuous snow with some parts of the trail hard to make out, due to the lack of tape and flagging in the trees. The clouds cleared momentarily for nice views of Goat and Kennedy Lake, but those views were brief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11778271735&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting back to the gondola I found out it had broken down. Looking at the queue size and number of people, I figured it would be several trips before I could get on the gondola so may as well do the BCMC down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11778576586&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gondola wasn’t fixed until that evening, meaning that apparently many people ill-equipped and not physically able to do the trail were taking it down in the evening. It’s a slippery trail and so there were many first responders out to help. I was on the bus home by that point, but that sounds like a tough day for many.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Mount Strachan</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-06-25-mt-strachan/"/>
<updated>2024-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/mt-strachan</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ Mount Strachan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saturday we headed up Mount Strachan. This is a pretty easy hike, but again at about 1,100m elevation we hit snow and ice. We were able to keep going, but it was inconsistent snow and bare rock - making spikes hard to use on my feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end we just gave up and hiked the ski runs up and down, boring but got the job done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11714341190&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got to the peak, but the true peak (10m higher) was looking rather scary, with very steep up and downs on invisible trails across treacherous snow. At this point, like everyone else we encountered that day, we decided not to go for the other peak and turn back from the true peak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s one of those weekends where I had grand plans of more peaks and they didn’t happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Damn.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>A backpack</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-06-17-a-backpack/"/>
<updated>2024-06-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/a-backpack</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In recent years I’ve upgraded some of my gear as I get more into backpacking, with things like a &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2022-04-04-a-tent/&quot;&gt;new tent&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2022-04-05-sleeping-bag/&quot;&gt;sleeping bag&lt;/a&gt; and so on. One thing I hadn’t done was look seriously at my backpack which I’d just bought at MEC for a trip around Europe because it seemed ok. I was thinking I needed something lighter and more comfortable. So I went to &lt;a href=&quot;https://vpo.ca/&quot;&gt;Valhalla Pure Outfitters&lt;/a&gt; (there’s one in North Vancouver now) and one of my old running mates works there and was able to give me some great detailed advice. And here’s what I got: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.osprey.com/talontm-velocity-30?color=Dark%2520Charcoal%2520Tumbleweed%2520Yellow&quot;&gt;Osprey Talon Velocity 30L&lt;/a&gt; and I 💚 it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/talon.png&quot; height=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s attention to detail on this pack that I’ve not seen on any of my other bags. All the straps have bits to stop them flapping. The side pockets can be accessed from the top and side - its easy to reach around and grab something without taking it off. The front straps are wide meaning its comfortable against my body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, this backpack is well fitting and barely feels like I’m carrying any weight at all. The slim but tall profile means that my centre of gravity is close to be body. Weight is well distributed onto my hips. Honestly a lot of time it feels like I’m barely carrying any weight. I’ve done multiple 5+ hour hikes with it so far and haven’t really noticed the weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s enough space that I can carry all my day gear, the ten essentials, all my overnight gear and spare clothes and food in it with ease. It has been a game changer. It turns out it’s not super light at 990g (but that’s 160g lighter than my last) but it’s so well designed and comfortable, I can’t imagine wanting anything else at this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has enabled me to easily carry emergency overnight gear on all my hikes, without any penalty. Even if I don’t plan on staying overnight, I can now comfortably hike the North Shore knowing that if a problem occurs, or I just run out of light, I can just settle in for the night and resume my hike the next day. That feels like the safest way to hike and that’s why I’m really happy with this pack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This now means I’ve got:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A small 5L Salomon running pack for runs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A small 10L Salomon running pack for day hikes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A 30L Osprey backpack for long hikes or a few days of backpacking.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A 40L MEC backpack for longer backpacking trips.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A 65L Arcteryx monster backpack for when I want to carry the world and hate myself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Pump Peak, Suicide Bluffs and Hollyburn</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-06-16-snow-in-june/"/>
<updated>2024-06-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/snow-in-june</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ Pump Pake ✅ Suicide Bluffs ✅ Hollyburn&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wet and snowy conditions on the mountains persist and this is making some bigger mountains challenging. At this time of year the snow is slippery and in the process of melting, it can be dangerous. On Saturday I went through the snow and fell into a rock and have many bruises, I got off easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saturday was an attempt to do Pump Peak and maybe beyond, but the snow was consistent and deep all the way from the base of the Brockton chair lift. At that point I put my spikes on, got my poles out and kept them out all the way up and back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11661066707&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the top when I got there (in the morning) there was very little visibility and over 1m+ deep snow still covering everything but the most exposed rocks. The weather was bad and I did not fancy trying to do Tim Jones Peak or Mount Seymour - those are on the way if you do Runners Peak or Elsay anyways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way back I decided to do Suicide Bluffs and then looped around to Dog Mountain. The snow had mostly cleared at this elevation and the trail was easy to follow. The weather lifted for a bit, there was even the odd bit of sun and some stunning views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunday was Hollyburn was snowy. And I was snowed on and rained on and cold. It was like a hike in December, not the middle of June.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11668479384&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the way down I was wondering if I’d chosen the wrong year to track and bag so many peaks. July to September is going to be &lt;strong&gt;busy&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; I’ve removed peaks below 1,000m on Gambier, Anvil and Bowen (apart from the one I did) because they just don’t interest me. Others might do them but I won’t be.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Vancouver Python User Group Changes</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-06-12-leaving-meetup/"/>
<updated>2024-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/leaving-meetup</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Summary: Meetup is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/blog/new-organizer-pricing-key-improvements/&quot;&gt;increasing prices&lt;/a&gt; so the costs for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/vanpyz/&quot;&gt;Python User Group&lt;/a&gt; will be over $700 CAD a year. &lt;strong&gt;We are closing our Meetup account and moving to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/vancouver/vanpy&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; before July 7th 2024&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-do-we-need&quot;&gt;What do we need?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need somewhere to organise activities and talks, announce events and communicate with the community. These are pretty simple and straightforward requirements. We’ve actually been doing a bunch of these things using GitHub anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-not-meetup&quot;&gt;Why not Meetup?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meetup has been costing it’s organisers about $37 CAD a month for ages and has just increased it’s price to over $60 CAD a month. The minimal functionality Meetup provides is not worth it. This was not optional price raise, there was no grandfathering in of old Meetups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When talking to the former organizer Bryan Chow about this, he resisted moving off Meetup and saving himself money because of how hard it is get off of Meetup. Since we can’t get an export of emails out of Meetup, we know that any shift to a new platform will cost us users, probably most of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A price rise of that amount for features that suck or should be free is unacceptable. Plus, I’m retiring and don’t want to spend my money on Meetup. It also means it’s really hard to either get anyone else to run it - no-one wants to take on this money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, here’s the first question Meetup asks when I decide to cancel:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/fuck-you-meetup.png&quot; width=&quot;800px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No - &lt;strong&gt;fuck you Meetup&lt;/strong&gt;. That’s not what this community is about. So just to be clear &lt;strong&gt;I will never charge people to come to a simple Python meetup&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-github&quot;&gt;Why GitHub?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s free and it will be for a long time yet. It does all the things we need. Everyone has an account there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We will&lt;/em&gt; lose people, &lt;em&gt;we will&lt;/em&gt; lose visibility and I think pretty much anyone else can take over the old group on Meetup. It’s like Meetup is holding us hostage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-next&quot;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/vancouver/vanpy&quot;&gt;vancouver/vanpy&lt;/a&gt; and click on the &lt;code&gt;Watch&lt;/code&gt; button:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/vanpy-watch.png&quot; width=&quot;800px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then select &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;All activity&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/vanpy-watch-all.png&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you get a lot of GitHub notifications, this might be a chance to try &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.github.com/en/account-and-profile/managing-subscriptions-and-notifications-on-github/viewing-and-triaging-notifications/customizing-a-workflow-for-triaging-your-notifications&quot;&gt;prioritizing your notifications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Mastodon follow the &lt;a href=&quot;https://hachyderm.io/@vanpy&quot;&gt;@vanpy&lt;/a&gt; account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-python-software-foundation&quot;&gt;The Python Software Foundation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PSF has a grant program to get Meetup costs paid for. I applied for that in November 2023 (yep &lt;strong&gt;8 months ago&lt;/strong&gt;) and still haven’t been added into the PSF program. At the last discord Q&amp;amp;A I think I heard that the person who as able to do this was on holiday (or something like that). I’m sorry for other user groups in this situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure what’s happened there with the PSF grants program but I’m not gonna keep waiting for whatever is happening to sort itself out. Perhaps there’s better places for the PSF grants than funding Meetup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; I have charged for conferences, but those are big and require money to put on.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

</feed>
