<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Andy McKay</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/blog/andy" rel="alternate"></link>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/blog/rss/latest/andy/" rel="self"></link>
<updated>2024-07-17T16:52:27+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/blog/andy</id>
<author>
<name>Andy McKay</name>
<email>andy@clearwind.ca</email>
</author>

<entry>
<title>Hitting my limit on the Howe Sound Crest Trail</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-07-17-my-limit/"/>
<updated>2024-07-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/my-limit</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ St Marks, ✅ Unneccessary, ✅ North Unneccessary, ✅ Thomas, ✅ James, ✅ David&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I 💚 hiking and the back country, camping and being out in nature. I like mountains and I’ve hiked lots of them. But I don’t like mountaineering in the sense of requiring vertical climbing, vertical drops, rock climbing etc. I’ve tried outdoors climbing and it just scared me, I just have a real fear of vertical drops. For the majority of hikes I’ve done &lt;em&gt;this has never been a problem&lt;/em&gt;. There’s the odd moment on mountains I didn’t like, but that’s rare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then I did the Howe Sound Crest trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11890867390&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This day enabled me to bag 6 peaks but completely destroyed me physically and pretty much wrecked me mentally too, I hit my limit. Between Unnecessary the other side of James Peak there was so much scrambly, vertical stuff that it scared the crap out of me. There’s the traverse around the West Lion, Thomas Peak, ridge walk up James Peak and then the traverse between James peaks. There are parts with vertical cliffs on both sides, sometimes just one side, sometimes inches away. Sometimes you are scrambling down rough rocks, roots and dirts towards instant death on cliffs. There are multiple places where a mis-step won’t just result in scratches, cuts or hurt limb, but just straight death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Many people do these trails and have no problem. This is likely just my problem.&lt;/em&gt; Some even love big drops and you’ll see them grinning on pictures. I don’t. It’s not just the medical problems I’ve had like inner ear vertigo type problems, I just can’t do it. Howe Sound Crest Trail pushed me over my limit and I was just terrified at points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was going to do the whole trail, but in the end found the quickest way off the trail when I realised it was just getting worse and went down into Lions Bay instead of camping. Of course, I’d done all the hard and scary parts and could have just continued, but I understood I was in a bad state and could not face anything else that day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understood that my problems aren’t shared and went back to read resources to check I wasn’t missing something. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.ca/Glorious-Mountains-Vancouvers-North-Shore/dp/1771602414&quot;&gt;Glorious Mountains of the North Shore&lt;/a&gt; says things like “There is no real exposure, but there exists the possibility for a fall and an injury.” and “Just take it calm and slow” and “Take care when approaching… a fall to the west would be fatal”. I like this book a lot, but for me the danger felt much worse and much more stressful than was presented. The Howe Sound Crest trail is number 2 in trails for search and rescue according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://bc.ctvnews.ca/these-10-b-c-trails-had-the-most-search-and-rescue-calls-last-year-1.6405200&quot;&gt;this list&lt;/a&gt; (actually this was a pretty accurate depiction).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, it’s done I’ll never go back and I can now definitely start crossing off mountains I will never, ever do. I’m no longer sure I’ll do all the peaks on the North Shore or even want to do this anymore, we’ll see.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Goat Mountain, Goat Ridge Peak</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-07-13-goat/"/>
<updated>2024-07-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/goat</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ Goat Mountain, ✅ Goat Ridge Peak&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goat Mountain is relatively straightforward, but has very steep paths up it. Some of those steep parts have chains, others do not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there it’s a hike around the ridge to Goat Ridge Peak. This is through heather, blueberry bushes and small trees, with many patches of snow causing streams and waterfalls. This is one of the most beautiful hikes I’ve done this year with absolutely amazing views. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I wasn’t alone. With clear and recent bear footprints in the snow and the mud. Not surprising given the number of blueberry bushes that will be perfect bear food soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11873068247&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What started out as a relatively easy hike, soon turned into something that I struggled with. My heart rate was climbing fast, I was tired and felt more wiped than I have in a long time. The feeling was similar to when I struggled on &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2023-08-18-mt-frosty/&quot;&gt;Mt Frosty&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hike across the peak is very exposed and I was in the mid-day sun at that point for quite a while, working my way across snow. I was tired, dehydrated and had lost a lot of electrolytes which I hadn’t replaced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I pulled a muscle climbing down some quite vertical sections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time I got back to the gondola I was thoroughly drained and tired. Currently I’m doubting if I can actually complete my goal, not only are some peaks really hard (and look very intimidating from up high), but I really questioned by fitness today. At this point I think I’m gonna have to make doing all the peaks a 2024 and 2025 goal.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Pump Peak, Tim Jones Peak, Mt. Seymour</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-07-10-tim-jones-mt-seymour/"/>
<updated>2024-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/tim-jones-mt-seymour</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ 2️⃣ Pump Peak, ✅ Tim Jones Peak, ✅ Mt Seymour&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mountain lakes swum: 1️⃣&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was originally aiming for Runner Peak, but decided that wasn’t happening today. The more I look at Runner Peak, the less I want to do it. Getting up Pump, Second and Third peaks was just fine. It was a hot day around 30c in town, a little cooler on the mountain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are still small patches of snow in parts, but everything is now hikeable and its only parts that get a lot of shade that have snow. No spikes needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11856984669&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really disappointed to be having to pick up garbage on Pump Peak, including plastic water bottles, ziploc baggies and instant noodle packets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stopped at Mystery Lake on the way down. One month ago (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/11606417454&quot;&gt;June 8th&lt;/a&gt;) we went past Mystery Lake and it was partially frozen, surrounded by snow. Today there was no snow. I stopped for a swim and it was glorious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting a new counter of mountain lakes swum in with a counter of 1️⃣ 😎&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Silver Star, Mt. Fromme</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-07-09-silver-star-fromme/"/>
<updated>2024-07-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/silver-star-fromme</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ Mount Fromme&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the weekend I was in Silver Star resort, so did some hiking on Silver Star Mountain. These aren’t peaks on the North Shore, but it was nice to do something different. We hiked up over Silver Star, down into the provincial park and then back around the hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11824384416&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was hot and the hike up was surrounded with lovely wildflowers. Going into the provincial park side wasn’t much to speak of, long trails with no people, no views, trees on every side, boggy and with bugs. The Black Prince cabin was neat though. Overall it was nice to get a lot of kms on new boots and it was pretty and sunny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that Silver Star hiking trails are very few, since its mostly for mountain bikers, and then they charge you to hike - I wouldn’t recommend it as a hiker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I did Fromme, which is a peak for the peak baggers list. We went down from the Gondola, then up pipeline pass and up to the top of the mountain. Then all the way down to Skyline road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11849326232&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall I really liked Fromme, not too long and steep. A nice flat top to relax on and (mostly) a nice gentle downhill. Would recommend as a nice day hike for most people. It was also really cool to see good views of all the other mountains I’ll be doing as well 😎&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Grouse, Dam and Little Goat</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-06-30-little-goat/"/>
<updated>2024-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/little-goat</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ Grouse ✅ Dam ✅ Little Goat&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are three of the easier peaks on the North Shore, being close to the top of the gondola. Which I took up, making for a relatively easy day. It wasn’t raining and when the skies momentarily cleared was quite warm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The snow hasn’t melted and after Dam it was continuous snow with some parts of the trail hard to make out, due to the lack of tape and flagging in the trees. The clouds cleared momentarily for nice views of Goat and Kennedy Lake, but those views were brief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11778271735&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting back to the gondola I found out it had broken down. Looking at the queue size and number of people, I figured it would be several trips before I could get on the gondola so may as well do the BCMC down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11778576586&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gondola wasn’t fixed until that evening, meaning that apparently many people ill-equipped and not physically able to do the trail were taking it down in the evening. It’s a slippery trail and so there were many first responders out to help. I was on the bus home by that point, but that sounds like a tough day for many.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Mount Strachan</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-06-25-mt-strachan/"/>
<updated>2024-06-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/mt-strachan</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ Mount Strachan&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saturday we headed up Mount Strachan. This is a pretty easy hike, but again at about 1,100m elevation we hit snow and ice. We were able to keep going, but it was inconsistent snow and bare rock - making spikes hard to use on my feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end we just gave up and hiked the ski runs up and down, boring but got the job done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11714341190&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got to the peak, but the true peak (10m higher) was looking rather scary, with very steep up and downs on invisible trails across treacherous snow. At this point, like everyone else we encountered that day, we decided not to go for the other peak and turn back from the true peak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s one of those weekends where I had grand plans of more peaks and they didn’t happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Damn.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>A backpack</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-06-17-a-backpack/"/>
<updated>2024-06-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/a-backpack</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In recent years I’ve upgraded some of my gear as I get more into backpacking, with things like a &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2022-04-04-a-tent/&quot;&gt;new tent&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2022-04-05-sleeping-bag/&quot;&gt;sleeping bag&lt;/a&gt; and so on. One thing I hadn’t done was look seriously at my backpack which I’d just bought at MEC for a trip around Europe because it seemed ok. I was thinking I needed something lighter and more comfortable. So I went to &lt;a href=&quot;https://vpo.ca/&quot;&gt;Valhalla Pure Outfitters&lt;/a&gt; (there’s one in North Vancouver now) and one of my old running mates works there and was able to give me some great detailed advice. And here’s what I got: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.osprey.com/talontm-velocity-30?color=Dark%2520Charcoal%2520Tumbleweed%2520Yellow&quot;&gt;Osprey Talon Velocity 30L&lt;/a&gt; and I 💚 it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/talon.png&quot; height=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s attention to detail on this pack that I’ve not seen on any of my other bags. All the straps have bits to stop them flapping. The side pockets can be accessed from the top and side - its easy to reach around and grab something without taking it off. The front straps are wide meaning its comfortable against my body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, this backpack is well fitting and barely feels like I’m carrying any weight at all. The slim but tall profile means that my centre of gravity is close to be body. Weight is well distributed onto my hips. Honestly a lot of time it feels like I’m barely carrying any weight. I’ve done multiple 5+ hour hikes with it so far and haven’t really noticed the weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s enough space that I can carry all my day gear, the ten essentials, all my overnight gear and spare clothes and food in it with ease. It has been a game changer. It turns out it’s not super light at 990g (but that’s 160g lighter than my last) but it’s so well designed and comfortable, I can’t imagine wanting anything else at this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has enabled me to easily carry emergency overnight gear on all my hikes, without any penalty. Even if I don’t plan on staying overnight, I can now comfortably hike the North Shore knowing that if a problem occurs, or I just run out of light, I can just settle in for the night and resume my hike the next day. That feels like the safest way to hike and that’s why I’m really happy with this pack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This now means I’ve got:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A small 5L Salomon running pack for runs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A small 10L Salomon running pack for day hikes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A 30L Osprey backpack for long hikes or a few days of backpacking.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A 40L MEC backpack for longer backpacking trips.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A 65L Arcteryx monster backpack for when I want to carry the world and hate myself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Pump Peak, Suicide Bluffs and Hollyburn</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-06-16-snow-in-june/"/>
<updated>2024-06-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/snow-in-june</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ Pump Pake ✅ Suicide Bluffs ✅ Hollyburn&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wet and snowy conditions on the mountains persist and this is making some bigger mountains challenging. At this time of year the snow is slippery and in the process of melting, it can be dangerous. On Saturday I went through the snow and fell into a rock and have many bruises, I got off easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saturday was an attempt to do Pump Peak and maybe beyond, but the snow was consistent and deep all the way from the base of the Brockton chair lift. At that point I put my spikes on, got my poles out and kept them out all the way up and back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11661066707&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the top when I got there (in the morning) there was very little visibility and over 1m+ deep snow still covering everything but the most exposed rocks. The weather was bad and I did not fancy trying to do Tim Jones Peak or Mount Seymour - those are on the way if you do Runners Peak or Elsay anyways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way back I decided to do Suicide Bluffs and then looped around to Dog Mountain. The snow had mostly cleared at this elevation and the trail was easy to follow. The weather lifted for a bit, there was even the odd bit of sun and some stunning views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunday was Hollyburn was snowy. And I was snowed on and rained on and cold. It was like a hike in December, not the middle of June.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11668479384&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the way down I was wondering if I’d chosen the wrong year to track and bag so many peaks. July to September is going to be &lt;strong&gt;busy&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; I’ve removed peaks below 1,000m on Gambier, Anvil and Bowen (apart from the one I did) because they just don’t interest me. Others might do them but I won’t be.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Vancouver Python User Group Changes</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-06-12-leaving-meetup/"/>
<updated>2024-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/leaving-meetup</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Summary: Meetup is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/blog/new-organizer-pricing-key-improvements/&quot;&gt;increasing prices&lt;/a&gt; so the costs for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/vanpyz/&quot;&gt;Python User Group&lt;/a&gt; will be over $700 CAD a year. &lt;strong&gt;We are closing our Meetup account and moving to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/vancouver/vanpy&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; before July 7th 2024&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-do-we-need&quot;&gt;What do we need?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need somewhere to organise activities and talks, announce events and communicate with the community. These are pretty simple and straightforward requirements. We’ve actually been doing a bunch of these things using GitHub anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-not-meetup&quot;&gt;Why not Meetup?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meetup has been costing it’s organisers about $37 CAD a month for ages and has just increased it’s price to over $60 CAD a month. The minimal functionality Meetup provides is not worth it. This was not optional price raise, there was no grandfathering in of old Meetups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When talking to the former organizer Bryan Chow about this, he resisted moving off Meetup and saving himself money because of how hard it is get off of Meetup. Since we can’t get an export of emails out of Meetup, we know that any shift to a new platform will cost us users, probably most of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A price rise of that amount for features that suck or should be free is unacceptable. Plus, I’m retiring and don’t want to spend my money on Meetup. It also means it’s really hard to either get anyone else to run it - no-one wants to take on this money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, here’s the first question Meetup asks when I decide to cancel:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/fuck-you-meetup.png&quot; width=&quot;800px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No - &lt;strong&gt;fuck you Meetup&lt;/strong&gt;. That’s not what this community is about. So just to be clear &lt;strong&gt;I will never charge people to come to a simple Python meetup&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-github&quot;&gt;Why GitHub?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s free and it will be for a long time yet. It does all the things we need. Everyone has an account there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We will&lt;/em&gt; lose people, &lt;em&gt;we will&lt;/em&gt; lose visibility and I think pretty much anyone else can take over the old group on Meetup. It’s like Meetup is holding us hostage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-next&quot;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/vancouver/vanpy&quot;&gt;vancouver/vanpy&lt;/a&gt; and click on the &lt;code&gt;Watch&lt;/code&gt; button:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/vanpy-watch.png&quot; width=&quot;800px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then select &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;All activity&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/vanpy-watch-all.png&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you get a lot of GitHub notifications, this might be a chance to try &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.github.com/en/account-and-profile/managing-subscriptions-and-notifications-on-github/viewing-and-triaging-notifications/customizing-a-workflow-for-triaging-your-notifications&quot;&gt;prioritizing your notifications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Mastodon follow the &lt;a href=&quot;https://hachyderm.io/@vanpy&quot;&gt;@vanpy&lt;/a&gt; account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-python-software-foundation&quot;&gt;The Python Software Foundation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PSF has a grant program to get Meetup costs paid for. I applied for that in November 2023 (yep &lt;strong&gt;8 months ago&lt;/strong&gt;) and still haven’t been added into the PSF program. At the last discord Q&amp;amp;A I think I heard that the person who as able to do this was on holiday (or something like that). I’m sorry for other user groups in this situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure what’s happened there with the PSF grants program but I’m not gonna keep waiting for whatever is happening to sort itself out. Perhaps there’s better places for the PSF grants than funding Meetup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; I have charged for conferences, but those are big and require money to put on.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>de Pencier and Black</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-06-09-de-pencier-black/"/>
<updated>2024-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/de-pencier-black</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ de Pencier ✅ Black Mountain&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Saturday I did De Pencier by hiking all the way up from Deep Cove. I could have done it from the parking lot, but it’s a good practice hike and I was able to get a ride back down, so may as well take the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s currently snow free up to about 950m. Snow is common in shaded areas over 1000m and is constant in shaded areas over 1050m. Around Mystery Lake, Brockton chair and De Pencier itself is still snowy and  spikes highly recommended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11606417454&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Sunday I did Black Mountain from the Cypress parking lot. A shorter hike with my sore legs was most welcome. There were some patches of snow in shaded areas, but spikes weren’t needed and it was mostly clear. On the top of Black Mountain there was no snow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11613740810&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On both hikes any snow in exposed areas was rapidly melting.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Mt Gardner</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-05-20-gardner/"/>
<updated>2024-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/gardner</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ Mt. Gardner ❌ Suicide Bluffs ❌ de Pencier&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Saturday with a couple of friends we did Mt. Gardner on Bowen Island. It’s one of the lower peaks and guaranteed to be snow free. We hopped on the ferry, parked at the south west end and then went up the hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11441621211&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly it’s a pretty straightforward hike, a few steep parts. At the top the true summit is pretty rubbish, so head north to the telecommunication towers for a better view. All we saw was mist and cloud as the weather closed in. We hiked all the way down in the rain which of course stopped, right as we completed the hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Sunday I aimed to do Suicide Bluffs and de Pencier. I figured at 1,100m odd they’d be snow free or at least less snow, especially considering my experience on South Needle (similar elevation) the week before. How different it was. About 15 minutes after leaving the parking lot, we were facing continual snow and had our spikes on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11449574600&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suicide bluffs trail was deep snow, something we were not prepared for. There’s no trail visible, no markings and without snow shoes we were getting very wet. We turned back quite quickly, not wanting to venture anywhere near unstable snow or cornices. We then thought about de Pencier so headed over that way and faced similar deep snow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point it started raining and was cold. So knowing that these peaks are something I do regularly during the summer and will come back to, decided to call it quits. A little disappointing, but the amount of snow still up there was surprising. Going to be another couple of weeks before those are easy to do.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Hike - South Needle via Lynn Peak</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-05-12-south-needle/"/>
<updated>2024-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/south-needle</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ Lynn Peak ✅ Rice Peak ✅ South Needle&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of aiming for more bike races or longer runs, this year I’ve set my sights somewhere slightly different. Instead I’m going to try and bag all the peaks in North Vancouver, as defined by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.baggerchallenge.ca/peaks&quot;&gt;Peak Baggers group&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately that group requires Facebook and I refuse to use that site so I’ve &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;got my own list going&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a big list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s still early in the year for any of the higher North or West Vancouver peaks. Most people are doing Gambier, Bowen and Anvil. Those are hills I might do at some point, but don’t really interest me as much as the big ones on the mainland. So I thought yesterday I’d take a stab at the Needles in Lynn Valley, because they are lower than most of the other peaks and aren’t as likely to be covered in snow and ice. I tried to get to South Needle last year and was turned around by snow and ice that made it really hard to hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11389460096&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, getting up to the first couple of peaks was relatively straightforward and there wasn’t any snow. Between those peaks and the South Needle there were patches of snow but nothing too bad and up to the South Needle at 1163m. The hike there is great, at times you are walking on tree lined ridge with huge tree lined steep slopes on each side. The trail has really steep parts and there was just one bit on the South Needle where my nervousness with heights hit me - a small rock outcropping with a 100% chance of death if you slip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the top the north side and the Middle Needle was all snow and ice covered. I met a group up there who tried to go towards Middle Needle and saw the steep slope with big drops covered in snow, ice, all in various stages of melting and turned back. They had better gear than me (I just had crampons) so I knew that was not going to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/south-needle.png&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way down, I went down the Hydraulic Creek trail, which is really steep. Just looking at the elevation change on Strava 👆 makes this clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then it was either back out along the road through the Seymour Demonstration Forest, or even further by heading over to Fishermans Trail and coming out at the top of Riverside drive. I’ve run and cycled that trail a lot and forgotten how boring and long it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An amazing hike with amazing views, it was a shame I couldn’t get the other two needles in but I can get those from the Coliseum mountain side another time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there it goes, my first attempt at trying to bag all the peaks with a couple of relatively easy ones. Let’s see how it goes!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Trip - Joshua Tree</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2023-12-18-joshua-tree/"/>
<updated>2023-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/joshua-tree</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In my new job I had five days of vacation to spend by the end of the year. So I took a week and went to Palm Springs and then to Joshua Tree with a friend. The original plan was a few days in Joshua Tree National Park followed by a day or two in Mojave Desert with overnights each way in Palm Springs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days before leaving we were trudging knee deep through snow at the top of Mount Seymour in North Vancouver. This trip turned out to be quite a contrast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this trip I made a couple of additions to my gear because I was concerned about night time temperatures for camping which drop below zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I finally got a puffy style jacket to keep me warm, I’ve seen these on a bunch of trails and always thought they were a bit weird, preferring layers instead. Would recommend.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I got a sleeping bag liner which adds another 15c to the sleeping bag range. Would also recommend.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-1&quot;&gt;Day 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organizing, car rental, fuel and food stock up - that sort of thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-2&quot;&gt;Day 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first hike was in Joshua Tree from the Blackrock campground. A 13km hike up over two small peaks, this was mostly our just breaking in hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;10380978341&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a good hike with some nice views, but not too serious elevation. It turns out there wasn’t too much else from this campsite. So we moved on the next day to the park “for reals” and Ryan campground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But of course, we had to take bunch of photos in the dark and the sunset. This was probably more fun than the hiking for this day 😀&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_0524.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_0536.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was cold overnight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-3&quot;&gt;Day 3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After moving to our next campsite, Ryan Campground we did some hiking &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nps.gov/thingstodo/hike-lost-horse-mine.htm&quot;&gt;around a mine or something&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;10380978261&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were horses. This was a nicer hike deeper into the desert with more Joshua Trees (which aren’t trees). Hiking out along a dry river bed (deep sand) was ugh. Was starting to get the vibes that the desert is pretty same same at this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of obligatory night time photos 👇&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_0591.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;800px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was getting colder overnight, I was feeling it, but still doing ok.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-4&quot;&gt;Day 4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn’t move campsites so were able two really good hikes in. First was a short hike &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nps.gov/jotr/learn/nature/barker-dam-loop.htm&quot;&gt;around a dam&lt;/a&gt;, although empty at the moment causes a distinct change in the flora and fauna, plus cool rocks and so on. Was pretty cool actually and our favourite hike to date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;10380978219&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then had the time to do another hike and this was really good too. Had some hiking, decent elevation, abandoned mines, great rocks, some cool cacti and so on. Enjoyed this one too:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;10380978276&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This night was really cold. I didn’t look at a thermometer, but I really felt it this time, having cold legs. Woke up to ice covering the tent. That was enough of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-5&quot;&gt;Day 5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We gave up on going to Mojave desert as we felt we’d seen the desert now, although I know they are different, we were feeling kinda done. Also we couldn’t do another night in the cold so we went to a hotel for the night and had some margarita’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-6&quot;&gt;Day 6&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took the gondola up to San Jacinto up to about 2,500m. Then we walked from there to the peak of the mountain at 3,300m over 6.5 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;10386775996&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is so different to the desert, the heat and the fauna. It’s much drier but with tall trees everywhere and absolutely stunning views out to the Pacific at the end, this was absolutely worth it and just made the whole trip worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We made the second tram up at 10:15am, then spoke to the super nice ranger to get our permit and then set off. But because of the time of year, we ended back at the tram just as darkness was falling. It was close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_6098.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;800px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trail had ice bits on it where streams crossed, but overall it was clear and I didn’t need spikes at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It just felt so much like it’s own little ecosystem up there at 3,000m and I ❤️ it. Would do again. Also the highest mountain I’ve peaked (3x higher than Seymour, 1.5x higher than Mt Rohr) even though I didn’t do all the elevation in one go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it. Had a good trip and really enjoyed it. San Jacinto was definitely the highlight for me. Would think twice about going back, would only really be interested when its more likely to rain, because for that period the desert comes alive (apparently).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

</feed>
