<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Andy McKay</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/blog/andy" rel="alternate"></link>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/blog/rss/latest/andy/" rel="self"></link>
<updated>2024-06-09T19:17:03+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/blog/andy</id>
<author>
<name>Andy McKay</name>
<email>andy@clearwind.ca</email>
</author>

<entry>
<title>de Pencier and Black</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-06-09-de-pencier-black/"/>
<updated>2024-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/de-pencier-black</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ de Pencier ✅ Black Mountain&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Saturday I did De Pencier by hiking all the way up from Deep Cove. I could have done it from the parking lot, but it’s a good practice hike and I was able to get a ride back down, so may as well take the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s currently snow free up to about 950m. Snow is common in shaded areas over 1000m and is constant in shaded areas over 1050m. Around Mystery Lake, Brockton chair and De Pencier itself is still snowy and  spikes highly recommended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11606417454&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Sunday I did Black Mountain from the Cypress parking lot. A shorter hike with my sore legs was most welcome. There were some patches of snow in shaded areas, but spikes weren’t needed and it was mostly clear. On the top of Black Mountain there was no snow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11613740810&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On both hikes any snow in exposed areas was rapidly melting.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Mt Gardner</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-05-20-gardner/"/>
<updated>2024-05-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/gardner</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ Mt. Gardner ❌ Suicide Bluffs ❌ de Pencier&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Saturday with a couple of friends we did Mt. Gardner on Bowen Island. It’s one of the lower peaks and guaranteed to be snow free. We hopped on the ferry, parked at the south west end and then went up the hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11441621211&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly it’s a pretty straightforward hike, a few steep parts. At the top the true summit is pretty rubbish, so head north to the telecommunication towers for a better view. All we saw was mist and cloud as the weather closed in. We hiked all the way down in the rain which of course stopped, right as we completed the hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Sunday I aimed to do Suicide Bluffs and de Pencier. I figured at 1,100m odd they’d be snow free or at least less snow, especially considering my experience on South Needle (similar elevation) the week before. How different it was. About 15 minutes after leaving the parking lot, we were facing continual snow and had our spikes on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11449574600&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suicide bluffs trail was deep snow, something we were not prepared for. There’s no trail visible, no markings and without snow shoes we were getting very wet. We turned back quite quickly, not wanting to venture anywhere near unstable snow or cornices. We then thought about de Pencier so headed over that way and faced similar deep snow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point it started raining and was cold. So knowing that these peaks are something I do regularly during the summer and will come back to, decided to call it quits. A little disappointing, but the amount of snow still up there was surprising. Going to be another couple of weeks before those are easy to do.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Hike - South Needle via Lynn Peak</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2024-05-12-south-needle/"/>
<updated>2024-05-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/south-needle</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bagged: ✅ Lynn Peak ✅ Rice Peak ✅ South Needle&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ℹ️ &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;List of 2024 peaks bagged&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;florished&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of aiming for more bike races or longer runs, this year I’ve set my sights somewhere slightly different. Instead I’m going to try and bag all the peaks in North Vancouver, as defined by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.baggerchallenge.ca/peaks&quot;&gt;Peak Baggers group&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately that group requires Facebook and I refuse to use that site so I’ve &lt;a href=&quot;/files/peaks-bagged.html&quot;&gt;got my own list going&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a big list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s still early in the year for any of the higher North or West Vancouver peaks. Most people are doing Gambier, Bowen and Anvil. Those are hills I might do at some point, but don’t really interest me as much as the big ones on the mainland. So I thought yesterday I’d take a stab at the Needles in Lynn Valley, because they are lower than most of the other peaks and aren’t as likely to be covered in snow and ice. I tried to get to South Needle last year and was turned around by snow and ice that made it really hard to hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;11389460096&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, getting up to the first couple of peaks was relatively straightforward and there wasn’t any snow. Between those peaks and the South Needle there were patches of snow but nothing too bad and up to the South Needle at 1163m. The hike there is great, at times you are walking on tree lined ridge with huge tree lined steep slopes on each side. The trail has really steep parts and there was just one bit on the South Needle where my nervousness with heights hit me - a small rock outcropping with a 100% chance of death if you slip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the top the north side and the Middle Needle was all snow and ice covered. I met a group up there who tried to go towards Middle Needle and saw the steep slope with big drops covered in snow, ice, all in various stages of melting and turned back. They had better gear than me (I just had crampons) so I knew that was not going to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/south-needle.png&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way down, I went down the Hydraulic Creek trail, which is really steep. Just looking at the elevation change on Strava 👆 makes this clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then it was either back out along the road through the Seymour Demonstration Forest, or even further by heading over to Fishermans Trail and coming out at the top of Riverside drive. I’ve run and cycled that trail a lot and forgotten how boring and long it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An amazing hike with amazing views, it was a shame I couldn’t get the other two needles in but I can get those from the Coliseum mountain side another time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there it goes, my first attempt at trying to bag all the peaks with a couple of relatively easy ones. Let’s see how it goes!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Trip - Joshua Tree</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2023-12-18-joshua-tree/"/>
<updated>2023-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/joshua-tree</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In my new job I had five days of vacation to spend by the end of the year. So I took a week and went to Palm Springs and then to Joshua Tree with a friend. The original plan was a few days in Joshua Tree National Park followed by a day or two in Mojave Desert with overnights each way in Palm Springs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days before leaving we were trudging knee deep through snow at the top of Mount Seymour in North Vancouver. This trip turned out to be quite a contrast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this trip I made a couple of additions to my gear because I was concerned about night time temperatures for camping which drop below zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I finally got a puffy style jacket to keep me warm, I’ve seen these on a bunch of trails and always thought they were a bit weird, preferring layers instead. Would recommend.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I got a sleeping bag liner which adds another 15c to the sleeping bag range. Would also recommend.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-1&quot;&gt;Day 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organizing, car rental, fuel and food stock up - that sort of thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-2&quot;&gt;Day 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first hike was in Joshua Tree from the Blackrock campground. A 13km hike up over two small peaks, this was mostly our just breaking in hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;10380978341&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a good hike with some nice views, but not too serious elevation. It turns out there wasn’t too much else from this campsite. So we moved on the next day to the park “for reals” and Ryan campground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But of course, we had to take bunch of photos in the dark and the sunset. This was probably more fun than the hiking for this day 😀&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_0524.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_0536.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was cold overnight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-3&quot;&gt;Day 3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After moving to our next campsite, Ryan Campground we did some hiking &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nps.gov/thingstodo/hike-lost-horse-mine.htm&quot;&gt;around a mine or something&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;10380978261&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were horses. This was a nicer hike deeper into the desert with more Joshua Trees (which aren’t trees). Hiking out along a dry river bed (deep sand) was ugh. Was starting to get the vibes that the desert is pretty same same at this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of obligatory night time photos 👇&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_0591.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;800px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was getting colder overnight, I was feeling it, but still doing ok.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-4&quot;&gt;Day 4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn’t move campsites so were able two really good hikes in. First was a short hike &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nps.gov/jotr/learn/nature/barker-dam-loop.htm&quot;&gt;around a dam&lt;/a&gt;, although empty at the moment causes a distinct change in the flora and fauna, plus cool rocks and so on. Was pretty cool actually and our favourite hike to date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;10380978219&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then had the time to do another hike and this was really good too. Had some hiking, decent elevation, abandoned mines, great rocks, some cool cacti and so on. Enjoyed this one too:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;10380978276&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This night was really cold. I didn’t look at a thermometer, but I really felt it this time, having cold legs. Woke up to ice covering the tent. That was enough of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-5&quot;&gt;Day 5&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We gave up on going to Mojave desert as we felt we’d seen the desert now, although I know they are different, we were feeling kinda done. Also we couldn’t do another night in the cold so we went to a hotel for the night and had some margarita’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-6&quot;&gt;Day 6&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took the gondola up to San Jacinto up to about 2,500m. Then we walked from there to the peak of the mountain at 3,300m over 6.5 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;10386775996&quot; data-style=&quot;standard&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is so different to the desert, the heat and the fauna. It’s much drier but with tall trees everywhere and absolutely stunning views out to the Pacific at the end, this was absolutely worth it and just made the whole trip worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We made the second tram up at 10:15am, then spoke to the super nice ranger to get our permit and then set off. But because of the time of year, we ended back at the tram just as darkness was falling. It was close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_6098.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;800px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trail had ice bits on it where streams crossed, but overall it was clear and I didn’t need spikes at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It just felt so much like it’s own little ecosystem up there at 3,000m and I ❤️ it. Would do again. Also the highest mountain I’ve peaked (3x higher than Seymour, 1.5x higher than Mt Rohr) even though I didn’t do all the elevation in one go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;–&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it. Had a good trip and really enjoyed it. San Jacinto was definitely the highlight for me. Would think twice about going back, would only really be interested when its more likely to rain, because for that period the desert comes alive (apparently).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Race report - Mt Frosty</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2023-08-18-mt-frosty/"/>
<updated>2023-08-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/mt-frosty</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Mount Frosty is the tallest mountain in Manning Park at 2,426m and last week I tried to run over it as part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://trailwhisperer.ca/frosty/&quot;&gt;Frosty Mountain Ultra&lt;/a&gt;. Sort of. Last year in three days I &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2022-07-14-mt-frosty/&quot;&gt;hiked over it and absolutely loved it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m in no shape to try the 50km, but aimed for the 27km instead. This is the biggest trail run I’ve done yet in terms of distance and elevation. Further more after hiking it, I knew it was a challenge. Here’s the elevation change:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/frosty-elevation.png&quot; width=&quot;800px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mount Frosty can be snowy in the summer and this race has had people snowed on or torrential rain before now. This year the main enemy was going to be the sun. That’s why there was quite a long and detailed amount of gear to carry, that wasn’t light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one week after the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2023-08-11-six-and-seventh-fondo/&quot;&gt;Gran Fondo&lt;/a&gt; and my goal was “Have fun, Don’t die”. I didn’t die, I mostly had fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9863400549&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first 5km or so is a fun run through very dry dusty trails. Then there’s a climb up to Windy Joe. That was power hiking. Then it alternated running and hiking for the next 4km plus. This was my favourite part with some amazing lovely running in the trees. Then the 6km uphill climb started. We came out into the sun and I started to suffer. Soon my pace fell badly and it all started to go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I crested at 3h 5m, that’s 17km into the race and the views were just absolutely amazing. On the top was a bagpiper. A bagpiper who’d hiked up early in the morning to stand at the top and pipe everyone over. The sight and sound of a bagpiper dressed in pink, with a kilt, drinking a beer to help us all over was &lt;strong&gt;amazing&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/bagpiper.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that things went wrong, I had multiple heart problems and my pace just fell off. I was aiming for an hour and half running down the hill, it took me two hours and it wasn’t pleasant. Dehydration, the sun, overdid it on the first bit, not in shape, bad nutrition, bad sleep (I barely slept the night before). Probably all of that played a part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I survived, but the downhill was not pleasant. I’m fine now and a beer later helped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was an amazing mountain, a lovely few hours of suffering in a beautiful place, and a well organized event. Plus a bagpiper. I’d be happy to do it again, I’m not going to let a bad heart day stop me.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Trip report - Mt Habrich</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2023-08-13-mt-habrich/"/>
<updated>2023-08-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/mt-habrich</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Again, this wasn’t a trip (as in overnight), but since I tried it three times, I feel like its worth a post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mount Habrich is a mountain at 1795m, behind the Squamish Chief and the Sea to Sky Gondola. I took some relatives up the Sea to Sky Gondola one day and since I paid for the pass, converted it into a year pass. I looked at Habrich and Sky Pilot and thought I could do those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns out Sky Pilot is a “serious mountain” involving things like creavasses glaciers, and vertical climbing. Things I’m not mad keen on, I like long hours of cardio and suffering. So after family I tried to do Mt. Habrich loop. Only 11.4km loop at about 5h 31m, doesn’t sound too bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-attempt&quot;&gt;First attempt&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2023-06-20-juan-de-fuca/&quot;&gt;Juan de Fuca&lt;/a&gt; trail by boots just fell apart. I was annoyed that they only lasted a year, so decided to get some solid boots. So I got some serious &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mec.ca/en/product/5024-148/996-vioz-gore-tex-backpacking-boots&quot;&gt;Zamberlan boots&lt;/a&gt; and everyone I know who had them loved them… once they broke them in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No matter what I do I couldn’t seem to break them in and get blisters. So witness my first hike with them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9395027270&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to turn back at 5km with big blisters on my heels. They’d been hurting for a while and I’d tried many different socks and a heel lock with my laces, to no avail. Knowning that I had to keep my heels in good shape for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2023-07-31-west-coast-trail/&quot;&gt;West Coast Trail&lt;/a&gt;, I had to call it quits. Annoyed on the way home, I stopped at MEC and bought some light trail Solomon boots. I completed the whole West Coast Trail in 6 days with zero blisters in those new boots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;second-attempt&quot;&gt;Second attempt&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this one I had a meeting in the morning and got to the top of the gondola after lunch and my phone hadn’t charged, leaving me with low phone battery and limited time. Not great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9752733479&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you get up to point, there are many, many branches in the trail and they aren’t well flagged. Basically I went the wrong way, then had to backtrack mulitple times. I found the trail and headed up it, but this cost me an hour and got me soaked due to dew on bushes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then on the way up I got stung in 3 spots on both my legs by wasps. The dry weather has meant there are lots of aggressive wasps this year, sigh. I proceeded to get lost a couple more times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I got up to 1635m and got my first real view of the peak. There’s a ridge over to the mountain and at that point I realised:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I was really low on phone battery which I was relying on for maps, I also forgot my headlamp so had no other light source.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I was looking at an estimated 3 hours to get along the ridge to the mountain and back.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There was bad weather coming in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 3 hours, the last gondola would go down and in 4 it would be dark. At that point I realised I had inadequate time, equipment and planning. It was time to head back to the gondola. One advantage of doing this was that I found the best route back to the gondola and wouldn’t get lost next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;third-attempt&quot;&gt;Third attempt&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this I was fully prepared, with all the right gear, a fully charge phone, headlamp, waterproofs and plenty of time, even if the weather wasn’t as great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9778389866&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hit the 1635m spot I turned around on my second attempt in approx. 1h 30 mins, half the time of last time. I then had a long ridge to go along, which looked intimidating with an intimidating pointy mountain at the end. The weather started to close in, the occassional bit of rain and dramatic clouds coming in close. On one side of the meeting visibility was about 100m, ending at cliffs as clouds rose up. The other side of the mountain was clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ridge is up and down, with some vertical bits and ropes to help out. The trail doesn’t actually go up Mount Habrich at that point, its about 100m further up and looks incredibly steep and unforgiving. This is the terrain of mountain climbers, not hikers. I do not do well with vertical heights like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I took the loop down and that is incredibly steep and continuous down. It reaches the service road, which is then a simple boring hike out for 5h 22m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I did this again, I’d probably do it from the bottom in Squamish to get all that extra elevation. I’d also aim to do it on a nice day to get better views, instead of just cloud. My turn around on the second day was maybe a good idea, I might have gone into a bad situation in there, although on reflection I was probably still safe (unless I’d had an accident).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the mountain will be there tomorrow, it’s important I’m there tomorrow to do it as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>My Sixth and Seventh Whistler Gran Fondo</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2023-08-11-six-and-seventh-fondo/"/>
<updated>2023-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/six-and-seventh-fondo</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve done the Whislter Gran Fondo a few times (&lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2015-09-12-gran-fondo/&quot;&gt;first&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2016-11-03-second-fondo/&quot;&gt;second&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2017-09-10-third-fondo/&quot;&gt;third&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2018-09-09-fourth-fondo/&quot;&gt;fourth&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2019-09-20-fifth-fondo/&quot;&gt;fifth&lt;/a&gt;). This week I completed my seventh Whistler Gran Fondo and realised I didn’t write about last years. So here goes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sixth-gran-fondo-2022&quot;&gt;Sixth Gran Fondo (2022)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t train enough, I was in bad shape. There was a headwind, just a horrible headwind the whole way. That’s all I can remember. I couldn’t get many drafts, you had to pedal going downhill otherwise you couldn’t get any speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;7786997882&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the first hour, I knew I had no chance of beating my times, so I tried to relax. Mostly I just got stressed and tired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the ride I said that’s it, I didn’t enjoy it I won’t do it again. Then my daughter signed up to do it next year. I signed up to support her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;seventh-gran-fondo-2023&quot;&gt;Seventh Gran Fondo (2023)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming into this ride I’d probably done less cycling than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2017 (up to Fondo)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2018 (up to Fondo)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2019 (up to Fondo)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023 (up to Fondo)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Time&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;243h&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;232h 16m&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;165h 51m&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;55h 48m&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Distance&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5,050km&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5,279km&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3,889km&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1,221km&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Rides&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;198&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;136&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;75&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;40&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s quite remarkable how little cycling I’ve done compared to previous years. I’ve been focusing on hiking, backpacking and bit of running throughout the summer. A prolonged period of illness (6+ weeks) at the beginning of the season and not participating in &lt;a href=&quot;https://steedcycles.com/&quot;&gt;Steed ride club&lt;/a&gt; has had a big effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d already approached this Fondo as I ride I would take slow and easy, enjoying the ride and supporting my daughter. Then my daughter decided not to ride.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I chilled and enjoyed the ride. Unlike last year, going into it with that mentality from the start, I actually did find the ride enjoyable. Fantastic views, great people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9817035495&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not too fussed about the time and didn’t sign up for next year. Not sure if I’ll ride it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also needed to try and keep my body intact because next week I’ve got &lt;a href=&quot;https://trailwhisperer.ca/frosty/&quot;&gt;this race&lt;/a&gt; and I’m excited and nervous about this, the way I used to be about the Whistler Fondo.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Trip report - Lynn Lake</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2023-08-04-lynn-lake/"/>
<updated>2023-08-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/lynn-lake</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A one day hike isn’t much of a trip, but this hike is a bit unusual for me. Let’s go back in time to 2020 and the height of the pandemic. My friends were looking for a hike that’s longer, but is still nearby, but without many people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We run and hike to Norvan falls a lot and leading off from there are three main trails:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/3989340157&quot;&gt;Coliseum Mountain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strava.com/activities/5788093741/&quot;&gt;Hanes Valley&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and Lynn Lake&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At that time I’d heard of the others, but not Lynn Lake, it looked easier than the others and it would be cool to see the lake that feeds the river Lynn. It is not easier than the others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;first-attempt-2020&quot;&gt;First attempt: 2020&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was raining a bit and cloudy, typical North Vancouver summer. But we aren’t the kind to be slowed down by weather, so we went for it. After Norvan falls you get to a very steep section, that heads up about 200m. Really steep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the trail kinda vanishes and gets close to the river. Then the trail basically is the river and bushes. And at his point you realise hiking up a river bed might be easier when its not raining (so you are wet), the river is full of water (so you are really wet), and it’s cold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So at about 9km (and a few hours into the hike) as a bunch of thoroughly miserable humans, we abandoned the hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;second-attempt-2021&quot;&gt;Second attempt: 2021&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That pandemic thing is still happening so a different friend and I tried it. This time we did it when the river was low and it was not raining. I was prepared…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;5643789066&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However it was not sunny and the river still had water in it and most of the rocks were slippy due to the low clouds. We got further than last time, but the river got narrower and things got really slippy. We were getting worried about hurting ourselves, and eventually called it quits. Does this bloody lake even exist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;third-attempt-2023&quot;&gt;Third attempt: 2023&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m trying to do all the trails on the North Shore, so I decided to give it one last try. British Columbia has been in the worst drought ever and it hasn’t rained for months. The river will never be as low, so I tried one more time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9739621297&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I made it after 3 hours of hiking. Turns out that when we abandoned our second attempt, we were a couple of hundred metres away from turning off the river and back into the bush. We would have been off the slippy rocks that caused us problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There then follows another 200m elevation gain up to the lake, which is honestly just a pond and not really worth the trip. But I did it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;overall&quot;&gt;Overall&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will be hiking up a river bed, seriously. So if it’s got a lot of water in it, it’s going to vary between deadly (during floods) and getting you wet. Just do it in the summer when there’s not much water in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you get to the spot where you follow the river bed, it’s best not to try going into the bushes, just stick to the river bed for a while. It does eventually veer off into the forest, but just going straight up the river is good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You won’t have cell phone service for most of this one and allow yourself a good 7+ hours for this.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Trip report - Broken Islands</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2023-08-03-broken-islands/"/>
<updated>2023-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/broken-islands</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2016-07-09-broken-islands/&quot;&gt;2016 I was able to go to the Broken Islands&lt;/a&gt;, this year I was able to go again with my family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Broken Islands is on the west coast of Vancouver Island, which means that combined with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2023-07-31-west-coast-trail/&quot;&gt;West Coast Trail&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2023-06-20-juan-de-fuca/&quot;&gt;Juan de Fuca trail&lt;/a&gt; this year, I’ve managed to visit a small almost contiguous portion of the amazing island.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of this trip was to have a nice relaxing trip, not long hours of cardio suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-there&quot;&gt;Getting there&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past you could take the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ladyrosemarine.com/&quot;&gt;Frances Barkley&lt;/a&gt; boat from Port Alberni and it drops you off at the lodge nearby. However that’s no longer available because of a change in ownership of the lodge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So instead we drove to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/place/Toquart+Bay,+Ucluelet,+BC+V0R+2B0/@49.0230739,-125.3678869,14z/data=!4m14!1m7!3m6!1s0x54890eb87d1b663b:0xb0e618a4654b73cb!2sToquart+Bay!8m2!3d49.0230762!4d-125.3472445!16s%2Fg%2F11clht847j!3m5!1s0x54890ebadbcf96e5:0xba1f01a06bc43efd!8m2!3d49.019025!4d-125.3595125!16s%2Fg%2F11_qy1cvs?entry=ttu&quot;&gt;Toquart Bay&lt;/a&gt;, stayed the night, and then caught a ferry from the bay over to the lodge (this is optional, it’s about a 2 hour kayak).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting there proved to be a challenge because of the daily Highway 4 closures and the range of our Tesla.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The advertised &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/legal/tesla-faces-california-class-action-its-ev-range-claims-2023-08-03/&quot;&gt;range of a Tesla is sometimes a bit of a lie&lt;/a&gt; and I was concerned about the extra drag that the gear for four people (so much water) plus two kayaks on the roof would add to the trip. It turns out it wasn’t too bad and we were able to get from the Lantzville supercharger and back with 9% left on the batter (Model 3 long range).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-1-lodge-to-hand&quot;&gt;Day 1: Lodge to Hand&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the lodge we rented a canoe to go with our two kayaks. Of note, the lodge now has a tap for you to fill up on water. It’s the last drinkable water available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9675459494&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hand is one of the closest campsites and has some fantastic sandy beaches, with warm water. Hand used to have a homestead on it, run by Annie McKay in the early 1900’s that used to supply the whaling station at Uclelet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-2-hand-to-clarke&quot;&gt;Day 2: Hand to Clarke&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With talk of gale force winds closing in the afternoon, we focused on getting moving early. Coping with high winds in a kayak is hard, in a canoe it’s very, very hard. To the point where I was concerned for our safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we headed out to Clarke, thinking that we might just have to abandon on a beach somewhere. We didn’t and the gale force winds (gusts up to 80km/h was forecast) never materialized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9675459711&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did get us a little lost, always pays to double check your maps at regular intervals, was still a decent paddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-3-benson-island&quot;&gt;Day 3: Benson island&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a rest day, with a trip to Benson island, a short hike and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9681782216&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s talk about water for a moment. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://parks.canada.ca/pn-np/bc/pacificrim/activ/camping/activ4&quot;&gt;parks site&lt;/a&gt; recommends: “Potable water is not available on the islands. Bring an adequate amount of freshwater with you. We recommend 4-6 litres per person, per day.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For 4 people, for 4+ days, minimum 4 litres per day is 64 litres of water. That’s a lot of water. We were going through at most 8 a day. That’s for cooking all our dehydrated food - and it was really sunny the first couple of days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took well over 64 liters of water and ending up throwing over 50% of it away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-4-clark-to-dodd&quot;&gt;Day 4: Clark to Dodd&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the paddling was memorable, but this day was really good. Gentle rolling waves were coming in, and we spent our time near rocks and seaweed as the waves rolled in. We saw many seals, fish and so much wildlife. Was a real west coast treat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9688896835&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stopped at Dodd and found the beach is really hard to camp at, there’s no campsites near the toilet, everything is shade and on a cloudy day pretty much sucked. So although we had “reserved” Dodd, we just went on to Hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9688896798&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we had to be at the lodge at 9:15am the next morning, being closer to the lodge, made life a little easier the next day too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;day-5-hand-to-lodge&quot;&gt;Day 5: Hand to Lodge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early start and back to the lodge and reverse the process we had on the way out, oh and dump a pile of water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9693372968&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were able to get the Highway 4 point by the 1pm opening of the road, meaning we were able to get to the ferry in time for a late afternoon ferry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;overall&quot;&gt;Overall&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Broken islands are just beautiful and a relaxing and amazing way to enjoy the west coast of Vancouver Island. Paddling around amazing islands full of wildlife with towering mountains in the background is wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>West Coast Trail - Second Time</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2023-07-31-west-coast-trail/"/>
<updated>2023-07-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/west-coast-trail</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This year I was able to do the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pc.gc.ca/en/pn-np/bc/pacificrim/activ/SCO-WCT&quot;&gt;West Coast Trail&lt;/a&gt; again. &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2022-06-25-west-coast-trail/&quot;&gt;Last time&lt;/a&gt; I did it solo, this year I was able to go with a friend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;👉 &lt;a href=&quot;https://pcweb.azureedge.net/-/media/pn-np/bc/pacificrim/WET4/visit/PDF/2019-WCT-Map_EN.pdf&quot;&gt;Map of the trail as a PDF&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going into the trail last year, I was quite anxious about what I was getting into - especially given the number of evacuations that occur and the reputation it has. This year I wasn’t worried at all, I’d done lots of hiking before and knew what was in store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After completing the trail last year, I’d realised that many people from around the world do the trail with vary levels of physical fitness and preparedness. Living in North Vancouver and hiking here all year round, I basically hike in the same conditions as the trail all year round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I meet people on the trail from every part of the world, they just don’t get that chance to practice or prepare for the conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I had more time and travelling with a friend had more opportunity to enjoy and share the experience. Last time I completed in 5 days, this time we aimed for 6 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-there-and-direction&quot;&gt;Getting there and Direction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the same as last year and doing south 👉 north again. I don’t think I’d ever want to do north 👉 south.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-one-gordon-river-to-camper-bay&quot;&gt;Day one: Gordon River to Camper Bay&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;18.47km in 8h 23m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve had one of the driest summers on record and haven’t seen rain for months. So naturally, it rained on us, a lot. It started off with the West Coast fog and drizzle and got worse and worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like last year we got to the Thrasher’s junction and realised that we’d have to put up the tents in the rain and basically sit in them for the rest of the day. Doing the boulder field around Owen Point in the rain the next day didn’t appeal either as it would be really slippy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we did what I did last year and went straight on inland to Camper Bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9545741591&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s when it really started rain. Everything became muddy and slippy and it feels more like jungle parkour with 30lb backpacks on muddy slippy trails than I hike. We didn’t see a single other person until Campers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a tough, wet and hard day. It stopped raining at the end, so fortunately we could set up in Campers in the dry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We heard there were 4 evacuations from Thrashers and 2 from Walbran - damaged ankles, damaged wrists, and hypothermia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; last year the exact same watch recorded 13.35km for this exact same part of the trail. I’m not sure where the extra 5km or so came from 🤷‍♂&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-two-camper-bay-to-walbran&quot;&gt;Day two: Camper Bay to Walbran&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;12.35km in 7h 47m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This day was super hard too, it rained on and off all the time we were hiking. It features lots of logs, broken boardwalks, mud and so many of the worst ladders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9545741595&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not all bad - it’s also got the marsh which is a lovely part of the trail. It’s flat and you get a nice view across the marsh. These last two days for me are so indicative of the trail, you really get into the rainforest and it’s just wonderful. Many huge old growth trees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arriving at Walbran was wonderful, the sun had come through after 2 days of rain and it lit up the forest in bright green. We dropped our backpacks on the beach and just soaked in the heat - before unpacking everything to dry out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-three-walbran-to-cribbs&quot;&gt;Day three: Walbran to Cribbs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;12.43km in 5h&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was planned as an easier day. Most days we were up and moving by around 7:30am, so we’d aimed to be done after lunch and have a bit of a rest day to relax. It started off with a fog bank rolling in, which meant that we didn’t get much of a view, but it was still beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9545741448&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a small inland bit around Carmanah lighthouse, but most of this part of the trail is beach walking. Last year the lighthouses were closed, so I was glad to be able to go and checkout the lighthouse grounds. Unfortunately the view was just fog 😢&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time we got to Cribbs the sun had come out. We set up our tents on the beach and then basically enjoyed the sun - and we got a bit sunburnt 😀&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A real highlight was a grey whale that decided to spend some time playing in the sea right off the rocky beach. About 20 metres away from the rock we were standing on, a grey whale spent 30 minutes or more hanging out - probably rubbing against the barnacles and rocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the last two tough days hiking in the rain, spirits were restored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to the people who kept turning up in camp from the North saying “long day, what a long day…” you’ve got some long ones coming up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-four-cribbs-to-tsusiat&quot;&gt;Day four: Cribbs to Tsusiat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;18.24km to 5h 24m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spacing of where to camp on the West Coast Trail remains due to the lack of camping between Cribbs and Tsusiat, so it does mean that this day is a long one, with shorter days either side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beaches in this section are gravel and they are hard to walk on. I’ve got no idea how to prepare for them, there’s nothing like this on any other hike. Gravel is soft and slips, because the beach is sloped consistently one way, my left knee started to hurt more on this bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9545741560&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, it was foggy, limiting the views. The drought was in evidence at the waterfall, which was much, much smaller than last year. The fog didn’t really lift, just coming thicker. But hey, we got to walk through the sea arch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multiple whales hung around by the campsite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-five-tsusiat-to-michigan&quot;&gt;Day five: Tsusiat to Michigan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;13.90km in 5h 28m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another scenic section with forest sections and some of the more gravelly beaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9545741476&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I felt that we were full on enjoying the trail, knowing that we’d pretty much completed the trail. We chatted to people who’d been moving at the same pace as us. The sun was strong, there was no fog and we ended up camping in the forest to avoid the heat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Michigan there were even more whales hanging out. Just watching the headland further out, we could see so many spouts of water coming up, that weren’t sure how many there were. A bunch of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michigan has nice views back to the headlands along the trail. It looks like such a long way. When we found out that the headland we could see was actually Bonilla Point (before Cribbs), we realised how far we’d come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-six-michigan-to-pachena&quot;&gt;Day six: Michigan to Pachena&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;12.91km in 3h 50m&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last easy bit of the trail. We left early and ended up at Pachena early and had to just sit on the beautiful sandy beach in the sun for a couple of hours waiting for the bus to take us home. Camping at Michigan feels like you’ve done the trail, but ending up on Pachena beach really is the home coming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9545741348&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The highlight of this part of trail are the lighthouse and sea lion rock. We got a nice chance to chat to the lighthouse keeper. Sadly there were no sea lions on the rock, they’d all migrated somewhere else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything I said last time &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2022-06-25-west-coast-trail/&quot;&gt;still holds&lt;/a&gt;. This is a beautiful trail in an amazing part of the world. I ❤️ this part of the world a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would do it every year if the opportunity came up. If I had to make a choice between this trail and another one in the world, I’d like to explore more of the world. Living nearby and it being relatively easy for me to organise, makes it a tempting thing to just keep doing again and again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Waking up at home on Sunday morning, I missed not being on the West Coast Trail. Missed waking up in my tent, making my breakfast, sitting watching the whales from the beach and looking forward to a day of hiking. That’s probably a good sign that I enjoyed my trip.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>GitOps</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2023-06-21-gitops/"/>
<updated>2023-06-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/gitops</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I went to the Vancouver DevOps Meetup, which was my first in person meetup in a long time. Didn’t know a single person there, but it was good to see people talking about interesting. Also thank you Best Buy for the pair of Airpods I won in the door prize raffle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The really interesting part for me was the &lt;a href=&quot;https://about.gitlab.com/topics/gitops/&quot;&gt;talk on GitOps&lt;/a&gt;, which basically is doing everything through Git. This was one of my favourite things at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, which didn’t use the name GitOps (as far as I’m aware) but did everything through GitHub as either code or issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Want to change DNS settings? Create a pull request.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Want to spin up a new service? Drop in a pull request with the configuration changes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Want to hire someone? Open an issue.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Want to re-organize and change teams? Create a pull request.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Want access to a new service, or remove access? Create a pull request.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All GitHub infrastructure was managed in GitHub. Configuration for services were stored in Git. To change something, you created a pull request with the changes. It would get reviewed by the appropriate teams. When the pull request is merged, then CI would kick off a new deployment with the changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting everything into GitHub providing a consistent interface that everyone understood, a consistent notification and review interface, an audit log and so on. This would be consistent across all the tooling. The power of this consistency here can’t be understated. If you don’t use this approach you are stuck on the learning curve as you figure out the UI, the API, the terminology and so on. That’s removed by having it all in one place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, it’s not perfect since often tooling needs to be built to allow this to happen. File formats and configuration will vary across teams and tools, so sometimes it’s not completely obvious what changes need to be made. Sometimes deploys would happen automatically, sometimes you need to run commands - that sort of thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, it’s important to ensure that deploys are easy and easy to rollback with appropriate tooling and reviews are in place to ensure that something terrible doesn’t happen. No-one wants to send in PR and accidentally break the main DNS entries for GitHub (as an example).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was one of the cooler things about working at GitHub and I missed it at other places.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Trip report - Juan de Fuca</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2023-06-20-juan-de-fuca/"/>
<updated>2023-06-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/juan-de-fuca</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The Juan de Fuca trail runs from Jordan River up to Port Renfrew on the West Coast of Vancouver Island. It’s in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bcparks.ca/juan-de-fuca-park/&quot;&gt;Juan de Fuca park&lt;/a&gt; and runs 47km from one end to the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comparisons with the West Coast Trail are common because the West Coast Trail starts at Port Renfrew and heads further north. In fact, sitting in the pub at the end of the trail, you can see where the entrance to the West Coast Trail is. There are four trail heads on the Juan de Fuca Trail and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://trailbus.com/&quot;&gt;trail bus&lt;/a&gt; will drop you off at them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-there&quot;&gt;Getting there&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a note that, with one brief exception on the way back &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, I got there and back without using a car, from North Vancouver. So that meant a bus, a bus, a ferry (seabus), a train (the skytrain) to Bridgeport station, a bus, a ferry (BC ferries) and a bus to get to downtown Victoria. Then I stayed the night at a hotel &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and took the &lt;a href=&quot;https://trailbus.com/&quot;&gt;trail bus&lt;/a&gt; in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took about 2.5 hours to get to the ferry terminal. It takes an hour by car, plus all the waiting around, so that really surprised at how fast, easy and cheap it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cycling there was something I considered, but riding from North Vancouver to the ferry terminal is horrendous and dangerous on the best of days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Total cost: $2.50 (transit in Victoria), $4.45 (two zones on translink), $19.20 (bc ferry), $50 (trail bus)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trail bus is the expensive part of the whole trip, if you’ve got more people and vehicle, the cost of the trail bus can quickly outweigh the cost of the ferry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-1-china-beach-to-chin-beach&quot;&gt;Day 1: China beach to Chin beach&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distance:&lt;/strong&gt; 19.39km&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 8h 08m&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elevation:&lt;/strong&gt; 988m up 📈 and the same down 📉&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9229033558&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps one of the more confusing naming schemes out there, but this was China beach to Chin beach. The trail bus dropped me off at around 8:30 and after a quick repack, I took off for the first campsite, 9km north along the trail. The weather was just great for this day, nice and sunny with a light breeze coming off the sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trail follows the coast and so you get the absolute delight that is the west coast, mild temperatures, lovely beaches and so on. I hit the first campsite, 9km in at about 11am or so, which is way to early to camp. At that point I decided to just press on the next 11km - knowing that the next 11km was some of the hardest on the trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would have settled for a campsite earlier than Chin beach, at 21km (according to the map &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;), the last few km were a hard push. The terrain is just continuously steep up and down as the trail goes up and down each creek. I gained almost 1000m, but ended up at sea level. The terrain is steep and also dry and dusty and technical to walk up and down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every campsite has tent pads, which for people with hiking pole tents, like me, not ideal. Fortunately that first night I found a lovely pad free spot with a good place for my hammock on the beach. I was very happy and tired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/IMG_0191.JPG&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-2-chin-beach-to-little-kuitsche-creek&quot;&gt;Day 2: Chin beach to Little Kuitsche Creek&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distance:&lt;/strong&gt; 11.70km&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 5h 07m&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elevation:&lt;/strong&gt; 552 up 📈 and the same down 📉&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9229033403&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On day two, I noticed that I’d overdone it on day one and I had a slow and sluggish start to the day, but was still able to press on and glad when I finished. This day was easier than yesterday, mostly. It still starts off tough with lots of up and down and then a reasonable sized (200m) hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then you come out on to the glorious Sombrio beach, complete with a waterfall falling onto the beach, a whale feeding and quite a lot of people. Sombrio beach is also a trail head, with road access so there’s quite a lot of people which is a bit of a shame. But a few km either way from the beach and it predictably thins out again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The campsite is not a beach campsite, its up in the trees. Water access is close, but down a hill that’s under construction and I found a bit of a challenge in my flip flops. Time to give up on flip flops as camp shoes and go for something more rugged. A super sunny day with hiking on the beach, fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-3-little-kuitsche-creek-to-port-renfrew&quot;&gt;Day 3: Little Kuitsche Creek to Port Renfrew&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distance:&lt;/strong&gt; 16.51km&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 5h 05m&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elevation:&lt;/strong&gt; 481 up 📈 and the same down 📉&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9229038107&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the easiest part of the trail, but is still lots of steep up and down. There were actually a few more flat bits on this one, which was nice. It turns out, that most people doing the trail aim for four days of hiking (I combined the first two days into one by going straight to Chin beach) so that meant I kept seeing the same people on the trail and campsites, which was nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weather was overcast, with bright spots in the afternoon, a lovely west coast day. Once you hit Botanical Beach, it’s really easy and flat with wide trails and lots of people. I did a hike around Botany Bay and then had to hike the 4km or so into town on road. After all that up and down, that was a nice break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few beers and a veggie burger in the pub at the end of the road, and I was ready to hop in the trail bus and repeat my trip home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve had a very hot, dry spring so far and so there were muddy parts on the trail, but they were few and far between. There was much less mud than on the West Coast Trail which I did &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2022-06-25-west-coast-trail/&quot;&gt;mid-June 2022&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone is going to compare this to the West Coast Trail, because it’s right there. In comparison, the Juan de Fuca trail is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More steep elevation changes, but no ladders.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Less muddy, but that might have been due to weather.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shorter, but more access points.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Less beach walking and much, much more forest walking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main difference is beaches, once you’ve got past Walbran Creek (if you are heading north), then you’ll find lots and lots of beach and flat hiking. That’s because as you go further north, the coast is no longer protected by the Olympic peninsula and over the millennia, waves crashing in off the Pacific have created fantastic beaches to explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This marked the end of my boots. I bought Scarpa boots last year and they have completely fallen apart. There were holes all the way through both sides, at the end of each beach I had to stop and empty the beach out of my boots. A post about my new boots soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was also my first trip with 100% homemade meals, they worked pretty well and helped me save money without having to buy expensive pre-made dehydrated meals. Will post about that soon also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting there and back without a car was cool and would recommend it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;My friend who was kind enough to give me a bed for the night on the way back, drove me home from the bus stop. Next morning I walked back to the bus and continued that way. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The bus leaves at 6:45am and so I wanted a hotel downtown to make it easy to get to. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;My GPS and the trail signs did not agree and were always a couple of km out. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
</entry>

<entry>
<title>Trip report - Stein Valley</title>
<link href="https://mckay.pub/2023-06-19-stein-valley/"/>
<updated>2023-06-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
<id>https://mckay.pub/stein-valley</id>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;May in Vancouver means that many mountains are still covered in snow and its not good snow. Layers of mucky half melted snow and ice that’s hard to walk on, with repeated fall throughs and such. Other places tend to be not quite warm enough yet, so my friend and I kick started our backpacking with &lt;a href=&quot;https://bcparks.ca/explore/parkpgs/stein_val/&quot;&gt;a trip to the Stein&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, the main reason for doing the Stein in May is that it’s really warm. Like hot. It’s way too hot to do in the summer. With temperatures in May around 30c, it’s amazing. Once you get into the trees, by that raging river, it’s somewhere special.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went there in &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2022-06-25-stein-valley/&quot;&gt;June last year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-one-heading-into-the-stein&quot;&gt;Day one: Heading into the Stein&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distance:&lt;/strong&gt; 8.58km&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 3h 35m&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elevation:&lt;/strong&gt; 303m&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9109569545&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The downside of going at this time of year is that the spring melt is in full swing. The quick rapid rise in temperature caused a lot of melt and once again we had to take the pipeline bridge across into the valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again the heat and lack of shade for that 4km until you get into the Stein valley properly is quite intense and something that really drained us. This year we were carrying much &lt;a href=&quot;https://mckay.pub/2022-06-25-packing-light/&quot;&gt;smaller and lighter backpacks fortunately&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again we camped at Devils Staircase campground, again with no-one else there. Last year we tried heading further north into the Stein, but hit a problem 1km north with a gully that was badly washed out that I just couldn’t cross. This year I went on ahead and it was much more doable - so we knew were good to go for the next day and head further into the Stein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-two-devils-staircase-to-the-suspension-bridge&quot;&gt;Day two: Devils Staircase to the Suspension bridge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9116469041&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distance:&lt;/strong&gt; 19.58km&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 7h 38m&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elevation:&lt;/strong&gt; 617m&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always wanted to get as far up the Stein Valley as I could, but something always prevented this. So with the goal in mind of getting to the suspension bridge we consolidated into one light backpack with suitable supplies and head off to the suspension bridge, 20km up the valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a wonderful day of hiking with light backpacks and exploring parts of the valley I’d never visited before. There were parts of this valley that were just fabulous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw this beauty in a tree, we think its a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pacific_marten&quot;&gt;Pacific Marten&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/pacific-marten-1.png&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/files/pacific-marten-2.png&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the top there are a few washouts that resulted in a bit of treacherous scrambling, but nothing too bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then reached the suspension bridge and that’s as far as you can go since its closed from beyond there as a result of damage in the 2021 floods (&lt;a href=&quot;https://bcparks.ca/stein-valley-nlakapamux-heritage-park/&quot;&gt;as per the website&lt;/a&gt;). I’m not sure if it will ever open again, but if it does the Stein Traverse is still high on my bucket list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We returned back to the Devils Staircase campground and found we were joined by a couple of other campers for the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;day-three-leaving-the-stein&quot;&gt;Day three: Leaving the Stein&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;strava-embed-placeholder&quot; data-embed-type=&quot;activity&quot; data-embed-id=&quot;9120298291&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script src=&quot;https://strava-embeds.com/embed.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distance:&lt;/strong&gt; 7.94km&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 2h 19m&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elevation:&lt;/strong&gt; 263m&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the last day, we woke up to a little bit of moisture in the air. There were even a couple of raindrops. The valley just became green and alive and vibrant, such a change from the heat beaten land before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Light backpacks and just 6c weather made for a nice hike back out of the valley, across the bridge and back to the car. It only took just over 2 hours to complete. In comparison, last year when we did this in what felt like blazing heat took 3.5 hours, with lots of stopping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Stein has become our first trip of year and we’ll probably do it again next year. I know I’ll be spending the long winter months looking forward to it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>

</feed>
